<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: web | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/web/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2016-01-13T21:36:51-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Write a Python Web Framework]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/11/21/write-a-python-web-framework/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-21T05:17:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/11/21/write-a-python-web-framework</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You don&rsquo;t have to use Django, Flask, Cherrypy, or even web.py.  It&rsquo;s
all about WSGI.  Guess what.  Everything you need is already built
into Python.  After all, Python promises &ldquo;batteries included.&rdquo;</p>

<p><a href="http://funwithlinux.net/2015/11/how-to-write-a-python-web-framework-from-scratch/">How To Write a Python Web Framework From Scratch</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Edward Tuft CSS]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/11/14/edward-tuft-css/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-14T21:32:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/11/14/edward-tuft-css</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is an interesting take on style, typesetting, publishing, and
CSS.  I don&rsquo;t agree with all of it but there are some nice ideas here
and the page/approach is very nice looking.</p>

<p>The main thing I disagree with is Tufte&rsquo;s strong preference for text
and prose rather than lists.  I think this is highly dependent on a
person&rsquo;s individual taste.  Also I&rsquo;m not convinced that a person who&rsquo;s
scanning an email message or document will absorb a paragraph of prose
as well as a bullet list.</p>

<p><a href="https://edwardtufte.github.io/tufte-css/">Tuft CSS</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Poor Performance of Javascript on Android]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/10/01/poor-performance-of-javascript-on-android/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-01T06:05:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/10/01/poor-performance-of-javascript-on-android</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In a posted discussion Jeff Atwood claims that, &ldquo;For several years now
we&rsquo;ve tracked the fact that, over time from 2012 onward, Android
JavaScript performance has become wildly divergent from iOS JavaScript
performance. And not in a good way.&rdquo;</p>

<p>He says:</p>

<blockquote><p>This is the benchmark most representative of Discourse performance,
and the absolute best known Android score for this benchmark is right
at ~400ms on a Samsung Galaxy S6. That doesn&rsquo;t seem too bad until you
compare..</p>

<p>iPhone 5 → 340ms<br />
iPhone 5s → 175ms<br />
iPhone 6 → 140ms<br />
iPad Air 2 → 120ms<br />
iPhone 6s → 60-70ms</p>

<p>In a nutshell, the fastest known Android device available today &mdash; and
there are millions of Android devices much slower than that out there
&mdash; performs 5× slower than a new iPhone 6s, and a little worse than a
2012 era iPhone 5 in Ember. How depressing.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="https://meta.discourse.org/t/the-state-of-javascript-on-android-in-2015-is-poor/33889">The State of JavaScript on Android in 2015 is… poor</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Indie Web]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/17/indie-web/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-17T08:22:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/17/indie-web</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since I first began the 30-day blogging challenge the indie web
movement was on my list of topics to discus.  My thinking on
it, and related topics, is still unsettled.  I&rsquo;ve read some and, well,
read some more.  Kevin Marks frequently appears on the Twit network
and particularly on <em>This Week in Google</em>, and has talked about the
indie web on many occasions.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a brief and early poll on where I am so far.  I like the basic
principle of owning all of your content.  That&rsquo;s the foundation of
this very site, this blog.  I don&rsquo;t like strongly coupling my various
identities across sites, not that strongly.  I prefer that they be
weakly coupled, if at all.  I&rsquo;m not that interested in discussions,
engagement and feedback.  At least not in the usual way they occur on
the web.</p>

<p>Microformats comprise a clever and intriguing idea.  I think there&rsquo;s value
in this evolved approach to (this part of) the so-called semantic
web.</p>

<p>The microformats movement has eschewed email and gone to using IRC
(Internet Relay Chat) and a wiki for their communication.  This hits
at the communication problems that I spend a lot of my
internet-thinking time on.  Email seems terribly inadequate in many
ways and yet insists being the best fit for many needs, particularly
when Gmail is used.  I agree with not using email for long messages or
long documents&mdash;I&rsquo;ve adopted a similar approach to communication.
(For long documents and messages I email a Google document instead of
a long email message).</p>

<p>I loathe using IRC.  That in itself is worth at least one long blog
post.  We use it at work since I&rsquo;ve been unable to stave off the push
by the millennials (plus or minus) there to use IRC.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s a very nice &ldquo;indie web in a box,&rdquo; With Known, which you can
even get a hosted account with.  At first, that seems anti-indie-web,
but it&rsquo;s all very well done.  The source is open and you can start on
their servers then move onto your own when you wish, similar to using
Wordpress.</p>

<p>So that&rsquo;s a quick update.  There should be more to come.</p>

<p><a href="http://indiewebcamp.com/">Indie Web Camp</a><br />
<a href="http://microformats.org/">Microformats</a><br />
<a href="http://www.kevinmarks.com/">Kevin Marks</a><br />
<a href="http://twit.tv/">Twit.tv</a><br />
<a href="https://withknown.com/">Known</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
