<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: email | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/email/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2014-11-08T23:38:49-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Inbox: First Impression]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/28/inbox-first-impression/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-28T06:01:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/28/inbox-first-impression</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 18.1</a></p>

<p>I just set up Inbox on a very old, in fact my oldest, earliest, Gmail
account.  Come to think of it, I guess that&rsquo;s appropriate in a way.
Here, briefly, are my very first impressions.</p>

<h2>Short Version</h2>

<p>Inbox is like the dead mouse your cat brings to you.  Thanks but
that&rsquo;s not exactly what I wanted and it&rsquo;s not quite useful to me,
though I appreciate the work you&rsquo;ve done.  I may even be impressed by
it.  It&rsquo;s true I could use something to eat right now, maybe even
something about that size, but that isn&rsquo;t it.</p>

<!-- More -->


<h2>Slightly More Detail</h2>

<p>Minimalist email messages:  Yes.  I like this idea of messages that
can look like tweets but still, maybe, have support for long messages.
Really, though, I think long messages should be a document that is
emailed.</p>

<p>The card thing:  Bah.  I don&rsquo;t use Google Now and I don&rsquo;t want that
much help.</p>

<p>The todo list thing: Thumbs down.  I&rsquo;m in the fifth year of my
highly-evolved GTD system and I don&rsquo;t want help with this from my email
program.  I don&rsquo;t mind it being there, it looks like it would be a
great help for folks that <em>do</em> use email to manage their lives (what a
horrible, horrible concept, though).  There needs to be some way to
get all of those green check marks and todo-listness out of the email if you
don&rsquo;t want to see it there.  Where&rsquo;s the OFF switch??</p>

<p>The automatic grouping thing: Thumbs down again.  Similar to the
above, I&rsquo;ve had complete control of my email with filters and labels
for years.  I don&rsquo;t need help.  Please get your ideas of labels and
filters out of my email!</p>

<p>Finally, it&rsquo;s not really minimal.  Inbox looks minimal and simpler,
but really it sneaks in all of the above cruft.  A program that sort
of looked like Inbox, more minimalist than Gmail, but that didn&rsquo;t
impose a lot of complexity and stuff in return would be worth a closer
look.</p>

<p>I expect changes to Gmail itself along these lines and maybe then
there will be some settings switches (no doubt almost impossibly
buried) to turn some of these &ldquo;helpful&rdquo; features off.</p>

<p>And I should make clear that this is all from my personal point of
view.  For the vast masses, Inbox may be just what folks need so I&rsquo;m
not saying it shouldn&rsquo;t exist and may not be a huge hit.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll find ways to keep playing with Inbox but it will be a while
before I unleash it on the actual Gmail that I use.</p>

<h2>P.S.</h2>

<p>It sure looks like <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CICMxwgm274">Mailboxapp</a> introduced some two years ago.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Google's New Gmail Inbox]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/23/googles-new-email-inbox/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-23T05:48:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/23/googles-new-email-inbox</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 13</a></p>

<p>Google is now making available to all users, albeit by invitation only
for now, Inbox, it&rsquo;s new Gmail app.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve barely seen it but initially I&rsquo;m a bit skeptical.  There&rsquo;s a
focus on automatically bundling  your email for you and managing todo
lists.  I already manage my email with a strong and extensive set of
filters and I manage todo lists and things like that via my
implementation of David Allen&rsquo;s GTD.  So I&rsquo;m probably not an intended
user.</p>

<p>It will probably look compelling.  One thing I do like are email-like
systems where the messages look more like short messages in a chat
session rather than email.  When I think about this as a good idea
and then look back at Gmail, it really already goes a long way in that
direction.  The messages in a conversation are nicely minimal.</p>

<p>Inbox also seems to have a little floating circle, in this case a red
dot. This little floating circle, that is both highly annoying and in
the way as far as I&rsquo;m concerned, seems to be a popular gimmick lately.
Witness the little chat circle in Facebook&rsquo;s mobile apps.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m being highly critical of software I&rsquo;ve never even seen, so I may
be wrong about Inbox.  I do like the idea of an even nicer and somehow
simpler email application but I want full control over what&rsquo;s
happening.  And I don&rsquo;t need a new Gmail.  It&rsquo;s actually nearly
perfect already.  I fear that ongoing attempts to move it forward will
begin to degrade what I like about Gmail.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.theverge.com/2014/10/22/7041227/google-inbox-hands-on-this-feels-like-the-future-of-email">Using Google Inbox: this feels like the future of email</a> at the Verge.<br />
<a href="http://readwrite.com/2014/10/22/google-inbox-deconstructing-email">Google May Be About To Blow Up Email With Its &ldquo;Inbox&rdquo; App</a> at Readwrite.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
