<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: email | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://daily.monolith149.com//blog/categories/email/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://daily.monolith149.com//"/>
  <updated>2016-10-01T00:18:39-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://daily.monolith149.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Whence The Chat Paradigm]]></title>
    <link href="http://daily.monolith149.com//blog/2015/09/30/whence-the-chat-paradigm/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-30T05:02:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://daily.monolith149.com//blog/2015/09/30/whence-the-chat-paradigm</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For some reason, the chat paradigm has become overly popular.  Internet
relay chat (IRC) was interesting in the mid-90s as a way to
communicate in an informal, unstructured sense.  However, I can&rsquo;t
believe it&rsquo;s still so popular.  Then we have Hipchat, Slack and
others.  What&rsquo;s the deal?</p>

<p>What is the utility of an endless scroll of mixed up and confused,
uncollated, blended conversations with no good way to determine their
topics or context?</p>

<p>Maybe it is the valid rebellion against email.  I thought for a while
that email had reached the end of its usefulness.  However, in my own
personal quest for a substitute, I&rsquo;ve reluctantly come to the
conclusion that email is the only workable, reliable solution.</p>

<p>Granted phone text messages are how I normally communicate with my
family.  Beyond my immediate family, family and friends are all on
Facebook.  One or two people still seem to use Google+ and, of course,
most Google employees.</p>

<p>Email has subjects, labels and excellent search.  It accommodates
messages of any length, including super short.</p>

<p>I do like the idea of minimal email and Google Inbox makes a valiant
attempt but I expect it to be squashed any minute as is the end of all
Google services, useful or not.  Ultimately, the native, plain
old Gmail is actually quite minimal when you really look at it.  Each
message in a conversation has the names of the people, a picture of
the sender and the message.  It looks like chat.</p>

<p>One personal change I&rsquo;ve made quietly over the past few months is to
drop all signatures including just signing my name on email messages.
The truth is we still have a compulsion to write an email message like
a letter or office memo, and not like a tweet or chat snippet.  I&rsquo;ll
still write in complete, hopefully correct, sentences with correct
spelling.  When corresponding with someone I don&rsquo;t often send email
to, then I&rsquo;m less familiar and will include my first name or full name
and maybe even a signature if it&rsquo;s a business message.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gmail Inbox Mistake]]></title>
    <link href="http://daily.monolith149.com//blog/2015/03/23/gmail-inbox-mistake/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-23T08:13:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://daily.monolith149.com//blog/2015/03/23/gmail-inbox-mistake</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well, that was a mistake.  To a large degree I really like Gmail&rsquo;s new
Inbox IOS app, and the desktop version doesn&rsquo;t look bad either.  I&rsquo;ve
used it on a rarely-used account and recently added in anther,
more-often-used account so I could try out more interaction.  I heard
someone on a podcast say, It doesn&rsquo;t really affect your regular Gmail
interface interactions so you can use both at the same time.  That
seemed to be the case to me, so I thought, okay, I&rsquo;ll just fire it up
on my main Gmail account.</p>

<p>That was a mistake.</p>

<p>So it does have an effect in a particular way.  I should have seen
it.  The Gmail model is to treat messages like to do items and mark
them as &ldquo;Done&rdquo; when you are finished with them, instead of marking
them as &ldquo;Read.&rdquo;  Marking as &ldquo;Read&rdquo; is still there but it&rsquo;s
independent.  Of course, &ldquo;Done&rdquo; is yet another label though it doesn&rsquo;t
show up in the list of labels so maybe it&rsquo;s more a kind of state.
However, you can search in the regular Gmail for &ldquo;label:done&rdquo; and it
will find your done messages.  (That&rsquo;s giving away the ending).</p>

<p>With the Inbox app, you can go through and use the little &ldquo;sweep&rdquo;
icons to sweep away large collections of messages as &ldquo;Done,&rdquo; all in
one, uh, swoop.  Fortunately, it didn&rsquo;t seem to let me do more than
one month at a time.  I finally got tired of that, but then went back
to check the Gmail view.</p>

<p>My mistake was thinking &ldquo;Done&rdquo; in the Inbox app meant &ldquo;mark as Read&rdquo;
in the Gmail app, which was wrong.  So I&rsquo;d moved hundreds of messages
out of my Inbox to who knows where.  Well now we all know they no
longer had the Inbox label and now had the Done label or state.  (And,
yes, I&rsquo;m now going to stop using the quotes around all of these states
and labels).  Also, as we all should know, in Gmail, you don&rsquo;t move
anything but only ever add and remove labels.</p>

<p>Well, that was a big change.  Part of my Gmail organization, written
about recently, is how I keep some things in the Inbox and some bypass
it and are only in labels.</p>

<p>Now I&rsquo;d moved the Inbox-only items completely out of site, read or
unread.</p>

<p>Thinking quickly, too quickly, and acting too quickly, I realized I
could try the search &ldquo;label:done&rdquo; and find them all.  So I just took
that list, clicked the upper left box to check all on the screen, then
checked the little link that always pops up that says, &ldquo;Select all
messages that match this search&hellip;&rdquo; to select <em>all</em> of the Done
items.  Then I just added the Inbox label back to them.</p>

<p>Except now I move a lot of messages (again, hundreds) into the Inbox
that formerly my filter had kept from ever being in the Inbox.  My
levels of email importance, and the underlying sorting, are something
like this:</p>

<ul>
<li>Only in the Inbox</li>
<li>In the Inbox but with a label</li>
<li>Only in a label (not in the Inbox)</li>
<li>Only in a label and marked as read on delivery</li>
</ul>


<p>I should have included that list in my previous post.</p>

<p>I was finally able to mostly clean up this mess by selecting the
various labels, select all of the messages, which now had the Inbox
label, and click the Archive operation.  Archive is Gmail-speak for
special operation that just removes the Inbox label.</p>

<p>I should never have believed that the Inbox app would be harmless and
wouldn&rsquo;t have some effect on my regular Gmail account.  Gmail
desperately wants to manage my email for me (to the point of just
taking it over) and, as much as I really like Gmail and think it&rsquo;s by
far the best email solution, I have to beat it down hard with a big
stick every time it raises it&rsquo;s head and tries to attack my email with
unwanted help.  It&rsquo;s exhausting.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s a metaphor for Google in general and will probably eventually
lead, in some large part, to their downfall.</p>

<p>I still like a lot about the Inbox app and it&rsquo;s interface and I&rsquo;ll
keep experimenting with a much less important account.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dealing with Email]]></title>
    <link href="http://daily.monolith149.com//blog/2015/02/23/dealing-with-email/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-23T06:18:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://daily.monolith149.com//blog/2015/02/23/dealing-with-email</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve used email since the beginning of the early days of the
Internet&rsquo;s explosion in the mid-80s.  It&rsquo;s gone through quite an
evolution as have my methods of managing what is probably a massive
flood of incoming information.  Since my methods work pretty well for
me, I really wouldn&rsquo;t know.</p>

<p>Lately I hear people either discussing how they fight their huge
battle with email, sometimes winning and sometimes losing, and I&rsquo;m
struck by how often they seem to miss some techniques I&rsquo;ve taken for granted
for years now.</p>

<p>In my current job I spend about 20 minutes reading email in the
morning.  After that, all of the email labels (basically folders if
that&rsquo;s the paradigm you use) are read, I&rsquo;m at what is sometimes called
&ldquo;inbox zero.&rdquo;  Throughout the rest of the day, I watch for occasional
emails from my team and the chain of people I report to.  That&rsquo;s
basically it.  I never see an email message that I wouldn&rsquo;t want to.</p>

<p>Here are the main techniques that I&rsquo;ve found success in using.</p>

<!-- More -->


<h2>Use Gmail</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve used Gmail since it came out in 2004, both for personal and work
email.  In all that time, I&rsquo;ve never deleted an email message.  That
was an original idea of Gmail, you were never expected to.  Google&rsquo;s
email service effectively deals with spam so that&rsquo;s immediately out of
the equation.  I&rsquo;ve barely given a thought to spam in that many
years. I don&rsquo;t check my spam folder.  There were maybe two times when
I seemed to be missing a message and I found a false positive in
there, but that&rsquo;s it.</p>

<p>Some people seem to be mystified by or simply don&rsquo;t like the
conversation view.  I can&rsquo;t imagine why this is.  It&rsquo;s the most
effective and logical to view an exchange of messages.  The list of
&ldquo;messages&rdquo; (actually conversations) in a mailbox is immediately
shorter, you can see how many are unread by conversation, and the
snippets show you a bit of context.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve used or taken a careful look at most of the email programs,
interfaces and services over it&rsquo;s history, particularly in roles of
providing user support and also being a system administrator of email
servers.  Please take my word for this, conversations in Gmail is the
best way to read email.</p>

<h2>Use Filters and Labels</h2>

<p>I use lots of filters.  The filters themselves aren&rsquo;t terribly
complicated.  Usually they either filter by who the email is from (one
of my bosses), who it&rsquo;s to, typically an email list, e.g., my team,
and sometimes the subject line.</p>

<p>The filter usually skips the inbox which means the message won&rsquo;t
appear there.  (Gmail tip:  There is no inbox.  There&rsquo;s nothing but a
gigantic barrel of all of your email, but you typically view it by
labels on the email. &ldquo;Inbox&rdquo; is just another label.  So is
&ldquo;Spam&rdquo;. Etc.)  They usually go into a custom label and may be marked
as read or not.</p>

<p>When naming labels, I give them names so they are properly sorted in
the left hand column.  Important filters start with the letter A,
e.g., &ldquo;A Bosses&rdquo;, &ldquo;A Team&rdquo;, &ldquo;A Project XYZ.&rdquo;  The filters for those
labels won&rsquo;t be marked as read so I can see how many unread messages
there are from a boss, my team, on the project.</p>

<p>After that come some less important labels like &ldquo;B Some Other
Project&rdquo;, &ldquo;B Meeting X&rdquo;, etc.  Those might be unread or they might
actually be marked as read.  They don&rsquo;t show up as bold with an
unread count, but I can go look at that &ldquo;pile&rdquo; if I ever need to see
what&rsquo;s been going on there.  Similarly, there are a few labels
starting with &ldquo;C&rdquo; that are even farther down on the list.</p>

<p>Below those, and probably off the screen, are labels without a special
sorting letter in their name.  Usually all of those are marked as read
(by the filter when the email arrives) and chances are I&rsquo;ll never look
at them.  This is where things go like chatty notification services
which is effectively noise.  There maybe tens of thousands of messages
in these.  If there were some particular kinds of messages in there I
needed so see, lost in that noise, then that means writing a more
specific filter to put those messages in a more important label and
leaving them unread.</p>

<p>Finally, you can set each label to be shown or not.   If you mark it
as not shown, then it won&rsquo;t even be in the left-hand list  when you
scroll down.  At the end of the list it says &ldquo;More&rdquo; with a little
arrow.  You click that to extend the list with the rest of the
not-shown labels.  If there are labels of mail I don&rsquo;t even care to
remember the existence of, I don&rsquo;t need to be reminded they are there,
I put them in that list.  It&rsquo;s like the closet, or maybe even the
trash heap.</p>

<p>After all of the filtering is done, all that remains in my inbox is
the general, uncategorized email, that I need to ready on a daily
basis.  That&rsquo;s reduced down to the 20 or so messages I read each day.</p>

<h2>Read Selectively</h2>

<p>Now I can look at my labels in the morning and see what messages
are there.  There are maybe 10 labels I read each morning but I don&rsquo;t
go through each label reading messages one by one.</p>

<p>I read the reporting chain label, team mail, and then typically the
inbox next.  Note that I&rsquo;ve been a GTD advocate and user for some six
years, so, of course, I don&rsquo;t spend more than a couple of minutes on a
message.  If a message is a long read, or requires something to be
done, I add an item to my Next Actions list, or some appropriate
list.  I usually put a link back to the message in the action.</p>

<p>(Gmail tip:  You can refer back to any particular conversation/message
by copying the link from the browser.  That link will always work for
that message.  I typically just add a word &ldquo;[Email]&rdquo; and link the
&ldquo;Email&rdquo; part to the message so I can just click on it.)</p>

<p>So I might have one or two new actions.</p>

<p>(Gmail tip:  You can search using the search term &ldquo;label:<label name>
is:unread&rdquo; to see all of the unread messages in a label.   This also
works for seeing just the unread messages in your inbox, e.g.,
&ldquo;label:inbox is:unread&rdquo;.  If I click on a label, the &ldquo;label:<label
name>&rdquo; is already in the search box (because that&rsquo;s all clicking on a
label does, it does that search).  Then, clicking in the search box
drops down the &ldquo;is:unread&rdquo; added to it because it&rsquo;s been used before,
so no typing is needed.</p>

<p>For some chains, I just flip through the messages quickly to see what
their content is.  If there&rsquo;s not a need to read it then or maybe
ever, I don&rsquo;t.  This is different from just marking it as read.  I
still open and look at each message to be sure I know what it&rsquo;s about.</p>

<p>For some labels, I don&rsquo;t even do that.  I just open the label and look
at the conversation subjects and snippets.  Often that&rsquo;s enough,
because this label already represents reduced importance.  Then I just
check all of the boxes by checking the one box up at the top of the
list, go to the &ldquo;More&rdquo; menu button and select &ldquo;Mark all as read.&rdquo;
Done for that label.</p>

<p>For the rest of the day I keep my team&rsquo;s label selected and ignore
most of the other labels, and the inbox, even though they accumulate
new, unread messages through the day.  They&rsquo;ll be dealt with next
morning.</p>

<h2>Concluding</h2>

<p>So, the basic idea is to tune the incoming email so I only see what I
need to see, and only read what&rsquo;s important.  I&rsquo;ve found that most of
this tuning can be done in four to six weeks of a new job, then there
is a decreasing number of tweaks through out six months to a year.
Beyond that, I only tweak a filter or add a label every three to six
months probably.</p>

<p>Some readers here may note that Gmail will automatically prioritize
your messages and even sort it into major categories to help you read
it.  I&rsquo;ve heard that these seem to work quite well.  I actually turn
all of those features off since my email handling is already finely
tuned.</p>

<p>Note what I don&rsquo;t worry about:  mail quotas, deciding what messages to
delete, organizing folders, spam.  Those are problems more than 10
years in my past.  I&rsquo;m amazed people still have to battle them on a
daily basis.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Inbox: First Impression]]></title>
    <link href="http://daily.monolith149.com//blog/2014/10/28/inbox-first-impression/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-28T06:01:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://daily.monolith149.com//blog/2014/10/28/inbox-first-impression</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 18.1</a></p>

<p>I just set up Inbox on a very old, in fact my oldest, earliest, Gmail
account.  Come to think of it, I guess that&rsquo;s appropriate in a way.
Here, briefly, are my very first impressions.</p>

<h2>Short Version</h2>

<p>Inbox is like the dead mouse your cat brings to you.  Thanks but
that&rsquo;s not exactly what I wanted and it&rsquo;s not quite useful to me,
though I appreciate the work you&rsquo;ve done.  I may even be impressed by
it.  It&rsquo;s true I could use something to eat right now, maybe even
something about that size, but that isn&rsquo;t it.</p>

<!-- More -->


<h2>Slightly More Detail</h2>

<p>Minimalist email messages:  Yes.  I like this idea of messages that
can look like tweets but still, maybe, have support for long messages.
Really, though, I think long messages should be a document that is
emailed.</p>

<p>The card thing:  Bah.  I don&rsquo;t use Google Now and I don&rsquo;t want that
much help.</p>

<p>The todo list thing: Thumbs down.  I&rsquo;m in the fifth year of my
highly-evolved GTD system and I don&rsquo;t want help with this from my email
program.  I don&rsquo;t mind it being there, it looks like it would be a
great help for folks that <em>do</em> use email to manage their lives (what a
horrible, horrible concept, though).  There needs to be some way to
get all of those green check marks and todo-listness out of the email if you
don&rsquo;t want to see it there.  Where&rsquo;s the OFF switch??</p>

<p>The automatic grouping thing: Thumbs down again.  Similar to the
above, I&rsquo;ve had complete control of my email with filters and labels
for years.  I don&rsquo;t need help.  Please get your ideas of labels and
filters out of my email!</p>

<p>Finally, it&rsquo;s not really minimal.  Inbox looks minimal and simpler,
but really it sneaks in all of the above cruft.  A program that sort
of looked like Inbox, more minimalist than Gmail, but that didn&rsquo;t
impose a lot of complexity and stuff in return would be worth a closer
look.</p>

<p>I expect changes to Gmail itself along these lines and maybe then
there will be some settings switches (no doubt almost impossibly
buried) to turn some of these &ldquo;helpful&rdquo; features off.</p>

<p>And I should make clear that this is all from my personal point of
view.  For the vast masses, Inbox may be just what folks need so I&rsquo;m
not saying it shouldn&rsquo;t exist and may not be a huge hit.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll find ways to keep playing with Inbox but it will be a while
before I unleash it on the actual Gmail that I use.</p>

<h2>P.S.</h2>

<p>It sure looks like <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CICMxwgm274">Mailboxapp</a> introduced some two years ago.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Google's New Gmail Inbox]]></title>
    <link href="http://daily.monolith149.com//blog/2014/10/23/googles-new-email-inbox/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-23T05:48:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://daily.monolith149.com//blog/2014/10/23/googles-new-email-inbox</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 13</a></p>

<p>Google is now making available to all users, albeit by invitation only
for now, Inbox, it&rsquo;s new Gmail app.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve barely seen it but initially I&rsquo;m a bit skeptical.  There&rsquo;s a
focus on automatically bundling  your email for you and managing todo
lists.  I already manage my email with a strong and extensive set of
filters and I manage todo lists and things like that via my
implementation of David Allen&rsquo;s GTD.  So I&rsquo;m probably not an intended
user.</p>

<p>It will probably look compelling.  One thing I do like are email-like
systems where the messages look more like short messages in a chat
session rather than email.  When I think about this as a good idea
and then look back at Gmail, it really already goes a long way in that
direction.  The messages in a conversation are nicely minimal.</p>

<p>Inbox also seems to have a little floating circle, in this case a red
dot. This little floating circle, that is both highly annoying and in
the way as far as I&rsquo;m concerned, seems to be a popular gimmick lately.
Witness the little chat circle in Facebook&rsquo;s mobile apps.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m being highly critical of software I&rsquo;ve never even seen, so I may
be wrong about Inbox.  I do like the idea of an even nicer and somehow
simpler email application but I want full control over what&rsquo;s
happening.  And I don&rsquo;t need a new Gmail.  It&rsquo;s actually nearly
perfect already.  I fear that ongoing attempts to move it forward will
begin to degrade what I like about Gmail.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.theverge.com/2014/10/22/7041227/google-inbox-hands-on-this-feels-like-the-future-of-email">Using Google Inbox: this feels like the future of email</a> at the Verge.<br />
<a href="http://readwrite.com/2014/10/22/google-inbox-deconstructing-email">Google May Be About To Blow Up Email With Its &ldquo;Inbox&rdquo; App</a> at Readwrite.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
