<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: email | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/email/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2017-04-01T06:07:54-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Danger: Effective Gmail Phishing]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2017/01/16/danger-effective-gmail-phishing/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-16T22:07:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2017/01/16/danger-effective-gmail-phishing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&ldquo;Wide Impact: Highly Effective Gmail Phishing Technique Being Exploited
by Mark Maunder&rdquo;</p>

<p>This is pretty insidious.  You get a message from someome you know.
It has an attachment.  You try to open it but up pops a Gmail login
page asking you to enter your password again for security.  That Gmail
login page is fake and your password is stolen as soon as you type it
in.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.wordfence.com/blog/2017/01/gmail-phishing-data-uri/">Effective Gmail Phishing</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Email Phishing Attack]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/01/email-phishing-attack/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-01T00:10:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/01/email-phishing-attack</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well, in my earlier post on security tips I mentioned links in email.
According to an article in <em>Business Insider</em>, that&rsquo;s exactly how John
Podesta&rsquo;s account was compromised.</p>

<!-- More -->


<blockquote><p>Simply put: Rather than clicking a legitimate link from Google, he
apparently clicked through to a fake website run by hackers. When he
entered his account information, he handed over the keys to his
Gmail.</p></blockquote>

<p>This article by Ben Gilbert goes into some detail about how this was
done.  It was an easy effort by the attacker and could have been
avoided with a bit more care on the part of the user.  He even did the
right thing in reporting it to his IT support but still clicked the
dangerous link in the email.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/hillary-clinton-campaign-john-podesta-got-hacked-by-phishing-2016-10">Hillary Clinton&rsquo;s campaign got hacked by falling for the oldest trick
in the book</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Its Email - Part 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/01/its-email-part-2/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-01T23:03:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/01/its-email-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Email isn&rsquo;t just for direct communication but it can be used for
notifications, too.  I can put up a blog post or two and then send a brief
email message to a list of friends and family with the links.  This ia
actually a method of using sender-stored email where the blog post
becomes the sender-stored message and the notification is via the
email notice.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>Beyond notifications, it&rsquo;s a way to stay in touch with an exact set of
family and friends which is otherwise hard to do.  That&rsquo;s because some
are on Facebook, some on Twitter, maybe even on Google+?  Nah,
probably not Google+.  Who knows, but I think email is still
universal.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Its Email]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/01/its-email/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-01T22:53:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/01/its-email</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This is a reposting of a bit I wrote on Fri 2015-05-29.</em></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve gone round and round trying to sort out what&rsquo;s the ideal
communication solution.  For now I&rsquo;ve come back to the simple answer:
email.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>I thought email was over, that it was time to leave it behind,
relegated to just handling commercial spam and first-contact
messages.  However, in searching for some replacement that made sense,
that had a simpler storage architecture, HTTP-only transport, and so
forth, I haven&rsquo;t found a simple solution.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s still true that sender-stored email is an ideal solution, but it
requires the <em>sender</em> to do the work.  It even works, at least when
<em>I&rsquo;m</em> the sender.  However, replies and conversations are a bit more
difficult with sender-stored email than with regular email.</p>

<p>The indie web and micro-formats are also interesting moves in this
direction, but they also represent a lot of work for the participant.</p>

<p>Ultimately, Gmail ends up being an implementation that has nearly all
of the properties of any of the replacements I can imagine,
particularly when all participants are actually on Gmail.  In that
case it is all secure HTTPS to the service, storage is secure and you
can get your data out if you want to leave Gmail.</p>

<ul>
<li>One to one is straightforward.</li>
<li>One to many is BCC.</li>
<li>Many to one is straightforward.</li>
</ul>


<p>And, it turns out that Gmail in it&rsquo;s native format is very
lightweight.  My recent move toward eliminating signing messages and
removing the signature makes it nearly identical to a simple chat.
Gmail&rsquo;s presentation keeps that view clean.</p>

<p>Gmail&rsquo;s Inbox moves a couple of steps closer to the clean and simple
ideal, but then it leaves other features hard to use.  Inbox
superimposes a todo list view on the email that&rsquo;s unwanted, with the
slight redeeming quality that it does provide a way to keep the inbox
looking clean and minimal.  My recent problem with Inbox, which I&rsquo;m
using for kenguyton@gmail.com, was that I had two unread messages that
I simply could not find on the phone app even though it had a badge
saying two items were there, somewhere!  Fortunately, going back to
Inbox on the desktop showed them right up top.  There seems to be some
bug in that system, maybe in the phone-desktop interaction.</p>

<p>So, for now, I&rsquo;m going back to basics.  Email.  I&rsquo;d never have
believed it.</p>

<p>That said, I do use phone text messaging, and more specifically,
iMessage on the iPhone, for the majority of my family communication.
I use Facebook messages and Facebook for some.  I&rsquo;ve never done more
than play with direct messages on Twitter.  We use Hipchat at work
which I dislike a lot.  That model is wrong in several ways. My
biggest complaint there is that Messages aren&rsquo;t threaded.</p>

<h2>References</h2>

<p><a href="/blog/2015/09/30/whence-the-chat-paradigm/">Whither the Chat Paradigm</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Whither The Chat Paradigm]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/09/30/whence-the-chat-paradigm/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-30T05:02:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/09/30/whence-the-chat-paradigm</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For some reason, the chat paradigm has become overly popular.  Internet
relay chat (IRC) was interesting in the mid-90s as a way to
communicate in an informal, unstructured sense.  However, I can&rsquo;t
believe it&rsquo;s still so popular.  Then we have Hipchat, Slack and
others.  What&rsquo;s the deal?</p>

<p>What is the utility of an endless scroll of mixed up and confused,
uncollated, blended conversations with no good way to determine their
topics or context?</p>

<p>Maybe it is the valid rebellion against email.  I thought for a while
that email had reached the end of its usefulness.  However, in my own
personal quest for a substitute, I&rsquo;ve reluctantly come to the
conclusion that email is the only workable, reliable solution.</p>

<p>Granted phone text messages are how I normally communicate with my
family.  Beyond my immediate family, family and friends are all on
Facebook.  One or two people still seem to use Google+ and, of course,
most Google employees.</p>

<p>Email has subjects, labels and excellent search.  It accommodates
messages of any length, including super short.</p>

<p>I do like the idea of minimal email and Google Inbox makes a valiant
attempt but I expect it to be squashed any minute as is the end of all
Google services, useful or not.  Ultimately, the native, plain
old Gmail is actually quite minimal when you really look at it.  Each
message in a conversation has the names of the people, a picture of
the sender and the message.  It looks like chat.</p>

<p>One personal change I&rsquo;ve made quietly over the past few months is to
drop all signatures including just signing my name on email messages.
The truth is we still have a compulsion to write an email message like
a letter or office memo, and not like a tweet or chat snippet.  I&rsquo;ll
still write in complete, hopefully correct, sentences with correct
spelling.  When corresponding with someone I don&rsquo;t often send email
to, then I&rsquo;m less familiar and will include my first name or full name
and maybe even a signature if it&rsquo;s a business message.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
