<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: physics | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/physics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2014-04-23T04:31:45-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gravity]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/03/01/gravity/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-01T14:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/03/01/gravity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/20140301_Space_Walk.jpg"></p>

<p>I just watched <em>Gravity</em> this morning.  It was very entertaining and I
liked the movie.</p>

<p>Congratulations are due for executing the physics of objects' motions
and the look of a so-called &ldquo;zero gravity&rdquo; (in orbit) environment so
well.  It was all believable.  I can&rsquo;t believe they didn&rsquo;t shuttle the
crew up to the ISS and shoot it on site, it was realistic enough.</p>

<p>The behaviour of tethered objects and such were pretty real.</p>

<p>However, there were some technical points to complain about.  Here&rsquo;s a
quick run down.  And, yes, there are lots of spoilers here.</p>

<p><em>Image: <a href="http://spaceflight1.nasa.gov/gallery/images/shuttle/sts-116/html/s116e06645.html">NASA Image</a>. S116-E-06645 (16 Dec. 2006)&mdash;Astronaut Robert
 L. Curbeam, Jr., STS-116 mission specialist, participates in the
 mission&rsquo;s third planned session of extravehicular activity (EVA) as
 construction resumes on the International Space Station.</em></p>

<!-- More -->


<h2>Physics</h2>

<p>A better title for the movie would have been &ldquo;Momentum.&rdquo;  Once they
got past the basics of orbital life and space, the physics wasn&rsquo;t
handled very well in some places.  For example, you don&rsquo;t need a
certain amount of thrust to get to another object.  The amount of
thrust results in a speed which only determines how long it will take
to get there.</p>

<p>Getting to the Chinese space station could be done with just thrusts
from the maneuvering thrusters.  Granted, it could take a while to get
there and there was the race against the orbiting debris (but see
below) and running out of oxygen.  If something is far away in the
orbital environment of space, you don&rsquo;t need a bigger engine the
farther away it is, unless you want to go faster and get there
sooner.  There <em>is</em> an argument to be made for having a lot of fuel
for maneuvering because rendezvous is <em>hard</em>.</p>

<h2>The Worst Flaw</h2>

<p>And while talking about momentum, we may as well get to what I
consider the worst flaw in the movie.  It occurs when Sandra Bullock&rsquo;s
and George Clooney&rsquo;s characters let go of each other and Clooney
floats off into the distance.  At that point neither of them is
moving.  They&rsquo;ve both already stopped (at least in their orbiting
frame of reference).  In reality, when they let go he&rsquo;d just hang
there.</p>

<p>Also, just the slightest tug would have started him moving back toward
the space station.  Similarly, if she could have executed a slight tug
on the parachute lines, she could have started herself or both of them
headed back, even if at a very slow speed.</p>

<p>The real problem to be solved at that moment was to make sure she
didn&rsquo;t lose the parachute line by her foot slipping off of it, or whatever
was her current situation, and also not losing their connection to
each othere.</p>

<h2>Astronaut Behaviour</h2>

<p>I don&rsquo;t think a real astronaut would be as panicked or apparently as
untrained as Sandra Bullock&rsquo;s character.   In real life, an astronaut
would be methodical, matter of fact and execute previously practiced
plans.   They would be more knowledgeable and resourceful.  They would
know where the buttons were though they would probably follow a
manual.  They would think through the problem and execute.</p>

<p>In spite of what we might have in the near future, we don&rsquo;t take
passengers into space yet.  Mission specialists are trained as
astronauts for many months.</p>

<h2>Helmet and Space Suit</h2>

<p>Why, in an emergency situation, in a compromised spacecraft, and with
a threat of further breaching, would you ever take your space suit and
helmet off?  I can buy that maybe you would have trouble getting to
some parts of a space station or craft, but a trained astronaut
wouldn&rsquo;t remove the suit until it was absolutely necessary and then
only as long as required.</p>

<p>Similarly, they would keep the helmet on when in the smaller craft and
they certainly wouldn&rsquo;t leave it bouncing around in the cabin.</p>

<h2>Use The Fire Extinguisher</h2>

<p>A fire in the cabin would quickly use up oxygen.  No one, astronaut or
not, would allow a fire to burn without using a fire extinguisher on
it.  Even if you were seconds away from splashing into the ocean.</p>

<h2>Landing</h2>

<p>Again, an astronaut would be trained well enough to execute a
landing.   They wouldn&rsquo;t open the hatch too quickly.    They would
have a flotation device ready.   They&rsquo;d know and follow the
procedure.  They would use the radio to reply to the broadcasts that
were, in English!, trying to make contact.</p>

<p>They would probably have a survival pack including a radio, marker dye
and/or strobe and other provisions.</p>

<p>I can&rsquo;t imagine they would blow the hatch, sink the capsule and end up
having to swim with nothing to a convenient shore.</p>

<h2>Chute Ejection</h2>

<p>One problem was the Soyuz being bound to the ISS by it&rsquo;s parachute.
I&rsquo;m pretty sure the parachute can be ejected with explosive bolts at
landing.  I don&rsquo;t think she&rsquo;d have had to unbolt it by hand, but could
arm and fire the bolts by pushing a button.</p>

<h2>Collision with Debris</h2>

<p>An accident and collisions are not unreal, but space is big.  Really,
really big.  The chances of such a debris cluster hitting a relatively
microscopic target, even the size of the International Space Station,
are astronomically small.  The debris cloud itself would be expanding
and getting bigger and bigger.  You might impact a single bolt or
piece of junk, and it <em>could</em> be fatal.  However, I don&rsquo;t think you&rsquo;d
have a cloud concentrated enough to stay that close together by the
time it got to the ISS even if their orbits did intersect.</p>

<p>Rendezvousing with another space craft on purpose is extremely hard.
That much random junk doing it by accident is unrealistic.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s also true that a typical orbit at that altitude, I think, has a
period of about 90 minutes.  However, if you rendezvous with something
at the same altitude, it&rsquo;s going to take anything but 90 minutes.  If
two bodies were going in opposite directions it would take at most
about 45 minutes.  If they were going in the same direction but at
slightly different speeds, then it would take a really long time, much
longer than the 90 minutes.  And, if they are going in the same
direction, the speed of impact is much lower, just the difference in
their speeds.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Foucault Pendulum]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/09/22/the-foucault-pendulum/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-22T06:37:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/09/22/the-foucault-pendulum</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/20130922_Berry_Pendulum.jpg"></p>

<p>The old planetarium adjoined the science hall of the museum and
the center piece exhibit there was a Foucault pendulum.  It was a
wonderful demonstration of the rotation of the earth.  The planetarium
office was on the third floor and also attached to the side of the
cylindrical section of the building containing the planetarium.  It
was my office until I moved into a brand new, below ground suite of
staff offices beneath the exhibit halls.  The interesting thing was
that the pendulum was suspended from the ceiling of that third floor
office.  Yes, the room had an opening in the floor, appropriately
surrounded by a rail for safety.</p>

<p>One of the Google Doodles for this past week was the Foucault
pendulum.  I looked at it a day or so after it was on the main search
page.  I didn&rsquo;t look at any of the explanations it might have linked
to, but it reminded me of trying to explain the pendulum to folks in
the exhibit hall.  The time it takes the pendulum to apparently rotate
is a very difficult concept and I&rsquo;ve been trying to think of a good
way to explain it for many decades.  Over the past few years, I think
I finally hit upon a reasonable and understandable explanation.</p>

<p><em>Image credit: Foucault pendulum at Berry College in Rome, Georgia
by <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/courtneymcgough/2318810863/">Courney McGough</a>
CC BY-NC-ND 2.0. Note, this is not the particular pendulum discussed in this
post.</em></p>

<!-- More -->


<h2>The Easy Part</h2>

<p>Basically, the Foucault pendulum demonstrates that the earth is
rotating.  A pendulum always tries to swing in the same direction.
Imagine holding a pendulum over a rotating phonograph record (that&rsquo;s a
vinyl record, you know, music, for you young folk).  Also imagine
placing your favorite, tiny action figure near the outside of the
record.  To the little figure, it will look like the pendulum,
swinging constantly in the same direction, is rotating, changing it&rsquo;s
direction.  That proves the record is turning.  This is how a Foucault
pendulum would behave at the North Pole and it&rsquo;s simple to understand.</p>

<p>However, things are different at the equator.  Imagine starting a
pendulum at the equator swinging north-south.  Now as the earth
rotates, the pendulum can continue to happily swing north and south
without any change in it&rsquo;s direction, all the way around the course
of a day.  The pendulum itself would be traveling <em>around</em> the earth,
but not <em>rotating</em>, relative to the ground beneath it, as it went.</p>

<h2>The Weird Part</h2>

<p>So the pendulum would appear to rotate once every 24 hours at the
pole, but at the equator it would never rotate, it would take infinite
time.  What&rsquo;s worse, between the two extremes it takes longer and
longer to rotate as one moves from the pole to lower latitudes.</p>

<p>In Atlanta, for example, at about 34 degrees latitude, the pendulum
would take about 43 hours to go around once.  How can that be since
the earth rotates in 24 hours?</p>

<h2>Try Driving</h2>

<p>Imagine the earth as a smooth sphere, no mountains or oceans, like a
globe.  And imagine you&rsquo;re going to drive around the earth in a car.
To make it interesting, we&rsquo;ll drive fast enough to make it around the
earth in 24 hours.  At the equator, this is easy.  We point the car
east and take off an 1000 miles per hour, or so.</p>

<p>What about 34 degrees above the equator?  There, we want to drive
along a parallel line, a parallel of latitude.  If we point our car
east and set off straight ahead, we won&rsquo;t follow the parallel.
Instead the car will follow a great circle (like a tilted equator).
It will cross the real equator &frac14; of the way around, hit 34 degrees
<em>south</em> latitude on the opposite side, and arrive again at it&rsquo;s
starting point.</p>

<p>To follow the parallel at 34 degrees, we have to turn the steering
wheel slightly to the left to stay on track.  Aircraft and ship&rsquo;s
pilots understand this.  Usually they like to travel along great
circles.</p>

<p>So if we cut our steering wheel to the left a little and drove at an
appropriate speed, we&rsquo;d make it around the parallel in 24 hours.  Now,
what if we took the car off of the earth-sized sphere and set it down
on an infinite plane?  With the steering wheel cut to the left that
same amount and traveling at the speed we used before, how long would
it take the car to drive around in a circle?  The answer is about the
43 hours it took the Foucault pendulum to go around.</p>

<p>Well, think about it.  If we took our car from the equator, with it&rsquo;s
steering wheel pointed straight ahead, it wouldn&rsquo;t go around in a
circle at all.  It would just drive off toward infinity.</p>

<p>For what it&rsquo;s worth, our car at the north pole would have to turn the
steering almost 90 degrees to the left and drive in donuts around the
pole.  In that case, just like the pendulum, the car would go around
in about 24 hours on the plane, if we drove (in this case very slowly)
at a speed to make it around the pole in 24 hours.</p>

<h2>Moving vs. Turning</h2>

<p>Notice that as the car is farther north, it&rsquo;s driving more slowly but
turning more.  That&rsquo;s what&rsquo;s really going on here.  At the equator,
you really don&rsquo;t turn <em>about a vertical axis</em> at all.  You head off
toward the east as if you&rsquo;re standing on a moving sidewalk.  Sure,
you&rsquo;re turning about the earth&rsquo;s axis, but not around your <em>own</em> axis
pointed straight up.  At the equator it&rsquo;s all moving and no turning.</p>

<p>At the pole, it&rsquo;s all turning but no moving.  You don&rsquo;t move or you&rsquo;d
leave the pole.  As you go from the equator to the pole, your motion
around the earth becomes more a turning motion and less a moving
motion.  You can tell there&rsquo;s less &ldquo;moving&rdquo; because the parallels are
smaller and smaller.  You don&rsquo;t have as far to go.</p>

<p>For the mathematical types, the time it takes the pendulum to rotate
is 24 hours divided by the sine of the latitude.</p>

<h2>That Crazy World of Geometry</h2>

<p>This is just one example of how much trouble we get into if we leave
the comfortable world of Euclid&rsquo;s plane geometry and try to do things
in a crazy world of say a sphere or saddle-shape.  And that&rsquo;s just for
a two-dimensional surface (of sorts).  If you get into other
geometries in three and more dimensions, then you&rsquo;re in the crazy
world that Einstein and his successors used to explain gravity purely
in terms of geometry&mdash;no forces needed.</p>

<h2>Back in the exhibit hall</h2>

<p>Each morning I&rsquo;d manually start the massive pendulum on it&rsquo;s
three-story cable swinging north-south.  Later in the day, it&rsquo;s
direction would have visibly changed.  Traditionally, an exhibit will
have little blocks that the pendulum can knock over as it changes
direction.  It&rsquo;s good enough to show that the earth truly is rotating
without understanding all of the above.  And it&rsquo;s pretty clever,
really, to be able to show such a large effect with such a simple
experiment.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
