<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: physics | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/physics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2016-09-23T23:30:45-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[LIGO and the GW150914 Discovery]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/02/21/ligo-and-the-discovery/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-21T07:12:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/02/21/ligo-and-the-discovery</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I finally found the paper for the recent LIGO discovery of gravity
waves from a black hole merger, event GW150914 at 2015-09-14 09:50:45
+0000 which data implies was the merging of two black holes, one with
mass 36 (+5, -4) solar masses and the other 29 (+4, -4) solar masses
into an object of 62 (+4, -4) solar masses with 3 (+0.5, -0.5) solar
masses radiated away (lost) as emitted gravitational waves.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>B.P. Abbot and collaborators say,</p>

<blockquote><p>Over 0.2 s, the signal increases in frequency and amplitude in about 8
cycles from 35 to 150 Hz, where the amplitude reaches a maximum. The
most plausible explanation for this evolution is the inspiral of two
orbiting masses, m1 and m2, due to gravitational-wave emission.</p></blockquote>

<p>The source redshift was measured as <em>z</em>=0.09 (+0.03, -0.04).</p>

<p>One interesting outcome in the conclusions is support for massive
black holes.</p>

<blockquote><p>GW150914 demonstrates the existence of stellar-mass black holes more
massive than ≃ 25 solar masses, and establishes that binary black
holes can form in nature and merge within a Hubble time. Binary
black holes have been predicted to form both in isolated binaries
and in dense environments by dynamical interactions.  The
formation of such massive black holes from stellar evolution
requires weak massive-star winds, which are possible in stellar
environments with metallicity lower than ≃ &frac12; the solar value.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="https://dcc.ligo.org/public/0122/P150914/014/LIGO-P150914_Detection_of_GW150914.pdf">The Paper: Observation of Gravitational Waves from a Binary Black Hole Merger by B. P. Abbott et al. (pdf)</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Observing Gravitational Waves]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/02/06/observing-gravitational-waves/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-06T12:05:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/02/06/observing-gravitational-waves</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The search for detection of gravitational waves continues.</p>

<p><a href="http://arstechnica.com/science/2016/02/after-100-years-scientists-are-finally-closing-in-on-einsteins-ripples/">Ars Technica article</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Periodic Table Row Seven Complete]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/01/08/periodic-table-row-seven-complete/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-08T21:52:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/01/08/periodic-table-row-seven-complete</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>Confirmation that four new elements – those with atomic numbers 113,
115, 117 and 118 – have indeed been synthesised has come from the
International Union of Pure and Applied Chemistry (Iupac), completing
the seventh row of the periodic table.</p></blockquote>

<!-- More -->


<blockquote><p>The groups credited for creating them – in Japan, Russia and the US –
have spent several years gathering enough evidence to convince experts
from Iupac and its physics equivalent, the International Union of Pure
and Applied Physics, of the elements’ existence. All four are highly
unstable superheavy metals that exist for only a fraction of a
second. They are made by bombarding heavy metal targets with beams of
ions, and can usually only be detected by measuring the radiation and
other nuclides produced as they decay.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.rsc.org/chemistryworld/2016/01/new-elements-periodic-table-seventh-row-iupac">Confirmation of four new elements completes seventh row of periodic table</a> from the Royal Society of Chemistry by Emma Stoye.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Atomic Energy Toys from the 50s]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/01/08/atomic-energy-toys-from-the-50s/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-08T21:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/01/08/atomic-energy-toys-from-the-50s</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.orau.org/PTP/collection/atomictoys/GilbertU238Lab.htm">Gilbert U-238 Atomic Energy Lab (1950-1951)</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kilogram Conflict Resolved at Last]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/10/14/kilogram-conflict-resolved-at-last/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-14T00:39:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/10/14/kilogram-conflict-resolved-at-last</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>For decades, metrologists have strived to retire ‘Le Grand K’ — the
platinum and iridium cylinder that for 126 years has defined the
kilogram from a high-security vault outside Paris. Now it looks as if
they at last have the data needed to replace the cylinder with a
definition based on mathematical constants.</p></blockquote>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>One method, pioneered by an international team known as the Avogadro
Project, involves counting the atoms in two silicon-28 spheres that
each weigh the same as the reference kilogram. This allows them to
calculate a value for Avogadro’s constant, which the researchers
convert into a value for Planck’s constant. Another method uses a
device called a watt balance to produce a value for Planck’s constant
by weighing a test mass calibrated according to the reference kilogram
against an eletromagnetic force.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.nature.com/news/kilogram-conflict-resolved-at-last-1.18550">Kilogram Conflict Resolved at Last</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
