<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: earth | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/earth/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2016-02-06T12:34:54-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Great Divide]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/18/the-great-divide/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-18T11:02:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/18/the-great-divide</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/dark_site_map.png"></p>

<p><a href="/blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 8</a></p>

<p>Recently some article about an upcoming astronomical event, I don&rsquo;t
recall which one, referred to the web site
<a href="http://darksitefinder.com/">darksitefinder.com</a> and the typical light
pollution maps there.  The maps illustrate the light being emitted
from the earth, mostly man-made, light that is strongly reflected back
from the atmosphere that illuminates the night sky, obscuring the view
of distant, astronomical objects.  But I noticed something that hadn&rsquo;t
caught my eye before.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>There was a very distinct line separating densely populated areas from
the eastern continental United States from the west.  Sure, I know the
West is more sparsely populated, at least until you get to the West
Coast, but I didn&rsquo;t know the dividing line dropped off so sharply.
The illumination levels correlate pretty well with population so this
is population density we&rsquo;re seeing here in nearly all cases.</p>

<p>The drop off edge doesn&rsquo;t quite match anything I can think of.  It&rsquo;s
not aligned with the Mississippi or any river really, or other
geologic feature, or a shift in climate or moisture.  There are cases
of all of those near the line but they don&rsquo;t quite match.  Some don&rsquo;t
match by a long shot.  I wondered if it might be a major north-south
railway that the last wall of cities there lies along.  That might be
but then you&rsquo;d still have to ask why the railroad ran along that
line.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s no historical boundary that corresponds either, that I&rsquo;ve been
able to find so far.</p>

<p>There must be something going on here.  Some global characteristic of
the continental U.S. that&rsquo;s larger than the growth and development of
little independent population centers.  A sharp line like that doesn&rsquo;t
imply independence.  (To be clear, I mean in the mathematical, process
sense).</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/darksite_close.png"></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m also fascinated by the rectangle of cities that Atlanta lies
in. The shape of Atlanta&rsquo;s light blob reveals the three fingers of
growth to the north along the I-75, Georgia 400, and I-85 corridors.</p>

<p>The bottom side of the rectangle is Montgomery, Columbus, Macon, and
Augusta.  The top side is Huntsville, Chattanooga, and Asheville.
Huntsville, Birmingham, and Montgomery make the west edge.  Asheville,
Greenville-Spartanburg, and Augusta make the east edge.</p>

<p>Knoxville is almost part of the northern edge but is stretched up
north, because it follows I-75 I think.</p>

<p>The population flow from Atlanta to Greenville-Spartanburg, Charlotte,
Greensboro, and Raleigh-Durham is fairly prominent.</p>

<p>You can also see the dark skies (the blue area) of Eastern Georgia
between Atlanta and Augusta.  That&rsquo;s the location both of Georgia
State&rsquo;s Hard Labor Creek observatory and the Deer Lick Astronomy
Village.  In sad contrast, notice how little dark sky is left in the
North Georgia Mountains north of Atlanta.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[O2 from the Ocean?]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/06/08/o2-from-the-ocean/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-08T12:01:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/06/08/o2-from-the-ocean</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/745225main_image04292013_250m_1024-768.jpg"></p>

<p>From <a href="https://twitter.com/earthskyscience/status/343396224805777409">@earthskyscience</a></p>

<p><a href="http://earthsky.org/earth/how-much-do-oceans-add-to-worlds-oxygen">How much do oceans add to world’s oxygen?</a></p>

<blockquote><p>Scientists agree that there’s oxygen from ocean plants in every breath
we take. Most of this oxygen comes from tiny ocean plants – called
phytoplankton – that live near the water’s surface and drift with the
currents. Like all plants, they photosynthesize – that is, they use
sunlight and carbon dioxide to make food. A byproduct of
photosynthesis is oxygen.</p>

<p>Scientists believe that phytoplankton contribute between 50 to 85
percent of the oxygen in Earth’s atmosphere. They aren’t sure because
it’s a tough thing to calculate.</p></blockquote>

<p><em>Image credit: <a href="http://www.nasa.gov/multimedia/imagegallery/image_feature_2499.html">NASA GFSC</a></em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
