<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: google | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/google/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2016-09-28T05:19:15-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chrome OS and Android Merge]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/11/05/chrome-os-and-android-merge/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-05T06:31:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/11/05/chrome-os-and-android-merge</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I think John Gruber of Daring Fireball said it best.  &ldquo;I think this
was inevitable. Android can (and does) run Chrome. Chrome can’t run
Android. And the browser-based web is decreasing in importance.&rdquo;</p>

<p><a href="http://daringfireball.net/linked/2015/11/02/chromeos-to-fold">WSJ: &ldquo;Google to Fold Chrome Operating System Into Android&rdquo;</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gmail Inbox Mistake]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/03/23/gmail-inbox-mistake/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-23T08:13:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/03/23/gmail-inbox-mistake</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well, that was a mistake.  To a large degree I really like Gmail&rsquo;s new
Inbox IOS app, and the desktop version doesn&rsquo;t look bad either.  I&rsquo;ve
used it on a rarely-used account and recently added in anther,
more-often-used account so I could try out more interaction.  I heard
someone on a podcast say, It doesn&rsquo;t really affect your regular Gmail
interface interactions so you can use both at the same time.  That
seemed to be the case to me, so I thought, okay, I&rsquo;ll just fire it up
on my main Gmail account.</p>

<p>That was a mistake.</p>

<p>So it does have an effect in a particular way.  I should have seen
it.  The Gmail model is to treat messages like to do items and mark
them as &ldquo;Done&rdquo; when you are finished with them, instead of marking
them as &ldquo;Read.&rdquo;  Marking as &ldquo;Read&rdquo; is still there but it&rsquo;s
independent.  Of course, &ldquo;Done&rdquo; is yet another label though it doesn&rsquo;t
show up in the list of labels so maybe it&rsquo;s more a kind of state.
However, you can search in the regular Gmail for &ldquo;label:done&rdquo; and it
will find your done messages.  (That&rsquo;s giving away the ending).</p>

<p>With the Inbox app, you can go through and use the little &ldquo;sweep&rdquo;
icons to sweep away large collections of messages as &ldquo;Done,&rdquo; all in
one, uh, swoop.  Fortunately, it didn&rsquo;t seem to let me do more than
one month at a time.  I finally got tired of that, but then went back
to check the Gmail view.</p>

<p>My mistake was thinking &ldquo;Done&rdquo; in the Inbox app meant &ldquo;mark as Read&rdquo;
in the Gmail app, which was wrong.  So I&rsquo;d moved hundreds of messages
out of my Inbox to who knows where.  Well now we all know they no
longer had the Inbox label and now had the Done label or state.  (And,
yes, I&rsquo;m now going to stop using the quotes around all of these states
and labels).  Also, as we all should know, in Gmail, you don&rsquo;t move
anything but only ever add and remove labels.</p>

<p>Well, that was a big change.  Part of my Gmail organization, written
about recently, is how I keep some things in the Inbox and some bypass
it and are only in labels.</p>

<p>Now I&rsquo;d moved the Inbox-only items completely out of site, read or
unread.</p>

<p>Thinking quickly, too quickly, and acting too quickly, I realized I
could try the search &ldquo;label:done&rdquo; and find them all.  So I just took
that list, clicked the upper left box to check all on the screen, then
checked the little link that always pops up that says, &ldquo;Select all
messages that match this search&hellip;&rdquo; to select <em>all</em> of the Done
items.  Then I just added the Inbox label back to them.</p>

<p>Except now I move a lot of messages (again, hundreds) into the Inbox
that formerly my filter had kept from ever being in the Inbox.  My
levels of email importance, and the underlying sorting, are something
like this:</p>

<ul>
<li>Only in the Inbox</li>
<li>In the Inbox but with a label</li>
<li>Only in a label (not in the Inbox)</li>
<li>Only in a label and marked as read on delivery</li>
</ul>


<p>I should have included that list in my previous post.</p>

<p>I was finally able to mostly clean up this mess by selecting the
various labels, select all of the messages, which now had the Inbox
label, and click the Archive operation.  Archive is Gmail-speak for
special operation that just removes the Inbox label.</p>

<p>I should never have believed that the Inbox app would be harmless and
wouldn&rsquo;t have some effect on my regular Gmail account.  Gmail
desperately wants to manage my email for me (to the point of just
taking it over) and, as much as I really like Gmail and think it&rsquo;s by
far the best email solution, I have to beat it down hard with a big
stick every time it raises it&rsquo;s head and tries to attack my email with
unwanted help.  It&rsquo;s exhausting.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s a metaphor for Google in general and will probably eventually
lead, in some large part, to their downfall.</p>

<p>I still like a lot about the Inbox app and it&rsquo;s interface and I&rsquo;ll
keep experimenting with a much less important account.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Inbox: First Impression]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/28/inbox-first-impression/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-28T06:01:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/28/inbox-first-impression</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 18.1</a></p>

<p>I just set up Inbox on a very old, in fact my oldest, earliest, Gmail
account.  Come to think of it, I guess that&rsquo;s appropriate in a way.
Here, briefly, are my very first impressions.</p>

<h2>Short Version</h2>

<p>Inbox is like the dead mouse your cat brings to you.  Thanks but
that&rsquo;s not exactly what I wanted and it&rsquo;s not quite useful to me,
though I appreciate the work you&rsquo;ve done.  I may even be impressed by
it.  It&rsquo;s true I could use something to eat right now, maybe even
something about that size, but that isn&rsquo;t it.</p>

<!-- More -->


<h2>Slightly More Detail</h2>

<p>Minimalist email messages:  Yes.  I like this idea of messages that
can look like tweets but still, maybe, have support for long messages.
Really, though, I think long messages should be a document that is
emailed.</p>

<p>The card thing:  Bah.  I don&rsquo;t use Google Now and I don&rsquo;t want that
much help.</p>

<p>The todo list thing: Thumbs down.  I&rsquo;m in the fifth year of my
highly-evolved GTD system and I don&rsquo;t want help with this from my email
program.  I don&rsquo;t mind it being there, it looks like it would be a
great help for folks that <em>do</em> use email to manage their lives (what a
horrible, horrible concept, though).  There needs to be some way to
get all of those green check marks and todo-listness out of the email if you
don&rsquo;t want to see it there.  Where&rsquo;s the OFF switch??</p>

<p>The automatic grouping thing: Thumbs down again.  Similar to the
above, I&rsquo;ve had complete control of my email with filters and labels
for years.  I don&rsquo;t need help.  Please get your ideas of labels and
filters out of my email!</p>

<p>Finally, it&rsquo;s not really minimal.  Inbox looks minimal and simpler,
but really it sneaks in all of the above cruft.  A program that sort
of looked like Inbox, more minimalist than Gmail, but that didn&rsquo;t
impose a lot of complexity and stuff in return would be worth a closer
look.</p>

<p>I expect changes to Gmail itself along these lines and maybe then
there will be some settings switches (no doubt almost impossibly
buried) to turn some of these &ldquo;helpful&rdquo; features off.</p>

<p>And I should make clear that this is all from my personal point of
view.  For the vast masses, Inbox may be just what folks need so I&rsquo;m
not saying it shouldn&rsquo;t exist and may not be a huge hit.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll find ways to keep playing with Inbox but it will be a while
before I unleash it on the actual Gmail that I use.</p>

<h2>P.S.</h2>

<p>It sure looks like <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CICMxwgm274">Mailboxapp</a> introduced some two years ago.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Farewell to Orkut]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/07/04/farewell-to-orkut/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-04T06:08:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/07/04/farewell-to-orkut</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/orkut.png"></p>

<p>I received an email from Google, well it says from Orkut, last night
with the subject line &ldquo;A Farewell to Orkut.&rdquo;</p>

<blockquote><p>After ten years of sparking conversations and forging connections, we
have decided it&rsquo;s time for us to start saying goodbye to Orkut. Over
the past decade, YouTube, Blogger and Google+ have taken off, with
communities springing up in every corner of the world. Because the
growth of these communities has outpaced Orkut&rsquo;s growth, we&rsquo;ve decided
to focus our energy and resources on making these other social
platforms as amazing as possible for everyone who uses them.</p></blockquote>

<p>The anecdotal evidence I&rsquo;ve heard from friends with connections in
Brazil is that most Orkut users have abandoned it for the dreaded
Facebook.  Somehow I don&rsquo;t expect they&rsquo;ve all moved over to Blogger and
Google plus.</p>

<p>In my case, I never used Orkut other than to set up an account and log
on a couple of times.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Opera vs. Chrome Part II]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/08/23/opera-vs-chrome-part-ii/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-23T08:02:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/08/23/opera-vs-chrome-part-ii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/20130823_chrome_mem2.png"></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/20130823_opera_mem2.png"></p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a comparison of Opera and Chrome memory with just three or four
tabs open.  (This is <em>not</em> a careful test).</p>

<p>In this case, Chrome is using 621 MB (612 KF2) of real memory
vs. Opera&rsquo;s 458 MB (458 KF2).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
