<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: google | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/google/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2014-11-17T08:53:58-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Inbox: First Impression]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/28/inbox-first-impression/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-28T06:01:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/28/inbox-first-impression</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 18.1</a></p>

<p>I just set up Inbox on a very old, in fact my oldest, earliest, Gmail
account.  Come to think of it, I guess that&rsquo;s appropriate in a way.
Here, briefly, are my very first impressions.</p>

<h2>Short Version</h2>

<p>Inbox is like the dead mouse your cat brings to you.  Thanks but
that&rsquo;s not exactly what I wanted and it&rsquo;s not quite useful to me,
though I appreciate the work you&rsquo;ve done.  I may even be impressed by
it.  It&rsquo;s true I could use something to eat right now, maybe even
something about that size, but that isn&rsquo;t it.</p>

<!-- More -->


<h2>Slightly More Detail</h2>

<p>Minimalist email messages:  Yes.  I like this idea of messages that
can look like tweets but still, maybe, have support for long messages.
Really, though, I think long messages should be a document that is
emailed.</p>

<p>The card thing:  Bah.  I don&rsquo;t use Google Now and I don&rsquo;t want that
much help.</p>

<p>The todo list thing: Thumbs down.  I&rsquo;m in the fifth year of my
highly-evolved GTD system and I don&rsquo;t want help with this from my email
program.  I don&rsquo;t mind it being there, it looks like it would be a
great help for folks that <em>do</em> use email to manage their lives (what a
horrible, horrible concept, though).  There needs to be some way to
get all of those green check marks and todo-listness out of the email if you
don&rsquo;t want to see it there.  Where&rsquo;s the OFF switch??</p>

<p>The automatic grouping thing: Thumbs down again.  Similar to the
above, I&rsquo;ve had complete control of my email with filters and labels
for years.  I don&rsquo;t need help.  Please get your ideas of labels and
filters out of my email!</p>

<p>Finally, it&rsquo;s not really minimal.  Inbox looks minimal and simpler,
but really it sneaks in all of the above cruft.  A program that sort
of looked like Inbox, more minimalist than Gmail, but that didn&rsquo;t
impose a lot of complexity and stuff in return would be worth a closer
look.</p>

<p>I expect changes to Gmail itself along these lines and maybe then
there will be some settings switches (no doubt almost impossibly
buried) to turn some of these &ldquo;helpful&rdquo; features off.</p>

<p>And I should make clear that this is all from my personal point of
view.  For the vast masses, Inbox may be just what folks need so I&rsquo;m
not saying it shouldn&rsquo;t exist and may not be a huge hit.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll find ways to keep playing with Inbox but it will be a while
before I unleash it on the actual Gmail that I use.</p>

<h2>P.S.</h2>

<p>It sure looks like <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CICMxwgm274">Mailboxapp</a> introduced some two years ago.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Farewell to Orkut]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/07/04/farewell-to-orkut/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-04T06:08:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/07/04/farewell-to-orkut</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/orkut.png"></p>

<p>I received an email from Google, well it says from Orkut, last night
with the subject line &ldquo;A Farewell to Orkut.&rdquo;</p>

<blockquote><p>After ten years of sparking conversations and forging connections, we
have decided it&rsquo;s time for us to start saying goodbye to Orkut. Over
the past decade, YouTube, Blogger and Google+ have taken off, with
communities springing up in every corner of the world. Because the
growth of these communities has outpaced Orkut&rsquo;s growth, we&rsquo;ve decided
to focus our energy and resources on making these other social
platforms as amazing as possible for everyone who uses them.</p></blockquote>

<p>The anecdotal evidence I&rsquo;ve heard from friends with connections in
Brazil is that most Orkut users have abandoned it for the dreaded
Facebook.  Somehow I don&rsquo;t expect they&rsquo;ve all moved over to Blogger and
Google plus.</p>

<p>In my case, I never used Orkut other than to set up an account and log
on a couple of times.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Opera vs. Chrome Part II]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/08/23/opera-vs-chrome-part-ii/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-23T08:02:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/08/23/opera-vs-chrome-part-ii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/20130823_chrome_mem2.png"></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/20130823_opera_mem2.png"></p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a comparison of Opera and Chrome memory with just three or four
tabs open.  (This is <em>not</em> a careful test).</p>

<p>In this case, Chrome is using 621 MB (612 KF2) of real memory
vs. Opera&rsquo;s 458 MB (458 KF2).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Opera vs. Chrome?]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/08/14/opera-vs-chrome/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-14T07:28:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/08/14/opera-vs-chrome</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/Opera-icon-high-res.png"></p>

<p>Chrome has gotten so slow and uses so much memory.  I downloaded the
lastest Opera this morning and tried it on Gmail and Picasaweb.  It
was much faster and left a lot more free memory!  When composing a
message in Gmail I didn&rsquo;t notice any loss of functionality.</p>

<p>Chrome was so fast and a joy to use when it was new.  What has
happened to Chrome?  And why?</p>

<p>[<em>Update Sat 2013-08-17 05:19:34 -0400: Just to be clear, I haven&rsquo;t
actually switched to using Opera.  I still use Chrome as my primary
browser. However, as a minimalist, I like simple, clean and fast.
I&rsquo;ll give Chrome a &ldquo;clean,&rdquo; but I don&rsquo;t think it&rsquo;s simple or fast
now.</em>]</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Android Fragmentation Visualized]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/08/05/android-fragmentation-visualized/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-05T06:40:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/08/05/android-fragmentation-visualized</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/opensignal_android.png" title="" ></p>

<p><a href="http://opensignal.com/reports/fragmentation-2013/">At OpenSignal.com</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
