<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: cosmology | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/cosmology/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2014-11-19T08:26:14-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sudden Galaxies]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/19/sudden-galaxies/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-19T08:12:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/19/sudden-galaxies</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>A team of astronomers using the Subaru Telescope&rsquo;s Suprime-Cam to
perform the Subaru Ultra-Deep Survey for Lyman-alpha Emitters have
looked back more than [<em>z=7</em>] to find 7 early galaxies that
appeared quite suddenly within 700 million years of the Big Bang. The
team, led by graduate student Akira Konno and Dr. Masami Ouchi
(Associate Professor at the University of Tokyo&rsquo;s ICRR) was looking
for a specific kind of galaxy called a Lyman-alpha emitter (LAE), to
understand the role such galaxies may have played in an event called
&ldquo;cosmic reionization&rdquo;.</p></blockquote>

<p>The team looked at distant galaxies that primarily emit Lyman-alpha
radiation, &ldquo;Lyman-alpha emitters&rdquo; or LAE, and saw fewer than expected,
further back in time.  There&rsquo;s an apparent sudden cutoff at that
redshift.  The redshift corresponds to a distance and time in history
that&rsquo;s model dependent.  The standard big bang model would put this at
about 13.1 billion years and only 700 million years after the big bang
itself.  The cosmological-history implication is that these galaxies
&ldquo;suddenly&rdquo; appear.</p>

<p>One thing is pretty certain.  A cosmological redshift of seven
indicates the universe was about 1/8 it&rsquo;s current size at the time the
light they observed was emitted.  That&rsquo;s 1 / (<em>z</em> + 1).</p>

<blockquote><p>According to the team&rsquo;s analysis, one reason that LAEs appeared very
quickly is cosmic reionization. LAEs in the epoch of cosmic
reionization became darker than the actual luminosity due to the
presence of the neutral hydrogen fog. In the team&rsquo;s analysis of their
observations, they suggest the possibility that the neutral fog
filling the universe was cleared about 13.0 billion years ago and LAEs
suddenly appeared in sight for the first time."</p>

<p>&ldquo;However, there are other possibilities to explain why LAEs appeared
suddenly,&rdquo; said Dr. Ouchi, who is the principal investigator of this
program. &ldquo;One is that clumps of neutral hydrogen around LAEs
disappeared. Another is that LAEs became intrinsically bright. The
reason of the intrinsic brightening is that the Lyman-alpha emission
is not efficiently produced by the ionized clouds in a LAE due to the
significant escape of ionizing photons from the galaxy. In either
case, our discovery is an important key to understanding cosmic
reionization and the properties of the LAEs in early universe.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://phys.org/news/2014-11-subaru-telescope-sudden-galaxies-early.html">Subaru Telescope detects sudden appearance of galaxies in the early universe at phys.org</a><br />
<a href="http://www.icrr.u-tokyo.ac.jp/2014/11/19120001.html">Press release from ICRR</a><br />
<a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1404.6066v2.pdf">PDF of paper &ldquo;Accelerated Evolution Of The Lyα Luminosity Function At z >~ 7 Revealed By The Subaru Ultra-Deep Survey For Lyα Emitters AT z = 7.3&rdquo;</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
