<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: astrophysics | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/astrophysics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2016-10-17T23:46:42-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Can You Cross a Wormhole?]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/21/can-you-cross-a-wormhole/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-21T08:04:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/21/can-you-cross-a-wormhole</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Do worm holes even exist?  At Smithsonian.com, Victoria Jaggard
writes the article &ldquo;Would Astronauts Survive an Interstellar Trip Through a
Wormhole?&rdquo;</p>

<p>Given the state of current physics the answer is, No.  The idea of
worm holes has come and gone in the science world, though it never
quite leaves.  The Kerr metric solution to Einstein&rsquo;s general
relativity equations applies to &ldquo;rotating&rdquo; black holes and adds new
twists, however there&rsquo;s still not really a way for humans to get
through.</p>

<p>Just like crossing an event horizon is beyond the edge of our
universe, these ideas are beyond the edge of our science.  Of course
we don&rsquo;t know everything and I have no doubt there are amazing things
still to be discovered.  I&rsquo;d never say it can&rsquo;t happen, just that we
don&rsquo;t have a good mechanism in our current astrophysics toolbox unless
we toss in a little magic.  Just like it is with faster-than-light
travel.</p>

<blockquote><p>Despite his ties to the film, [cosmologist Kip] Thorne is also
pessimistic that a traversable wormhole is even possible, much less
survivable. &ldquo;If they can exist, I doubt very much that they can form
naturally in the astrophysical universe,&rdquo; he writes in the book. But
Thorne appreciates that Christopher and Jonah Nolan, who wrote
Interstellar, were so keen to tell a story that is grounded in
science.</p></blockquote>

<p>There&rsquo;s more to come on this topic and other folks have weighed in.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.smithsonianmag.com/science-nature/would-astronauts-survive-interstellar-trip-through-wormhole-180953269/">Would Astronauts Survive an Interstellar Trip Through a Wormhole?</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
