<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: computers | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/computers/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2016-11-01T00:31:56-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Pocket Computer]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/16/a-pocket-computer/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-16T06:20:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/16/a-pocket-computer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This is a re-post of a blog post I wrote on 2004-08-31 17:48 on
Monolith Daily about an idea of pocket computing that Jim K and I had.
I&rsquo;ve made a couple of minor grammatical corrections.</em></p>

<!-- More -->


<h2>Computing in the Future</h2>

<p>One day while walking in a mall, c. 1982, the idea of the tablet
computer suddenly became very clear to me. It wasn&rsquo;t an original idea,
I&rsquo;m sure. I wasn&rsquo;t exactly aware of Alan Kaye&rsquo;s ideas at the time, as
far as I know, but I was always impressed by the newspads in Arthur
C. Clarke&rsquo;s <em>2001: A Space Odyssey.</em>
I had the full vision of a notepad-sized computer which would replace
computers, books, HBO, and a portable music device.</p>

<p><em>[Added Note:  I had read the book</em> The Mote In God&rsquo;s Eye <em>by Larry Niven and
 Jerry Pournelle but didn&rsquo;t remember that it also contained the idea
 of a pocket computer.]</em></p>

<p>In recent years I&rsquo;ve watched DVD movies and digital videos on a laptop
and I&rsquo;ve seen actual tablets finally come into use by people around me
in the office.</p>

<p>Today, in a discussion with Jim K, we had another vision that seems to
be a reasonable direction for computing. Again, I doubt
this is original and this certainly could be something that we&rsquo;ve read
somewhere. Some of these ideas have probably floated around Xerox PARC
for years and even Alvin Toffler, in Future Shock wrote about everyone
carrying around a little personal computer/information device. (Also I
know that some of these ideas, particularly about wireless access like
Blue Tooth, have been around for a while and even implemented.)</p>

<h3>A &ldquo;Pocket Computer,&rdquo; Literally</h3>

<p>Think of the &ldquo;key-chain&rdquo; digital drives that have recently become
popular. These are little fob-sized devices that plug into a USB port.
Now, for the maybe-not-so-distant future, imagine a device about that
size that has a whole computer built into it. This computer has
memory, a fast CPU and wireless connectivity over a short range (say
less than a meter or so), similar to Blue Tooth. You can just carry
this computer around in your pocket.</p>

<h3>The Desktop</h3>

<p>On your desk is simply a keyboard and flat panel. When you sit down at
your desk, your pocket computer automatically finds and links to your
keyboard and screen. Voila! You have a desktop computer.</p>

<p>This happens when you walk up to any desk top screen and
keyboard. (There are appropriate security measures of course, so just
any device can&rsquo;t grab your system).</p>

<h3>A Laptop?</h3>

<p>Notice there&rsquo;s no need for a laptop. You can carry around a tablet of
sorts which is just an I/O device (display, pad, and maybe
keyboard). When you activate this tablet, it links to your pocket
computer.</p>

<p>The same is true for a PDA. Again, this only needs to be an active I/O
device.</p>

<p>Add a linkable headset and you have a iPod-like device.</p>

<h3>Really Portable</h3>

<p>You don&rsquo;t have to carry a laptop home. All you do is get up from your
desk and leave.</p>

<p>When you get home and sit down in front of your desktop
screen-keyboard-mouse station, your pocket computer links and
activates it.</p>

<h3>A New Sneakernet</h3>

<p>Though sending output to a printer via the typical, networked way
still has advantages, imagine printing a document so that it&rsquo;s spooled
onto your pocket computer. You get up and walk to a printer. Your
computer finds the printer, links to it and the printer prints your
pages. (Yeah I know, this is an old idea).</p>

<h3>It&rsquo;s All About Storage</h3>

<p>These pocket devices would primarily be storage devices that just
happen to have computers grafted onto them because the computers are
so cheap and tiny, they are inconsequential. If you need more storage,
you buy a new keychain-sized device and throw it into your pocket. You
get another computer for free.</p>

<p>With a little direction from you, the new device and old device could
find each other and either transfer your files to the new one or link
themselves together into storage/computing array.</p>

<h3>Clusters galore</h3>

<p>Throw several pocket computers in your pocket. They could link
themselves together into a redundant storage array. Or into a
computing cluster. Or both simultaneously.</p>

<p>Fill a bucket with them and you have a high-performance computing
cluster. They decide how to link themselves together in a useful
topology.</p>

<h3>Backups</h3>

<p>With a pocket computer set up to be a backup device, whenever your
pocket computer finds this &ldquo;backup buddy,&rdquo; it makes copies of all
changed files. I think I&rsquo;d keep a backup buddy on the dresser and one
in a desk drawer at the office.</p>

<p>If your pocket device fails, just grab a backup buddy and and it
becomes your new &ldquo;master.&rdquo;</p>

<h3>ID, Security Badges, Wallets and Keys</h3>

<p>Such pocket computers could fill the roll of smart id badges (doors
unlock for you automatically because the device identifies you).</p>

<p>They could be your electronic wallet. When you walk out of a store
with a cart of goods, your pocket computer could check you out and pay
for you. It could link to a display on the cart so you could confirm
the purchases and okay the payment.</p>

<p>Your pocket computer could even start your car, and unlock your house.</p>

<p>(It could require some input from you so that just anyone that picks
it up didn&rsquo;t have access to everything).</p>

<h3>Books</h3>

<p>When you pick up a book reader (if it&rsquo;s different from a tablet), the
pocket computer would link in to give you access to books it stored.</p>

<h3>Other Media</h3>

<p>To buy media (music, movies, books, software) at a store you just
select the media you want to buy and they are automatically downloaded
to your pocket computer. If you buy them on-line, they are downloaded
to your pocket computer from there.</p>

<h3>On-line Access</h3>

<p>When you are near a network access point, your pocket computer links
in and connects you to the Internet.</p>

<h3>Your Watch?</h3>

<p>Just a linked display.</p>

<h3>Do You Want to Play a Game?</h3>

<p>Your kid sits down in your room with friends, with your wireless game
controllers (with displays), and all your pocket computers link
together in a network. With the right game software, you can all play
a shared game.
Software Distribution</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s one way to do it. This is actually an old idea but with fast
enough and convenient enough I/O, it might become feasible.</p>

<p>You buy your software on-line and it&rsquo;s stored on a central
service. Your whole computing environment is virtual and on-line. When
you want to use a new pocket computer, it links to an on-line access
point and downloads all of your software. This lets you install your
software transparently, including moving it to a new pocket device.</p>

<p>You don&rsquo;t have to worry about media or proof of purchase.</p>

<h3>Security Notes</h3>

<p>Of course security for such a device would be critically
important. You should be able to register devices you allow it to link
to. This could be a white list and black list approach. Such a device
could work like a child and ask, &ldquo;Can I link to that device?&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;No, not that one. That&rsquo;s a stranger.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Or, you could simply say, &ldquo;Don&rsquo;t ask me about linking to anyone
else. I&rsquo;ll tell you when you can!&rdquo;</p>

<h3>Where do these crazy ideas come from?</h3>

<p>First, computers are shrinking. I don&rsquo;t think anything I&rsquo;ve described
above needs more CPU power and memory than we have today. If computer
technology continues to shrink the processor, then the power we have
now will grow smaller.</p>

<p>Server class machines are shrinking now to card-sized blades so
desktop systems will continue to shrink, too.</p>

<p>Wireless is becoming more and more common, from cell phones that link
to each other with Blue Tooth, to wireless LANs, to wireless keyboards
and mice.</p>

<p>Storage continues to shrink. We have solid state storage today, in our
cameras, in our iPods, and in our keychain drives.</p>

<p>When computers shrink to become smaller than the storage device, and
cheaper, an interesting thing happens. In the past, we used floppies,
CDs and removing hard storage devices to move information from one
computer to another (when not just transferring over a communications
channel of some kind). What if the computer is small enough to be
built into the storage device? -—cheap enough so that every storage
device has it&rsquo;s own computer?</p>

<h3>Some problems to overcome</h3>

<p>One problem you would have to solve is power. The little pocket
computer needs a good battery. Batteries are shrinking and getting
better (look at cell phones).</p>

<h2>Epilogue</h2>

<p><em>One thing I clearly didn&rsquo;t anticipate in 2004 was the smart phone in
 its recent form.  It&rsquo;s actually played most of these roles.  It
 hadn&rsquo;t occurred to me how powerful an attached, high-resolution
 display screen would be.</em></p>

<p><em>There&rsquo;s also one wireless technology that we still don&rsquo;t have,
really.  Did you catch it?  We can&rsquo;t wirelessly connect a device to a
high-resolution monitor. Yes, we have &ldquo;cast&rdquo; capability but that&rsquo;s to
a receiver plugged into the display. I can&rsquo;t play a movie on my phone
and have it display in HD on the TV withouth plugging an HDMI cable
into my phone.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pi Dongle]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/13/pi-dongle/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-13T07:40:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/13/pi-dongle</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://youtu.be/qbWYUFgLhSU">Turn The Raspberry Pi Zero Into A Mini Dongle Computer &ndash; Video</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Triumph of the Nerds]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/24/triumph-of-the-nerds/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-24T14:42:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/24/triumph-of-the-nerds</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the best documentaries on the history of micro computing,
covering 1975 to 1995, is Robert X. Cringley&rsquo;s &ldquo;Triumph of the Nerds.&rdquo;
It&rsquo;s currently on YouTube.</p>

<p><a href="https://youtu.be/sX5g0kidk3Y">Part 1</a><br />
<a href="https://youtu.be/EiffgiRAYUI">Part 2</a><br />
<a href="https://youtu.be/ZFUsYXZSMqs">Part 3</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ultimate Amiga Talk]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/01/08/ultimate-amiga-talk/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-08T21:57:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/01/08/ultimate-amiga-talk</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As an Amiga 1000 owner (I still have it) this talk was extremely well
done, brought back memories, and is quite accurate.</p>

<p><a href="https://youtu.be/BbVAvDbzXFk">The ultimate Amiga 500 (sic) talk</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Raspberry Pi Much Faster Than SPARCstation 20]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/01/08/raspberry-pi-muct-faster-than-sparcstation-20/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-08T21:27:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/01/08/raspberry-pi-muct-faster-than-sparcstation-20</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>A couple weeks back, I tweeted the following:</p>

<p>&ldquo;Turns out a Raspberry Pi now is about 6× as fast as a SPARCstation 20
was 20 years ago. And a Pi 2 is more like 15× as fast.&rdquo;</p>

<p>I was a little low in my numbers, too&mdash;they’re more like 7× and 16×
to 41× as fast&mdash;since I was going from memory!</p>

<p>Here’s how I came up with that.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://eschatologist.net/blog/?p=266">Raspberry Pi vs SPARCstation 20: Fight!</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
