<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2014-11-10T06:58:47-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[IOS Reliable Updates]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/10/ios-reliable-updates/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-10T06:42:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/10/ios-reliable-updates</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are two key reasons that I&rsquo;m overjoyed to have made the switch
from Android to IOS and the iPhone.</p>

<p>One is the reliability of OS updates.  There&rsquo;s no worrying about
pure-Google vs. vendor-imposed-UI and junk apps. There&rsquo;s no waiting
for a vendor to either roll out an update or, more likely, just force
you to buy a new phone or wait for your cycle to end to get a new
phone.</p>

<p>The IOS updates are (so far) annual, universal and hassle
free.  And by hassel free I&rsquo;m referring to the above issues.  It&rsquo;s
granted there have been hiccups and bugs, but usually they are
resolved in a reasonable time.  I try to be cautious and wait for a
minor update or to before diving in.  Thus, I skipped 8.0 and waited
for 8.1.</p>

<p>The other joy is from the pictures the iPhones make.  There are
Android phones with better camera specs on paper, and yet, the photos
are often just not up to par.  My Galaxy Nexus made images that ranged
from okay to terrible.  When I go back and look at them now, they look
even worse than I realized.  I know other people disagree but I&rsquo;m
firmly in the camp: There&rsquo;s no contest here.</p>

<p>So, that makes two items removed from the list of things to have to
deal with.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Blog Stats From 30 Days]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/10/blog-stats-from-30-days/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-10T06:35:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/10/blog-stats-from-30-days</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For what it&rsquo;s worth:</p>

<p>30 days<br />
39 posts<br />
10575 words</p>

<p>The words include the blog heading.  That&rsquo;s an average of 271 words
per post and 1757 characters per post.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[After Blogging for 30 Days]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/10/after-blogging-for-30-days/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-10T05:17:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/10/after-blogging-for-30-days</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well, It&rsquo;s now day 31 and I&rsquo;ve finished the <a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">30-day challenge</a> to blog for 30
days.  The original challenge that I read didn&rsquo;t include weekends but I
went ahead and blogged straight through since there&rsquo;s actually more
time to write on the weekend than during the week.</p>

<p>I did manage to put a post up every day with the exception of day 23.
I wrote the day 22 and 23 entries on day 22 using my Kindle HD Fire,
Draft and Dropbox and didn&rsquo;t actually post them until day 24.  I
didn&rsquo;t actually do any writing on day 23.  I&rsquo;ll leave it to the 30-day
blogging judges to decide how to count that.</p>

<p>Some posts were long, some were medium length, some had pictures and
links, some were only a link, a couple were basically just
&ldquo;re-tweets.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Reflecting on the experience I&rsquo;m amazed at how short 30 days is.  It
doesn&rsquo;t seem like there are 30+ posts and it felt like a much shorter
time.  But then, 30 days, months, years do seem to go by super-fast
lately.</p>

<p>I enjoyed the freedom of not hesitating to write the short,
tweet-length posts and then working on the longer ones when I had
something to say.  I didn&rsquo;t work hard to find pictures to add but only
used them when I felt they were appropriate or needed.  Just writing
words was okay and that freedom made it fun and doable.</p>

<p>The thing I liked the least about the experience was the quality of my
writing which I think is considerably decreased from what it used to
be.  I could have put more effort into better writing but I was just
getting some words down.  In essense, I was publishing maybe the
second draft of what I wrote, but not a &ldquo;final draft.&rdquo;  That was the
most dissatisfying part.  I got into the habit of writing but maybe
not writing well or at least better. Maybe that will be the next
challenge I take on, to write at least as well as I think I used to.</p>

<p>Another result of all of this blogging was a better work flow.  I
fixed my process by smoothing out lot of friction in the steps I take
to post.  I wrote a fully-automated script so I can locally publish
the blog (I actually do proof read entries there, spell check and see
how they look), and then push the update to public on Github with a
single command.  I fixed emacs to automatically go into text mode and
made some changes on Github to make pushing easier.</p>

<p>One of the lessons other bloggers shared as they were doing this
process was the appropriateness of the mid-length post.  That means
it&rsquo;s okay to write more than a tweet but less than a long essay.
That&rsquo;s part of the life-blood of journaling.  Sometimes you just pen a
brief entry but that&rsquo;s enough to stake out that day.  Being able to go
beyond 140 characters is a chief advantage that puts blogging above
tweeting while keeping the ability to write as little as desired.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve come to enjoy writing in Markdown even more.  It&rsquo;s simple to use
and, in the end, I have a completely readable and portable collection
of text files that aren&rsquo;t tied to a particular platform or site.  I
can take this site anywhere now.</p>

<p>One down side is that I&rsquo;m running up against the performance of
Octopress.  At this very point it takes 35 seconds of wall clock time
to generate the site.  That&rsquo;s not bad but it seems like a long wait in
computer &ldquo;waiting for a command to finish&rdquo; time.  I think I need to
look into breaking off the archives into a separate site or section so
they are generated independently.  Most of the archive, all of it
really, is static at this point and shouldn&rsquo;t need to be regenerated
for every post.  However, there would be some tricks in blending it in
to the main site, e.g., so that search covers the whole site including
archives.  It might be as simple as a different repo on Github and
posting it as a separate site with a different name but the exact same
look and feel.  There&rsquo;s more research, thinking and maybe
experimenting to do here.</p>

<p>So what next?  I&rsquo;m not going to focus on making sure I post something
every day.  I think I&rsquo;ll keep blogging more than I was for a while.
I&rsquo;m definitely going to take advantage of the freedom to blog anyway
way I wish, long or short, elaborate or trivially simple.  I&rsquo;m going
to read more blogs by other folks that have taken up the challenge and
try to benefit from their lessons learned.</p>

<p>When I started the 30 days, I brainstormed a nice long list of post
ideas in just a few minuts. After managing to cover a lot of them and
adding ideas through the month, amazingly, the list doesn&rsquo;t seem
any shorter.  There&rsquo;s still a lot to write about!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[IOS 8.1]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/09/ios-8-dot-1/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-09T21:53:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/09/ios-8-dot-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/20141109_iPhone.jpg"></p>

<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 30</a></p>

<p>Today I upgraded to IOS 8.1 with no trouble and it&rsquo;s working well so
far.</p>

<p>I am one of those users who doesn&rsquo;t have the 5-GB or so of space on my
iPhone to do an over-the-air upgrade.  In spite of that, you can do an
upgrade without needing the space if you connect your iPhone to your
Mac (or Windows?) running iTunes and use iTunes to do the upgrade.  It
does the downloading and expansion of files on your desktop machine
then installs the upgrade over the USB cable.</p>

<p>The upgrade/install went without any trouble and it took almost
exactly 36 minutes it predicted.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve not used it too much.  So far, all the apps look and work the
same as in IOS 7.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[More 30-day Blogging Takers]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/08/more-30-day-blogging-takers/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-08T23:41:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/08/more-30-day-blogging-takers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 29.1</a></p>

<p>Matt Cutts also has taken on the 30-day blogging challenge.  He&rsquo;s
doing it for the month of November.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.mattcutts.com/blog/30-day-challenge-write-every-day/">30 day challenge: writing every day</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Text Mode and Auto Fill Mode]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/08/text-mode-and-auto-fill-mode/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-08T04:45:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/08/text-mode-and-auto-fill-mode</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 29</a></p>

<p>I finally did something I&rsquo;ve meant to do for a while.  I configured
emacs to automatically use text-mode and auto-fill-mode for Markdown
files.  Markdown files end in either <strong>.markdown</strong> or <strong>.md</strong> in my
experience so far.  These blog posts are written in Markdown.</p>

<p>Since text-mode and auto-fill-mode weren&rsquo;t automatic, I had to execute
them manually using <strong>M-x</strong> (that&rsquo;s the ESC key followed by &ldquo;x&rdquo; in
emacs) everytime I opened one of those files, e.g., to write a blog
post.</p>

<p>Adding the following lines to my <strong>.emacs</strong> file in the home directory
fixed this.</p>

<pre><code>;;; Add markdown files to text-mode.
(add-to-list 'auto-mode-alist '("\\.markdown\\'" . text-mode))
(add-to-list 'auto-mode-alist '("\\.md\\'" . text-mode))

;;; Make auto-fill-mode the default for text-mode.
(add-hook 'text-mode-hook 'turn-on-auto-fill)
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Buying a Telescope - Part 4]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/07/buying-a-telescope-part-4/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-07T05:27:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/07/buying-a-telescope-part-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 28</a></p>

<p>A final thought, but the most important one.</p>

<p>Now I&rsquo;ll tell you the most important secret about telescopes and
observing, the thing that&rsquo;s more important than the aperture, more
important than how sturdy the mounting is, and more important than
portability.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>That thing is experience.  Here are three examples.</p>

<h2>Jupiter</h2>

<p>With my 2.4-inch I independently discovered the planet Jupiter.  I
pointed my telescope at a bright &ldquo;star&rdquo; rising in the East and found
it wasn&rsquo;t a tiny, sparkling (due to the atmosphere) point like stars
but a little, pale, white oval.  Also there were tiny &ldquo;stars&rdquo; on
either side in a straight line.  They were the Galilean satellites
discovered by Galileo, Io and Europa (the size of our moon) and
Ganymede and Callisto (about the size of the planet Mercury).  Jupiter
itself was the white oval in the middle.</p>

<p>Later, I visited the planetarium and saw Jupiter for the first time in
a 10-inch telescope.  I could see the dark belts on the cloud surface!
Now here&rsquo;s the magic.  After that, I could always see the North and
South Equatorial belts on Jupiter in <em>my</em> telescope.  As my mentor
would later say, my eye had become educated.</p>

<h2>M33</h2>

<p>In my super-observing 20s I&rsquo;d seen many galaxies but had never
observed the face-on galaxy in our Local Group, M33.  I&rsquo;d tried many
times and could point a telescope right there but couldn&rsquo;t see it.
Galaxies are very dim with a very low surface brightness.  After all,
notice how hard it is to see our own Milky Way and we&rsquo;re inside of it!
And M33 was not even at an angle but flat, face-on.</p>

<p>Back then there was this precocious, teenage amateur in the astronomy
club who could find the galaxy without any trouble.  At one gathering
in the observatory, he put the 14-inch Celestron on the galaxy and for
the first time I was able to see it!  From that time on, I had no
trouble finding and seeing M33.</p>

<h2>The 2.4</h2>

<p>One night, at my parents&#8217; house, when I was in my 20s, I took my old
2.4-inch telescope out to observe.  By that time, I was an
experienced, star-hopping, deep-sky observer.  The finder didn&rsquo;t work
and there was no diagonal and I had to crane my neck and look up
through the telelscope while sitting on the ground.  I had my old
Norton&rsquo;s Star Atlas I&rsquo;d bought as a teenager.  With that little, old,
$30 Sears telescope I was able to find M81 and M82 galaxies in Ursa
Major, M51 the Whirlpool Galaxy, M1 the Crab Nebula, M27 the Ring
Nebula, and more!</p>

<h2>The conclusion</h2>

<p>What you see through a telescope has more to do with your personal
experience than the telescope itself.  That means, to see things, you
have to use the telescope!  The more you look, the more you&rsquo;ll see.
That&rsquo;s true in a single night and it&rsquo;s true in a lifetime.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Buying a Telescope - Part 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/06/buying-a-telescope-part-3/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-06T04:58:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/06/buying-a-telescope-part-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 27</a></p>

<p>Some parting thoughts.</p>

<h2>Magnification</h2>

<p>There&rsquo;s a common misconception that telescopes are all about
magnification.  One sure sign of a questionable telescope is one that
puts its magnification up front.  Worse is one that advertises 200x,
300x, and more.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>It works like this.  The main mirror or lens, called the &ldquo;objective,&rdquo;
collects light, information, and produces a real image somewhere in
the back of the telescope.  It&rsquo;s usually inside the eyepiece holder.
It&rsquo;s called a real image because it acts like a little picture
floating there in space.  If you point a telescope at something and
look at the back of it, with no eyepiece, you can see the real image.</p>

<p>The quality of the image, including it&rsquo;s resolution, depends on the
amount of information collected by the objective, generally the larger
the aperture, the more detail is in the image.  The eyepiece is a
little magnifying lens you use to look at the image, just like you use
a magnifier to look at a small object like jewelry or a photograph.</p>

<p>If you imagine taking something with a picture like a newspaper,
magazine or a book (if you can even find one of those), and look at it
with say a 10x or 20x magnifier, you can probably see more details in
the picture.  You might be able to make out something that you missed
without the magnifier.</p>

<p>However, if you then find a 100x or 200x magnifier and look at the
picture, what do you think you&rsquo;ll see?  You&rsquo;ll probably see the dots
the picture is made of, or just a fuzzy blur but you won&rsquo;t see any
more details in the original picture.  There&rsquo;s not enough detail,
resolution, information in the picture for 200x to work.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s the way a telescope real image works.  Even if the manufacturer
includes an eyepiece that gives 200x magnification, you&rsquo;ll just see an
unimpressive blur, if you could ever find the object at that
magnification.</p>

<p>Worse, you&rsquo;re also magnifying the speed at which an object in the
telescope appears to move (as the earth turns).  At 30x to 50x this
isn&rsquo;t that much a problem.  At 100x it&rsquo;s moving but you can keep up.
At higher magnifications, unless you have a mounting with a clock
drive, the object goes screaming by.</p>

<p>The basic rule of thumb is 20x to 30x per inch of aperture for normal
observing, and you might double it to get a closer look.  For a
2.4-inch telescope that means 40x to 80x.  Note in the previous post
that the Orion 2.4-inch has eyepieces for 28x and 70x.  That&rsquo;s
perfect!  200x or 400x for a 2.4 is absurd.</p>

<p>For the 4.5-inch telescope, 90x to 180x in theory are good.  It&rsquo;s
eyepieces at 36x and 91x are okay, but you could add an accessory to
take the 91x up to 150x to 200x but I&rsquo;d expect you to use those
magnifications rarely.</p>

<p>Back in the old observatory where we had a 14-inch Celestron
Schmidt-Cassegrain on a permanent pier mounting.  It was an f/11
telescope meaning the focal length was 154-inches (14 x 11) which
equals 3912 mm.  Our typical eyepieces when public observing were a
32-mm and 10-mm.  The 32-mm gave 122x and 24-mm at 162x.
(Magnification is just the telescope focal length divided by the
eyepiece focal length). We might use
a 10-mm or so for 391x, but usually not for the general public.  At
some point, the atmosphere itself limits the detail in the image,
regardless of how large the telescope is.  Astronomers call that
effect the &ldquo;seeing.&rdquo;</p>

<h2>Clock Drives and Tracking</h2>

<p>As discussed above, we&rsquo;re standing on a moving platform, the earth.
For that reason, the whole sky is constantly turning as if we&rsquo;re on a
merry-go-round.  The sun, moon, stars, everything in the sky rises in
the east and sets in the west for this reason. Some telescopes have an
equatorial mounting and a clock drive or computer driven tracking
system to follow the stars across the sky.  If you&rsquo;re just doing
visual observing, and you have a good mounting, you can easily keep
the object you&rsquo;re observing in the field of view.  There&rsquo;s great joy
in visual observing this way.</p>

<p>If you do become interested in some types of visual imaging or more
serious observing of certain types, then you may want to look at a
telescope with a tracking system like this, but I wouldn&rsquo;t start with
one.</p>

<h2>Try Before You Buy</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s a great idea to see what it&rsquo;s like to use a telescope.  Visit
your local planetarium or observatory on an observing night or find a
local astronomy club.  Maybe go to a meeting or two, one where they
offer some presentation or have a speaker on some topic and then,
either at the same meeting or a separate one, where members bring
their telescopes which they&rsquo;ll happily show you along with views of a
variety of objects through them.</p>

<h2>Use the Internet</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve skipped explaining a lot of terms and concepts that surround
amateur astronomy and telescopes.  Excellent explanations are readily
available on the Internet.  Orion has nice tutorials and beginner
guides on their site.  Of course Wikipedia has articles on many topics
surrounding amateur telescopes.  And you&rsquo;ll find other sources.</p>

<p>You should also download the free software for your computer,
<em>Stellarium</em>.  This is a beautiful &ldquo;planetarium program&rdquo; that shows
you the current night sky or the sky from any location, time and date
on earth.  You can use it to learn constellations, what planets are
visible, and every other object in the sky an amateur would be
interested in.  You can also print star maps to take outside.</p>

<p><a href="http://telescope.com/">Orion</a><br />
<a href="http://www.stellarium.org/">Stellarium</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Buying a Telescope - Part 2c]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/05/buying-a-telescope-part-2c/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-05T02:39:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/05/buying-a-telescope-part-2c</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 26</a></p>

<p>Recommendations continued.</p>

<h2>The 2.4-inch Refractor</h2>

<p>I always recommend binoculars as a good way to start observing.
However, if you&rsquo;re a kid who wants a telescope, binoculars might be a
disappointment.  Many astronomers would scoff at the old 2.4-inch
standard but I think this is a fine telescope to start with.  It&rsquo;s the
lowest cost beginner scope and  you can use it to see the beginner
objects.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>My first telescope was a 2.4-inch (60-mm) refractor from Sears with a 700 mm
focal length making it an almost an f/12 focal ratio.  Mine had a
25-mm eyepiece for 28x, a 12.5-mm for 56x (still okay) and an absurd
little 4-mm eyepiece for an unusable 175x.  These were inexpensive
0.965-in &ldquo;toy&rdquo; eyepieces.</p>

<p>Orion has the nicest 2.4-inch (60-mm) I&rsquo;ve seen with serious
accessories and a very reasonable price, $100.</p>

<p>The telescope takes serious, full-sized 1.25-in eyepieces and comes
with the typical 10-mm and 25-mm giving very nice 28x and 70x
magnifications.  It has a solid wood tripod.  If you&rsquo;re on a budget,
this is probably the best bet and I&rsquo;m sure it&rsquo;s better quality and
less expensive than a similar telescope you could walk into a store
down the road and buy.</p>

<p>Be sure to read my post about observing experience, coming soon.</p>

<h2>The Dobsonian 4.5</h2>

<p>I think the Dobsonian is the ideal amateur, visual observing
telescope.  Invented by amateur telescope maker John Dobson, and
achieving hobby-wide popularity around 1980, the Dobsonian changed
everything.  Suddenly, large-aperture amateur telescopes became
affordable.</p>

<p>The Orion SkyQuest XT4.5 Classic 4.5-inch Dobsonian which is, in my
opinion, the perfect beginner telescope.  It&rsquo;s portable, even for
kids, a super-sturday mounting, and has a nice, large aperture that
will allow you to see anything the typical amateur would look for.
Beginner telescopes are usually 2.4 to three or four inches.  This is
4.5!  It has a very nice 6x26 finder scope and two perfect eyepieces,
a 25-mm and 10-mm giving magnifications of 36x and 91x.  The focal
ratio is about f/8 which is classic for a Newtonian reflector like
this.  At the time I&rsquo;m writing this the price is $240 including
standard shipping.</p>

<p>Dobsonians are easy to maneuver, stay where you point them, and
they&rsquo;re just a joy to use.  The only thing this telescope isn&rsquo;t really
ideal for is any type of astrophotography.  There&rsquo;s not a clock drive
so the telescope won&rsquo;t follow the objects in the sky as the earth
rotates.  For visual observing (looking through the telescope) this
isn&rsquo;t a problem.</p>

<p>If I was going to recommended just one telescope, this would be it.</p>

<h2>The 8-inch Schmidt-Cassegrain</h2>

<p>If you have a significant budget and want a telescope that will do it
all but is still portable, I recommend the 8-inch Schmidt-Cassegrain
telescope (SCT).  These telescopes have fine optics, perform well, and
typically make an excellent platform for astro-imaging.  The 8-inch is
still not too heavy so it&rsquo;s still reasonably portable.</p>

<p>I grew up with the Celestron C8 and I have a used one now with the
most-solid, locked-triangle tripod from the 70s and 80s.  I have to
confess that I&rsquo;m not up to date on what the current crop of 8-inch
SCTs are.  Celestron and Meade are the famous names in this arena.
There may be others now.</p>

<p>One nice thing about most of these telescopes is how the the eyepiece
tailpiece is mounted solidly to the back of the telescope.  That means
any camera or equipment you attach will be similarly solid.  The
telescope focuses by moving the whole primary mirror forward and
backward along the baffle tube.  It&rsquo;s a clever design and makes it all
very solid and stable.</p>

<p>These telescopes range in price from $1000 to $2000 roughly, and
probably beyond.</p>

<p><a href="http://telescope.com/">Orion</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Farewell Tom Magliozzi 1937-2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/04/farewell-tom-magliozzi-1937-2014/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-04T06:40:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/04/farewell-tom-magliozzi-1937-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 25</a></p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t know when or how I first happened to hear the show <em>Car Talk</em>
but I quickly became a huge fan.  When I couldn&rsquo;t listen to the show
live, I got a subscription through Audible and would download MP3s of
the show and burn them onto CDs to listen to.</p>

<p>Click and Clack were hilarious, their personalities were infectious,
and their ability to diagnose car problems preceeded and exceeded
Dr. House&rsquo;s corresponding ability at playing the medical Sherlock
Holmes.</p>

<p>Probably like most listeners, it was a while before I learned that
they were actually both MIT graduates, Tom had a Ph.D., and that they
both played Bluegrass music.</p>

<p>I haven&rsquo;t been a listener for a few years but I&rsquo;ve always remained a
fan.</p>

<p>This is one of my favorite videos.  Martin Guitar presents Click and
Clack with a special Car Talk edition guitar.  Then they perform.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cBOfm-nj1dU">Martin Guitar Presentation</a></p>

<p>Articles</p>

<p><a href="http://www.cartalk.com/blogs/staff-blog/tom-magliozzi-1937-2014">From the Car Talk Blog</a><br />
<a href="http://online.wsj.com/articles/BL-SEB-84583">Wall Street Journal</a><br />
<a href="http://www.npr.org/2014/11/03/357428287/tom-magliozzi-popular-co-host-of-nprs-car-talk-dies-at-77">NPR</a><br />
<a href="http://www.boston.com/cars/news-and-reviews/2014/11/03/don-drive-like-brother-tom-magliozzi-biggest-hits/cfUZN88nBxurXRnmUS9HsJ/story.html">Boston.com</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Buying a Telescope - Part 2b]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/03/buying-a-telescope-part-2b/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-03T06:27:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/03/buying-a-telescope-part-2b</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 24</a></p>

<p>Recommendations continued.</p>

<h2>Binoculars</h2>

<p>The first recommendation is always binoculars.   They are two
telescopes instead of one.  They are the most portable telescopes you
can get and you get two, one for each eye.</p>

<p>The investment is around $100.  It&rsquo;s a good investment because,
regardless of how serious you become as an astronomer, you always have
a need for binoculars.  There are some objects that don&rsquo;t look as good
in a telescope.  A total lunar eclipse is an example.  When I was a
serious deep sky observer, I often found objects or at least the stars
surrounding their location using binoculars.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>Finally, if you decide you don&rsquo;t enjoy astronomy that much, instead of
binoculars getting forgotten in a closet, they are always useful for
things like concerts, sporting events, and nature viewing.</p>

<p>The ideal binocular size for astronomy is 7x50 or 10x50.  That means
the magnification is 7x or 10x and the aperture is 50-mm.  The
aperture divided by the magnification is the diameter of the exit
pupil and having an exit pupil near the size of the dilated pupils of
your dark-adapted eyes is the goal.  The 7mm to 5mm exit pupil sizes
fit the dilated pupil size of young and middle-aged adults fairly
well. Our eyes dilate less as we age.</p>

<p>The binocular should also have a tripod mounting point, usually a hole
in the middle tapped for a &frac14;-20 screw.  You can then buy a binocular
tripod adapter to attach them to a camera tripod.  You can make an
adapter for the cost of a few cents at a hardware store with a &frac14;-20
bolt and nut or two, and a small angle bracket.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve had a pair of Orion Scenix 7x50 binoculars for quite a few years
and I&rsquo;ve been quite happy with them.  They aren&rsquo;t the highest
precision or quality binoculars but they are well-made and do the job
pretty well for my own observing.</p>

<p><a href="http://telescope.com/">Orion telescope.com</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Buying a Telescope - Part 2a]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/03/buying-a-telescope-part-2/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-03T01:14:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/03/buying-a-telescope-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 23</a>*</p>

<p>Recommendations.</p>

<h2>Orion</h2>

<p>Since the planetarium days, I&rsquo;ve favored Orion Telescopes as an
excellent and reliable source of reasonably priced and good quality
telescopes.  Their telescopes are well-made, of outstanding quality,
and not the absurdly overpriced telescopes you find at your nearest
big store.</p>

<p>What we used to call those &ldquo;department store&rdquo; telescopes, which
typically were of poor quality and vastly overpriced.  The classic
starter telescope is a 2.4-inch (60-mm) refractor on an altazimuth
mount.  I&rsquo;ve seen the &ldquo;department store&rdquo; versions of these for $250,
even $400.  The are often advertised as 400X or 300X magnification
(which is absurd and meaningless).  That same telescope, of higher
quality, outstanding and appropriate accessories at Orion is $100.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not going to cover all of the different types of telescopes but
just refer you to the web for that.  You should read about refractors
and reflectors.  Equatorial mounts and altazimuth.  Dobsonian,
Newtonian and Schmidt-Cassegrain, Maksutov and catadioptric telescopes
in general.  It sounds like a lot, but the basic ideas are not
complicated.</p>

<h2>*Posting Day</h2>

<p><em>I wrote this post while away from home on Sat 2014-11-01 and didn&rsquo;t
actually post it on day 23 but after midnight at 1:14 on day 24.  I
don&rsquo;t actually have a way to post entries when away from home so I can
only write them and then post them later.  So, in fact, I didn&rsquo;t
actually do any of the work on this post on day 23.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://telescope.com/">Orion telescope.com</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Buying a Telescope - Part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/01/buying-a-telescope-part-1/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-01T10:07:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/01/buying-a-telescope-part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 22</a></p>

<p>Back in the planetarium days I was frequently asked about buying a
telescope, especially around Christmas.  Over the decades since then
people still ask me from time to time and still ask more often around
Christmas.  I had a pretty well-formulated answer eventually and I&rsquo;ve
written it up a number of times.  (I&rsquo;m not sure if I know where any of
those old write ups are).</p>

<p>We&rsquo;ll start with the basics, what&rsquo;s important when it comes to
telescopes:   aperture, mounting and portability.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>Note that magnification, computers and electronics, and accessories
aren&rsquo;t on the list.</p>

<h2>Aperture</h2>

<p>When it comes to telescopes, aperture is more important than anything
else.  Like a bucket in rain, a telescope&rsquo;s most important job is
capturing light raining down from stars, galaxies, planets, etc.
Light carries information and the more light that&rsquo;s gathered the more
you can see.  This is why the next big observatory is always about how
large the aperture of the next telescope is going to be.  In my early
years, the 200-inch Hale Telescope on Mount Palomar was the largest.
These days we call it the five-meter telescope.  Now we have the E-ELT
European Extremely Large Telescope in the queue at 39 meters.</p>

<p>The aperture is simply the diameter of the main lens (on the front) or
the main mirror (in the back) of the telescope.</p>

<p>In the past, most amateur astronomers might have a six- or massive
eight-inch telescope.  A 12- or 16-inch was truly gigantic.  Now, it&rsquo;s
not uncommon for an amateur to have a 24- or 30-inch telescope.  The
10- and 12-inch apertures are not uncommon.</p>

<p>Basically you should get the largest aperture you can afford, that has
a sturdy, stable mounting and is portable enough to use.  That last
part is the trick.</p>

<h2>Mounting</h2>

<p>After the aperture, the next important feature is the mounting.  A
good mounting should be sturdy and solid.   If a telescope shakes,
even a tiny, barely perceptable amount, it degrades the image.</p>

<p>I know of no better example of this than binoculars.  It&rsquo;s a great joy
to take a nice pair of binoculars out and look at the sky.  But put
them on a camera tripod and it&rsquo;s like you suddenly switched to HD.
More details suddenly become visible.  It&rsquo;s because our hand-holding
always shakes at least a tiny amount and it&rsquo;s enough to make a
difference.</p>

<p>A good mounting should also be easy to set up.  Some equatorial
mountings seem like they take 30 mintues to assemble.  Some Dobsonian
mounts take about 10 seconds.</p>

<p>The mounting should also make it easy to move the telescope smoothly
to point it at the objects you want to observe.  It should easily stay
where you point it.</p>

<h2>Portability</h2>

<p>I can&rsquo;t tell you how many times I&rsquo;ve given all of this information to
people, answered their questions, and hear from them that they finally
got their new telescope!  Then later I find out they&rsquo;ve only used it
one or two times and then not since.  Often never.</p>

<p>Many, maybe even most telescopes are bought and only used once or
twice and then abandoned.  One implication of this is that there&rsquo;s a
huge supply of nearly new, &ldquo;used&rdquo; telescopes if one could only find
them.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll address another aspect of this try-and-abandon problem later, but
a huge factor is portability.  The basic rule is, the less a telescope
weighs the more it gets used.  Smaller is better in this sense,
exactly the opposite of aperture.  Having the nicest, big telescope
doesn&rsquo;t do anything for your observing hobby if you never want to take
it out and set it up.  On the other hand, a smaller telescope that
lets you grab and go is an instrument you&rsquo;ll use.  That makes it more
enjoyable regardless of what it&rsquo;s aperture is.</p>

<p>For this reason, it&rsquo;s a good idea to try before you buy.</p>

<p>I truly love my 10-inch Dobsonian telescope.  It will always be my
favorite.  However, sometimes I find that I hesitate to take it with
me.  I find myself thinking I wouldn&rsquo;t mind something more like a
six-inch Dobsonian, purely for portability, convenience, and my back.</p>

<h2>Next</h2>

<p>In Part Two I&rsquo;ll make actual recommendations and in Part Three cover
some details about other things I&rsquo;ve alluded to.</p>

<h2>Colophon</h2>

<p>I wrote this and the Part 2a posts while away from home using a Amazon
Kindle Fire HD, the Amazon Basics Bluetooth keyboard, Draft software,
and saved the files to Dropbox.  I currently don&rsquo;t have a set up for
posting when not at home so I just wrote the entries and posted them
when I returned.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SQRL!]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/31/sqrl/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-31T05:11:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/31/sqrl</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 21</a></p>

<p>For several months now Steve Gibson of GRC.com and Security Now has
been working on a new authentication protocol he named SQRL, the
Secure Quick Reliable Login.  On his web site he describes what
happens when you log into a site, say Amazon, using SQRL (assuming
Amazon adopted it).</p>

<p>The website displays a QR code, described as a &ldquo;SQRL code,&rdquo; beside the
usual userid and password login prompt.</p>

<blockquote><ul>
<li>The user can tap or click directly on the SQRL code to login, or
launch their smartphone&rsquo;s SQRL app, and scan the QR code.</li>
<li>For verification, SQRL displays the domain name contained in the
SQRL code.</li>
<li>After verifying the domain, the user permits the SQRL app to
authenticate their identity.</li>
<li>Leaving the login information blank, the user clicks the “Log in”
button&hellip; and is logged in.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>The approach is highly secure, difficult to attack, easy to implement,
and easy to use.  He describes details at his site.</p>

<p>This is an elegant solution to the problems that come from dealing
with passwords and I hope it continues to climb since it&rsquo;s taken off!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.grc.com/sqrl/sqrl.htm">SQRL at GRC.com</a><br />
<a href="http://twit.tv/show/security-now">Security Now</a><br />
<a href="http://twit.tv/show/security-now/424">Episode 424 on SQRL</a><br />
<a href="http://sqrl.pl/guide/">Sqrl.pl Illustrated Guide</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Are Quasars Dying?]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/30/are-quasars-dying/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-30T06:26:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/30/are-quasars-dying</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 20.1</a></p>

<p>From <a href="http://www.dailygalaxy.com/my_weblog/2014/10/are-quasars-dying-at-the-farthest-reaches-of-the-universe.html">The Daily Galaxy</a>.</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;We have been able to confirm that, indeed, apart from the highly
energetic and rapidly evolving quasars, there is another population
that evolves slowly. This population of quasars appears to follow the
quasar main sequence discovered by Sulentic and colleagues in
2000. There does not even seem to be a strong relation between this
type of quasars, which we see in our environment and those &lsquo;monsters&rsquo;
that started to glow more than ten billion years ago&rdquo;, says Ascensión
del Olmo another IAA-CSIC researcher taking part in the study.</p>

<p>They have, nonetheless, found differences in this population of quiet
quasars. &ldquo;The local quasars present a higher proportion of heavy
elements such as aluminium, iron or magnesium, than the distant
relatives, which most likely reflects enrichment by the birth and
death of successive generations of stars,&rdquo; says Jack W. Sulentic
(IAA-CSIC). &ldquo;This result is an excellent example of the new
perspectives on the universe which the new 10 meter-class of
telescopes such as GTC are yielding,&rdquo; the researcher concludes.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rocket Explodes]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/30/rocket-explodes/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-30T06:16:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/30/rocket-explodes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 20</a></p>

<p>From <a href="http://www.newscientist.com/article/dn26475-cargo-rocket-explosion-is-a-blow-for-commercial-space.html">New Scientist</a>.</p>

<p>The Orbital Sciences Antares rocket&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>&hellip;flying cargo to the International Space Station
exploded just 14 seconds after lift-off last night, creating a
spectacular fireball and shockwave as the fully fuelled rocket crashed
back down onto its launch pad.</p>

<p>No one was hurt when the uncrewed spacecraft was destroyed, but the
loss will dent attempts by the spacecraft&rsquo;s builder, Orbital Sciences
Corporation of Dulles, Virginia, to build confidence in its ability to
supply ISS cargo services to NASA.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The 19-Inch Rack]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/29/the-19-inch-rack/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-29T08:31:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/29/the-19-inch-rack</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/19-in-rack.png" title="" ></p>

<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 19</a></p>

<p>Last night, while driving home, I stopped at an intersection where
work was being done on the traffic signals.  Looking at the open
control box I suddenly realized it was just a 19-inch rack inside the
silver box.  I think I even saw a network switch in there and a
surprising number of mounted devices.  That makes sense.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve worked around the standard 19-in racks in data centers for a long
time.  Even before that, when I was in school, it was common for a
physics lab to have a row of several 19-in racks.  They were usually
filled with instruments, controllers and maybe even an occasional
computer though microcomputers, small enough to fit in a rack, were
just beginning to appear on the scene.</p>

<p>Even large telescopes will have the standard racks mounted right on
the back of the telescope, like the 120-inch telescope here at the
Lick Observatory on Mount Hamilton.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/lick-120.jpg"></p>

<p>Where did they begin?  An on-line article &ldquo;Audio-Video Equipment
Racks&rdquo; credits Westinghouse.</p>

<blockquote><p>The origins of rack mounting dates to the days of industrialist George
Westinghouse way back in 1890. Westinghouse had first designed
19-inch shelving to house relay gear used in his railroad
industry. Eventually, early telephone companies also adopted this
19-inch width.</p></blockquote>

<p>For that reason they are sometimes called &ldquo;relay racks.&rdquo;  Wikipedia
says the relay rack name came from telephony and then appeared in
railroad signaling by 1911.</p>

<p>The Electronic Industries Alliance (EIA) &ldquo;standardized them in its
310-D standard, first published in 1965.&rdquo;  That standard included the
1.75-in rack space height and the 19-in width (482.6 mm).</p>

<p>Wikipedia says,</p>

<blockquote><p>The 19-inch rack format with rack-units of 1.75 inches and holes
tapped for 12-24 screws with alternating spacings of 1.25 inches and
0.5 inch was an established standard by 1934. The EIA standard was
revised again in 1992 to comply with the 1988 public law 100-418,
setting the standard U as 44.5mm (15.9mm + 15.9mm + 12.7mm), making
each &ldquo;U&rdquo; officially 1.752 inches.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.princeton.edu/~achaney/tmve/wiki100k/docs/19-inch_rack.html">19-inch rack</a> at Princeton.edu/~achaney.<br />
<a href="http://www.practical-home-theater-guide.com/equipment-racks-1.html">Audio-Video Equipment Racks &ndash; Part 1</a> in the Practical Home Theatre Guide.<br />
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/19-inch_rack">19-in Rack</a> on Wikipedia.</p>

<p><em>Photo credit: US National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.<br />
Lick photo: by the author.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Inbox: First Impression]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/28/inbox-first-impression/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-28T06:01:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/28/inbox-first-impression</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 18.1</a></p>

<p>I just set up Inbox on a very old, in fact my oldest, earliest, Gmail
account.  Come to think of it, I guess that&rsquo;s appropriate in a way.
Here, briefly, are my very first impressions.</p>

<h2>Short Version</h2>

<p>Inbox is like the dead mouse your cat brings to you.  Thanks but
that&rsquo;s not exactly what I wanted and it&rsquo;s not quite useful to me,
though I appreciate the work you&rsquo;ve done.  I may even be impressed by
it.  It&rsquo;s true I could use something to eat right now, maybe even
something about that size, but that isn&rsquo;t it.</p>

<!-- More -->


<h2>Slightly More Detail</h2>

<p>Minimalist email messages:  Yes.  I like this idea of messages that
can look like tweets but still, maybe, have support for long messages.
Really, though, I think long messages should be a document that is
emailed.</p>

<p>The card thing:  Bah.  I don&rsquo;t use Google Now and I don&rsquo;t want that
much help.</p>

<p>The todo list thing: Thumbs down.  I&rsquo;m in the fifth year of my
highly-evolved GTD system and I don&rsquo;t want help with this from my email
program.  I don&rsquo;t mind it being there, it looks like it would be a
great help for folks that <em>do</em> use email to manage their lives (what a
horrible, horrible concept, though).  There needs to be some way to
get all of those green check marks and todo-listness out of the email if you
don&rsquo;t want to see it there.  Where&rsquo;s the OFF switch??</p>

<p>The automatic grouping thing: Thumbs down again.  Similar to the
above, I&rsquo;ve had complete control of my email with filters and labels
for years.  I don&rsquo;t need help.  Please get your ideas of labels and
filters out of my email!</p>

<p>Finally, it&rsquo;s not really minimal.  Inbox looks minimal and simpler,
but really it sneaks in all of the above cruft.  A program that sort
of looked like Inbox, more minimalist than Gmail, but that didn&rsquo;t
impose a lot of complexity and stuff in return would be worth a closer
look.</p>

<p>I expect changes to Gmail itself along these lines and maybe then
there will be some settings switches (no doubt almost impossibly
buried) to turn some of these &ldquo;helpful&rdquo; features off.</p>

<p>And I should make clear that this is all from my personal point of
view.  For the vast masses, Inbox may be just what folks need so I&rsquo;m
not saying it shouldn&rsquo;t exist and may not be a huge hit.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll find ways to keep playing with Inbox but it will be a while
before I unleash it on the actual Gmail that I use.</p>

<h2>P.S.</h2>

<p>It sure looks like <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CICMxwgm274">Mailboxapp</a> introduced some two years ago.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Programming Languages]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/28/programming-languages/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-28T05:27:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/28/programming-languages</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 18</a></p>

<p>I recently made a list of the program&rsquo;s I&rsquo;ve written that I&rsquo;d consider
my favorites.  Then I made a list of the programming languages I had
used.  I think the result would qualify as a list of my favorite
programming languages.</p>

<ul>
<li>FORTRAN</li>
<li>BASIC</li>
<li>SNOBOL</li>
<li>Pascal</li>
<li>C</li>
<li>Objective-C</li>
<li>Perl</li>
<li>Python</li>
</ul>


<p>I&rsquo;m pretty sure I&rsquo;ve written more code over the years in Perl and
Python.  I&rsquo;m not sure which would be in the lead at this point.</p>

<p>Two other languages, Smalltalk and LISP, are languages I really enjoy
but only in an occasional, recreational sense.  I&rsquo;ve never found either to be
useful for anything very practical.  However, it&rsquo;s a joy to write pure
object-oriented code in the wondrous Smalltalk-80-based environment of
Squeak.  Similarly, it&rsquo;s a thrill to write pure functional programs in
LISP, using Racket Scheme.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Centaurus A]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/27/centaurus-a/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-27T23:10:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/27/centaurus-a</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/centaurus_a.jpg"></p>

<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 17</a></p>

<p>From the <a href="http://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/chandra/multimedia/galaxy-centaurusA.html#.VE8I1It4oU8">NASA Chandra</a> pages.</p>

<blockquote><p>Centaurus A is the fifth brightest galaxy in the sky &mdash; making it an
ideal target for amateur astronomers &mdash; and is famous for the dust
lane across its middle and a giant jet blasting away from the
supermassive black hole at its center. Cen A is an active galaxy about
12 million light years from Earth.</p></blockquote>

<p><em>Image credit: X-ray: NASA/CXC/SAO; Optical: Rolf Olsen; Infrared:
 NASA/JPL-Caltech.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
