<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2016-12-20T15:19:32-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Flight Gear]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/12/20/flight-gear/"/>
    <updated>2016-12-20T15:05:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/12/20/flight-gear</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I just recently learned from Andy Ihnatko on &ldquo;Macbreak Weekly&rdquo; that
there is an open source flight simulator called &ldquo;Flight Gear.&rdquo;  It
seems quite capable with many add-ons provided.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flightgear.org">FlightGear.org</a><br />
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FlightGear">FlightGear on Wikipedia</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[USENIX Computing Systems]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/12/20/usenix-computing-systems/"/>
    <updated>2016-12-20T15:02:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/12/20/usenix-computing-systems</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For many years I received the USENIX &ldquo;Computing Systems&rdquo; journal and
recently, when doing I search, I discovered the entire archive is
on-line.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.usenix.org/publications/compsystems/computing-systems">Computing Systems</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[NASA Made a Fundamental Mistake]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/12/20/nasa-made-a-fundamental-mistake/"/>
    <updated>2016-12-20T14:55:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/12/20/nasa-made-a-fundamental-mistake</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On an ISS Power supply.</p>

<p>&ldquo;The ISS is currently home to&hellip;four 14,000-pound payload-holders
called ExPRESS Logistics Carriers. Experiments from Earth like the
laser-communicator OPALS fly up to Station and Lego-attach to these
carriers, which provide them with a place to stay and, just as
importantly, the electrical power and data links they need to do their
jobs. But since 2013, scientists sending up payloads have had trouble
with the on-orbit utility grid.&rdquo;</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>&ldquo;Right now, experiments need special power converters if they want to
hook up with the carriers. And that’s because NASA made a mistake:
Inside the carriers, some capacitors were installed incorrectly. &hellip;in
the part of the carriers that powers payloads, engineers installed
some capacitors backward.&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;In designing the carrier, engineers had first planned to use
capacitors that they could hook in any which way. But then they had
changed the design, swapping in one-way capacitors. In between, no one
had updated the blueprints. And so the circuit makers had made the
circuits exactly as instructed, not paying attention to which way the
capacitors faced. All four on-orbit carriers and the in-space spare
turned out to have the same problem.&rdquo;</p>

<p><a href="https://www.wired.com/2016/12/nasa-made-really-dumb-mistake-iss-power-supply/">NASA’s Power Supply Mistake on the ISS Was Totally Avoidable</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Crash Course in Astronomy]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/12/20/crash-course-in-astronomy/"/>
    <updated>2016-12-20T14:49:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/12/20/crash-course-in-astronomy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m not always a fan of Phil Plait, but he usually does an outstanding
job of explaining astronomy.  This course on Youtube of bite-sized
topics are quite well done.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>I&rsquo;m also not a fan of cramming all of Phil&rsquo;s statments together in a
packed video.  It&rsquo;s frenetic and wears on me after a bit but, taken in
small doses, the content is good and the editing is bearable.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL8dPuuaLjXtPAJr1ysd5yGIyiSFuh0mIL">Crash Course Astronomy</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hyperfine Spectrum of Antimatter H]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/12/20/hyperfine-spectrum-of-antimatter-h/"/>
    <updated>2016-12-20T14:40:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/12/20/hyperfine-spectrum-of-antimatter-h</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From phys.org,</p>

<p>&ldquo;In a paper published today in the journal Nature, the ALPHA
collaboration reports the first ever measurement on the optical
spectrum of an antimatter atom.&rdquo;</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>&ldquo;Today&rsquo;s ALPHA result is the first observation of a spectral line in
an antihydrogen atom, allowing the light spectrum of matter and
antimatter to be compared for the first time. Within experimental
limits, the result shows no difference compared to the equivalent
spectral line in hydrogen. This is consistent with the Standard Model
of particle physics, the theory that best describes particles and the
forces at work between them, which predicts that hydrogen and
antihydrogen should have identical spectroscopic characteristics.&rdquo;</p>

<p><a href="http://phys.org/news/2016-12-alpha-spectrum-antimatter.html">ALPHA observes light spectrum of antimatter for first time</a><br /></p>

<p><a href="http://phys.org/news/2014-01-cern-antihydrogen-atoms-hyperfine.html">CERN experiment produces first beam of antihydrogen atoms for
hyperfine study</a><br /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/vaap/ncurrent/full/nature21040.html">Observation of the 1S–2S transition in trapped antihydrogen</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Oracle Is Collecting Java Charges]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/12/20/oracle-is-collecting-java-charges/"/>
    <updated>2016-12-20T14:32:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/12/20/oracle-is-collecting-java-charges</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This doesn&rsquo;t really apply to personal use of Java but mainly if you
develop and sell something.  (As far as I understand it).  The
Register says,</p>

<blockquote><p>Oracle is massively ramping up audits of Java customers it claims are
in breach of its licences – six years after it bought Sun
Microsystems.</p></blockquote>

<!-- More -->


<blockquote><p>A growing number of Oracle customers and partners have been approached
by Larry Ellison’s firm, which claims they are out of compliance on Java.</p>

<p>Java SE is free but Java SE Advanced Desktop, Advanced and Suite are
not. Java SE Suite, for example, costs $300 per named user with a
support bill of $66; there’s a per-processor option of $15,000 with a
$3,300 support bill. Java SE comes with the free JDK and JRE, but
Advanced Desktop, Advanced and Suite layer in additional capabilities
such as Java Mission Control and Flight Recorder also known as JRockit
Mission Control and JRockit Flight Recorder.</p>

<p>Java SE is free for what Oracle defines as &ldquo;general purpose computing&rdquo;
– devices that in the words of its licence cover desktops, notebooks,
smartphones and tablets. It is not free for what Oracle’s licence
defines as &ldquo;specialized embedded computers used in intelligent
systems&rdquo;, which Oracle further defines as &ndash; among other things &ndash;
mobile phones, hand-held devices, networking switches and Blu-Ray players.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.theregister.co.uk/2016/12/16/oracle_targets_java_users_non_compliance?mt=1481991081793">Oracle finally targets Java non-payers – six years after plucking Sun</a><br />
<a href="https://java.com/en/">Java.com</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Color Gamut]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/23/color-gamut/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-23T01:06:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/23/color-gamut</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The phrase &ldquo;color gamut&rdquo; has been thrown around a lot lately.  What is
it?  This blog post by Craig Hockenberry explains color gamut.</p>

<blockquote><p>From your point-of-view, the important thing about DCI-P3 is that it
can display a wider range of color. Apple’s promotional literature
states that the new iPad Pro has &ldquo;up to 25% greater color saturation
than previous models.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<!-- More -->


<p><a href="http://blog.iconfactory.com/2016/04/looking-at-the-future/">Looking at the Future</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Drought Update]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/23/drought-update/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-23T00:59:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/23/drought-update</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Even though his coverage is centered on Birmingham, Alabama, James
Spann&rsquo;s weather coverage is outstanding.  Here&rsquo;s his latest excellent
drought update.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.alabamawx.com/?p=107628">Drought Update – November 20</a><br /></p>

<!-- More -->


<blockquote><p>Droughts don’t start suddenly, and don’t end quickly either. It will
take multiple long, soaking rain events for us to dig out of this. It
will happen, but it takes time.</p>

<p>In some cases, short term droughts turn into long term
droughts. Alabama has had five major long term droughts since record
keeping began: 1929-32, 1938-45, 1950-63, 1980-82, and 1984-88. No
evidence this happens now, but it can’t be ruled out completely.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.alabamawx.com">Alabama WX Weather Blog</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[GOES-R Weather Satellite]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/23/goes-r-weather-satellite/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-23T00:47:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/23/goes-r-weather-satellite</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&ldquo;A new environmental-monitoring satellite poised to launch into space
on Saturday (Nov. 19) will fly a lightning mapper higher than ever
before, allowing for better severe-storm monitoring across the United
States and in nearby regions, NASA officials said.&rdquo;</p>

<p>from Elizabeth Howell on Space.com.</p>

<!-- More -->


<blockquote><p>The GOES-R instrument, called the Geostationary Lightning Mapper, is
supposed to watch lightning around the Americas and nearby oceans to a
resolution of about 6.2 miles (10 kilometers).</p>

<p>An advanced baseline imager&hellip;will look at Earth in 16 different
spectral bands (11 more than the current GOES series) to provide
information on weather, climate and natural hazards.</p>

<p>The satellite will monitor solar flares— and the influence of the
sun&rsquo;s electromagnetic radiation in the Earth&rsquo;s upper atmosphere —
using the Extreme Ultraviolet and X-ray Irradiance Sensors. GOES-R
will also carry a telescope that can monitor the sun in extreme
ultraviolet wavelengths.</p>

<p>During solar events, GOES-R will predict the flux of charged particles
near Earth, using the Space Environment In-Situ Suite instrument and a
magnetometer.</p>

<p>GOES-R will be renamed GOES-16 when it goes to geostationary
orbit. The satellite will do a checkout and validation phase of about
one year, and then will begin operations.</p></blockquote>

<p>From the NOAA.gov page.</p>

<blockquote><p>GOES-R will scan the skies five times faster than today’s GOES
spacecraft, with four times greater image resolution and three times
the spectral channels. It will provide high-resolution, rapid-refresh
satellite imagery as often as every 30 seconds, allowing for a more
detailed look at a storm to determine whether it is growing or decaying.</p>

<p>There are four satellites in the GOES-R series: –R, –S, –T and –U,
which will extend NOAA’s geostationary coverage through 2036.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.space.com/34764-goes-r-satellite-tracks-lightning-and-more.html">Powerful GOES-R Satellite to Map Earth&rsquo;s Lightning and Much More</a><br /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.goes-r.gov">NOAA/NASA GOES-R</a><br /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.goes-r.gov/spacesegment/instruments.html">Instruments Overview</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Super Moon -  Super Story]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/15/super-moon-super-story/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-15T06:01:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/15/super-moon-super-story</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/Moon-Earth_distance,_Moon_phases.gif"></p>

<p>The hyped story about the &ldquo;Super Moon&rdquo; is near the top of our on-line
news feeds.  I&rsquo;ll try to untangle the hype from some facts.  It&rsquo;s true
that this <em>full Moon</em> will be the closest since 1948-01-26.</p>

<p>The next closest super Moon will be in 2034, only four years before
our UNIX calendars run out of steam.</p>

<p>But how big a deal is this?  And what&rsquo;s really going on?</p>

<!-- More -->


<h2>Short version</h2>

<p>If you don&rsquo;t want to dive into the details below, here&rsquo;s the long
story short.  Every month the Moon is closer and farther from the
Earth as it follows its elliptical orbit.  Due to the tidal force from
the Sun, sometimes those distances are a little more extreme than
others.</p>

<p>The so-called  &ldquo;Super Moon&rdquo; occurs when the full Moon coincides very
closely with the Moon&rsquo;s closest approach, apogee, to the Earth for the
year.  But it&rsquo;s really only around 3% larger than any other close
approach during the year, and these happen every year.  They just
don&rsquo;t always occur when the Moon is almost exactly full.</p>

<h2>Kepler&rsquo;s first law</h2>

<p>Kepler&rsquo;s first law is that orbits have the shape of an ellipse with
the primary body at one of the two foci.  In this case the Earth is at
the focus.  The ellipse means the Moon moves closer to and farther
away from the Earth as it goes around.  It&rsquo;s closest point is called
the perigee, and the farthest point is the apogee.</p>

<h2>Sun&rsquo;s tidal forces</h2>

<p>Tidal forces stretch things.  The tidal force due to the Sun&rsquo;s and
Moon&rsquo;s gravity stretch the Earth&rsquo;s oceans so they have high points and
low points.  The tidal force of the Sun also stretches the Moon&rsquo;s
orbit.  When the Sun is in the direction of the long ellipse, the Sun
stretches it in a longer ellipse.  The extreme distances are even more
extreme:</p>

<p>apogee = 406,700 km, perigee = 356,400 km.</p>

<p>When the Sun is at right angles to the major axis, the orbit is pulled
into a less eccentric ellipse and the extremes are reduced.</p>

<p>apogee = 404,000 km, perigee = 370,400 km.</p>

<h2>Monthly motions</h2>

<p>Every month the Moon passes apogee and perigee as it orbits the
Earth.  In the excellent diagram above from the Wikipedia article on
the &ldquo;Orbit of the Moon,&rdquo; you can see the varying distance of the
Moon from the Earth plotted.  The minimum points are the perigee,
closest, distance.  Each month, when the Moon is at perigee, it will appear
a bit larger, than when it&rsquo;s farther away.</p>

<p>Notice how the minimum and maximum distances are not as extreme in
April as they are in August.  That&rsquo;s the Sun&rsquo;s tidal effect.</p>

<p>In this diagram, which was for 2014, it looks like the Moon was closest
to the Earth in about the second week of August at perigee.</p>

<h2>Moon phases</h2>

<p>The other thing in this diagram is the phase of the Moon.  The
diagonal lines show the Moon going from new (phase = 0) to full (phase
= 0.5) and back to new each month.  The vertical lines show when the
new Moons occur.</p>

<p>What we&rsquo;re really interested in here is the <em>full Moon</em> so it would
have been nice if there were vertical lines halfway in between the new
Moons to mark the phase = 0.5 full Moons.</p>

<h2>The big deal</h2>

<p>So now we have all the pieces to understand what the big deal is.
It&rsquo;s this.  How close does the full Moon come to the closest perigee
of the year?  Well, it almost never hits it perfectly, but it varies
from year to year.  In the year in the diagram, it looks like the
halfway full-Moon point would fall nearly on the mid-August closest
perigee.</p>

<p>Using the perigee-apogee calculator from below for 2014 we find the
full Moon hit the closest perigee on 2014-08-10 almost exactly, zero
hours difference!  The perigee distance was 356,896 km.</p>

<p>In contrast, this year they missed by about 2 hours on 2016-11-14 at a
distance of 356,511 km.  So the full Moon was off a bit, but the
closest perigee this year was a bit closer.  Why a bit closer?  It has
to do with the angle of the Sun to the ellipse of the Moon&rsquo;s orbit.</p>

<h2>But it isn&rsquo;t really</h2>

<p>So that timing of full Moon and closest perigee of the year is what
it&rsquo;s all about.  But notice that the Moon gets this close every year!
It&rsquo;s just not necessarily at, or exactly at, the time of the full
Moon.  Further, the Moon gets almost that close every month!</p>

<p>As we said above, the closet perigee distance is 356,400 km while the
farthest perigee is 370,400.  That&rsquo;s 3.93% larger from the farthest
perigee to closest.  That&rsquo;s how much the &ldquo;close&rdquo; Moon varies through
the year.</p>

<p>So where did the big 14% come from that I kept seeing in all of these
articles.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s the difference in size between when the Moon is at apogee vs
perigee, and that happens every month, two weeks apart.  Actually it&rsquo;s
about 13.36% when the ellipse is stretched, and about 9.8% when it&rsquo;s
not.</p>

<p>So again, this happens <em>every</em> month, but just not when the Moon is
full.</p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SuperMoon">Wikipedia &ndash; SuperMoon</a><br /></p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orbit_of_the_Moon">Wikipedia &ndash; Orbit of the Moon</a><br /></p>

<p><a href="https://www.fourmilab.ch/Earthview/Moon_ap_per.html">Inconstant Moon</a><br /></p>

<p><a href="https://www.fourmilab.ch/Earthview/pacalc.html">Perigee Apogee Calculator</a><br /></p>

<h2>Image credit</h2>

<p>Distance and Moon phases in 2014, calculated using algorithms from:
Jean Meeus, Astronomical algorithms, Willmann-Bell, Richmond,
Virginia, 1991 Jean Meeus, Astronomical formulae for calculators,
Willmann-Bell, Richmond, Virginia, 1988. Moon phases: 0 (1) &ndash; new Moon
0.25 &ndash; first quarter 0.5 &ndash; full Moon 0.75 &ndash; last quarter</p>

<p>CC BY-SA 3.0</p>

<p>by Darekk2.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The IOT Answer is the Hub]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/15/the-iot-answer-is-the-hub/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-15T00:11:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/15/the-iot-answer-is-the-hub</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Steve Gibson said this on a recent episode of <em>Security Now</em>.  He
says, the solution to the IOT security problem is the hub.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>He goes on to point out that all IOT (Internet of things) devices
should connect to a single device in your home that responsibly
handles the communications and security.</p>

<p>Recently, poorly secured, home IOT devices have been credited with
being the medium for massive scale denial of service (DOS) attacks
against well-known web sites.  The flood of cheap and inexpensive
devices like home cameras, wifi-enabled light bulbs, into homes with
very fast outbound network connections have enabled a huge force that
can be used that want to engage in digital vandalism to those who want
to bring a site under a full attack.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.grc.com/securitynow.htm">Security Now at GRC.com</a><br />
<a href="https://twit.tv/shows/security-now">Security Now at twit.tv</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How it Feels to Learn Javascript]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/15/how-it-feels-to-learn-javascript/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-15T00:08:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/15/how-it-feels-to-learn-javascript</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This article on Hacker Noon sounds too real.   It&rsquo;s depressing because
it&rsquo;s true.</p>

<p><a href="https://hackernoon.com/how-it-feels-to-learn-javascript-in-2016-d3a717dd577f#.vs20xmt4q">How it feels to learn JavaScript in 2016</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Five Classic Telescopes]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/14/five-classic-telescopes/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-14T23:51:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/14/five-classic-telescopes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Brian Ventrudo writes about five classic telescopes in this article on
the <em>One-Minute Astronomer</em> blog.  Here&rsquo;s my own experience with these
instruments.</p>

<!-- More -->


<h2>Unitron</h2>

<p>We had a 2.4 at the museum observatory and it was a
beautiful and delightful telescope.  I used it to observe, visually
via projection, the 1984 annular solar eclipse when I saw the Sun&rsquo;s
corona.</p>

<h2>Questar</h2>

<p>These portable little 3.5-inch Maksutovs were the beautiful jewels of
astronomy.  My planetarium and astronomical mentor, Mike Hood, has
collected Questars over the years.</p>

<h2>Celestron</h2>

<p>The leading Schmidt-Cassegrain brand ruled over our observatory.  We
had a 10-inch model identical to the one in Ventrudo&rsquo;s article.  It
was mounted on a permanent pier on the observatory floor.  There was
also the 14-in Celestron and two 8-inch models which I hauled around
to do observing programs.  I observed a large portion of the Messier
catalog on those 8-inches.</p>

<h2>RV-6 Dynascope</h2>

<p>The classic Criterion 6-in f/8 is a telescope I never owned or used
but I&rsquo;ve seen and looked through the RV-6.  I think there might have
been one added to the observatory collection after my time.  This
telescope and the corresponding Edmund Scientific 6-in f/8 Newtonian,
were the telescopes I dreamed most about in my early, teen astronomer
years.</p>

<h2>Coulter Dobs</h2>

<p>Dobsonian telescopes, which came to light around the turn of the
decade to 1980, changed amateur astronomy.  Large apertures became
affordable and usable.  I built my own 10-inch f/4.5 but bought the
optics from Coulter.</p>

<p><a href="http://oneminuteastronomer.com/918/5-classic-telescopes/">5 Classic Telescopes That Changed Amateur Astronomy</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hans Zimmer]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/14/hans-zimmer/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-14T23:39:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/14/hans-zimmer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Trey Ratcliff writes about photographing Hans Zimmer, his crew, and an
orchestra recording a score for one of the Batman movies.  The story
is entertaining and amazing.  The photographs are exquisite.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.stuckincustoms.com/2016/11/03/behind-the-scenes-with-hans-zimmer/">Behind The Scenes With Hans Zimmer</a><br />
<a href="http://www.stuckincustoms.com">Stuck in Customs</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Unreadable Web]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/01/unreadable-web/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-01T00:27:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/01/unreadable-web</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Kevin Marks has written an excellent article on how web pages are
being made very hard to read because it&rsquo;s the in-style thing to do.</p>

<!-- More -->


<blockquote><p>There’s a widespread movement in design circles to reduce the contrast
between text and background, making type harder to read. Apple is
guilty. Google is, too. So is Twitter.</p>

<p>Typography may not seem like a crucial design element, but it is. One
of the reasons the web has become the default way that we access
information is that it makes that information broadly available to
everyone. “The power of the Web is in its universality,” wrote Tim
Berners-Lee, director of the World Wide Web consortium. “Access by
everyone regardless of disability is an essential aspect.”</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="https://backchannel.com/how-the-web-became-unreadable-a781ddc711b6#.70urt9e64">How the Web Became Unreadable</a><br/></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DOS IOT Botnet Attack]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/01/dos-iot-botnet-attack/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-01T00:22:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/01/dos-iot-botnet-attack</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There&rsquo;s been a lot of discussion about the insecurity of the internet
of things (IOT) devices such as security cameras, DVRs, thermostats
and more.  Frankly, many of these are Linux systems that are poorly
prepared from a security standpoint and sometimes blatantly exposed.
Such devices were used in the recent, massive attacks against the DNS
service.</p>

<!-- More -->


<blockquote><p>&ldquo;We&rsquo;re seeing attacks coming from a number of different locations,&rdquo;
Drew said. &ldquo;An Internet of Things botnet called Mirai that we
identified is also involved in the attack.&rdquo;</p>

<p>The botnet, made up of devices like home Wi-Fi routers and Internet
protocol video cameras, is sending massive numbers of requests to
Dyn&rsquo;s DNS service. Those requests look legitimate, so it&rsquo;s difficult
for Dyn&rsquo;s systems to screen them out from normal domain name lookup
requests.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://arstechnica.com/security/2016/10/double-dip-internet-of-things-botnet-attack-felt-across-the-internet/">Double-dip Internet-of-Things botnet attack felt across the Internet</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rowhammer]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/01/rowhammer/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-01T00:18:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/01/rowhammer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Rowhammer is a sophisticated, clever and dangerous way to attack
computers and Android phones.  Dan Goodin reports in <em>Ars Technica.</em></p>

<!-- More -->


<blockquote><p>Researchers have devised an attack that gains unfettered &ldquo;root&rdquo; access
to a large number of Android phones, exploiting a relatively new type
of bug that allows adversaries to manipulate data stored in memory
chips.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://arstechnica.com/security/2016/10/using-rowhammer-bitflips-to-root-android-phones-is-now-a-thing/">Using Rowhammer bitflips to root Android phones is now a thing</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Email Phishing Attack]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/01/email-phishing-attack/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-01T00:10:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/01/email-phishing-attack</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well, in my earlier post on security tips I mentioned links in email.
According to an article in <em>Business Insider</em>, that&rsquo;s exactly how John
Podesta&rsquo;s account was compromised.</p>

<!-- More -->


<blockquote><p>Simply put: Rather than clicking a legitimate link from Google, he
apparently clicked through to a fake website run by hackers. When he
entered his account information, he handed over the keys to his
Gmail.</p></blockquote>

<p>This article by Ben Gilbert goes into some detail about how this was
done.  It was an easy effort by the attacker and could have been
avoided with a bit more care on the part of the user.  He even did the
right thing in reporting it to his IT support but still clicked the
dangerous link in the email.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/hillary-clinton-campaign-john-podesta-got-hacked-by-phishing-2016-10">Hillary Clinton&rsquo;s campaign got hacked by falling for the oldest trick
in the book</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What's going on inside Lithium Ion Batteries?]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/23/whats-going-on-inside-lithium-ion-batteries/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-23T07:32:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/23/whats-going-on-inside-lithium-ion-batteries</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Steve Gibson from Security Now provided two excellent sources this
week explaining what&rsquo;s happening when lithium ion batteries fail.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>From Paul O’Shea, Editor, <em>Power Electronics News</em> interviewing Nadim
Maluf, CEO of Qnovo, and Robert Nalesnik, VP of Marketing for Qnovo.</p>

<blockquote><p>Now, let’s examine one particular manufacturing defect in which a
slight misalignment between the anode and cathode occurs during the
assembly process. The same structure as above now has the anode layer
shifted slightly to the right. At the misaligned edge, the requisite
overlap of the anode relative to the cathode is now diminished or even
possibly eliminated. The anode/cathode ratio at this spot drops below
the requisite limit for ensuring safety. The result is the onset of
lithium metal at this edge. The lithium metal forms on the anode
edge. As the lithium metal grows in size and thickness, it ultimately
punctures the separator and causes an electrical short between the
anode and cathode. Boom! There is a catastrophic failure.</p>

<p>The tolerance requirements in the manufacturing of lithium-ion
batteries have risen sharply with increasing energy density. Short of
using new materials (which still do not exist in commercial
deployment), increasing the energy density means reducing all the
extra space inside the battery that is not made of anode and cathode
materials. These are the only two materials that store energy;
n> everything else is just overhead. They are still needed for other
functions and safety, but they do not contribute to storing electrical
charge. Therefore, battery designers keep reducing this overhead and,
in the process, make the manufacturing tolerances even tighter. That
is a recipe for many disasters to come unless we start adding a lot
more intelligence to the battery to avoid and mitigate these
undesired situations.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.powerelectronicsnews.com/technology/pushing-to-the-very-edge-of-safe-li-ion-charging">Pushing to the very edge of safe Li-ion charging</a><br /></p>

<p>From the Qnovo blog.</p>

<p><a href="http://qnovo.com/104-perils-4-4-volts/">104. The Perils of 4.4 Volts</a><br />
<a href="http://qnovo.com/103-real-science-behind-exploding-batteries/">103. The Real Science Behind Battery Safety</a><br />
<a href="http://qnovo.com/102-easy-not-right-pick-samsung/">102. It’s Easy, but Not Right, to Pick on Samsung</a><br />
<a href="http://qnovo.com/101-making-sense-100-kwh/">101. Making Sense of 100 kWh</a><br />
<a href="http://qnovo.com/100-state-lithium-ion-battery/">100. The State of the Lithium Ion Battery</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Counterfeit Apple Cables from Amazon]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/23/counterfeit-apple-cables-from-amazon/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-23T07:11:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/23/counterfeit-apple-cables-from-amazon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is why I only buy Lightning cables, chargers and batteries for
Apple products from the Apple Store.  It&rsquo;s just too risky to buy them
anywhere else.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>It&rsquo;s been known for a long time that cheaply made Lithium Ion
batteries are very dangerous and will short, catch fire and burn.  Now
Samsung has made this abundantly clear.</p>

<p>Ben Lovejoy of <em>9to5 Mac</em> writes &ldquo;More than 90% of &lsquo;genuine&rsquo; Apple
chargers &amp; cables sold on Amazon are fake, says Apple.&rdquo;</p>

<blockquote><p>There’s no shortage of third-party chargers and cables sold for Apple
equipment, some of them claiming to be the genuine article, but Apple
has found that even Amazon has been selling counterfeit products
labelled as the real thing. The products concerned were sold by Amazon
directly, and not by a third-party Marketplace seller.</p>

<p>The items have now been removed from sale, and Apple is suing the
company that made them …</p></blockquote>

<p>Amazon responded.</p>

<blockquote><p>Amazon responded, stating that the company ‘has zero tolerance for the
sale of counterfeits on our site.  We work closely with manufacturers
and brands, and pursue wrongdoers aggressively.’</p>

<p>Given the number of fake Apple products available, we always urge
caution where the price is significantly lower than the official
price. This is especially true in the case of MagSafe power supplies,
where any price lower than available from authorized resellers is an
immediate warning flag.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="https://9to5mac.com/2016/10/19/amazon-fake-apple-chargers-cables/">Article at 9to5 Mac</a><br />
<a href="http://www.patentlyapple.com/patently-apple/2016/10/apple-sues-mobile-star-for-selling-counterfeit-power-adapters-and-charging-cables-through-amazon.html">Patently Apple</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
