<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2016-10-04T01:21:45-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The C Programming Language]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/04/the-c-programming-language/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-04T01:15:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/04/the-c-programming-language</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The classic &ldquo;The C Programming Language&rdquo; by Kernighan and Ritchie is
online in full at the below link.  This is the second edition from
1988.</p>

<p><a href="https://hassanolity.files.wordpress.com/2013/11/the_c_programming_language_2.pdf">The C Programming Language</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bigger Milky Way]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/04/bigger-milky-way/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-04T01:06:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/04/bigger-milky-way</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Brian Clark Howard at National Geographic writes that &ldquo;Our Part of the
Milky Way is Four Times Bigger Than We Thought.&rdquo;</p>

<!-- More -->


<blockquote><p>Published in the journal Science Advances this week, a new study
reported that our surrounding area of stars, gas, and dust—called the
Local Arm, Orion Spur, or Orion–Cygnus Arm—is actually about 20,000
light-years long.</p>

<p>The Local Arm is still considerably shorter than the Milky Way’s four
main arms, which wind around the galaxy&rsquo;s center for roughly 80,000
light-years. The total diameter of the galaxy is often reported as
about 100,000 light-years, although Reid says more recent evidence
suggests it is probably more like 70,000 light-years, at least to the
edge of where star density starts to really drop off.</p></blockquote>

<p>The abstract from the paper in &ldquo;Science Advances,&rdquo; &ldquo;The local spiral
structure of the Milky Way&rdquo; by Ye Xu, et al.</p>

<blockquote><p>The nature of the spiral structure of the Milky Way has long been
debated. Only in the last decade have astronomers been able to
accurately measure distances to a substantial number of high-mass
star-forming regions, the classic tracers of spiral structure in
galaxies. We report distance measurements at radio wavelengths using
the Very Long Baseline Array for eight regions of massive star
formation near the Local spiral arm of the Milky Way. Combined with
previous measurements, these observations reveal that the Local Arm is
larger than previously thought, and both its pitch angle and star
formation rate are comparable to those of the Galaxy’s major spiral
arms, such as Sagittarius and Perseus. Toward the constellation
Cygnus, sources in the Local Arm extend for a great distance along our
line of sight and roughly along the solar orbit. Because of this
orientation, these sources cluster both on the sky and in velocity to
form the complex and long enigmatic Cygnus X region. We also identify
a spur that branches between the Local and Sagittarius spiral arms.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://news.nationalgeographic.com/2016/09/milky-way-local-arm-four-times-bigger-than-expected/">Our Part of the Milky Way Is Four Times Bigger Than We Thought</a></p>

<p><a href="http://advances.sciencemag.org/content/2/9/e1600878">The local spiral structure of the Milky Way</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Stop the Twitter Email!]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/02/stop-the-twitter-email/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-02T17:48:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/02/stop-the-twitter-email</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Good grief!  Stop the email!  Okay, apparently I have more Twitter
accounts than you can count on one hand and I&rsquo;m getting a continuous
flood of email from them.  They are all filtered in various ways, in
Gmail, so they go into labels that are those I mostly don&rsquo;t read, but
the flood is still annoying.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>Today, I finally logged into (almost) all of them and under Settings,
Email Notifications, I unclicked most of the blue boxes near the
bottom about network activity and suggestions and such.  I left
checked the boxes about letting me know if someone retweeted a tweet
(since that rarely happens except for one account I use as part of
work) or sent me a reply or direct message.  That should quiet down
the bird some.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Its Email - Part 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/01/its-email-part-2/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-01T23:03:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/01/its-email-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Email isn&rsquo;t just for direct communication but it can be used for
notifications, too.  I can put up a blog post or two and then send a brief
email message to a list of friends and family with the links.  This ia
actually a method of using sender-stored email where the blog post
becomes the sender-stored message and the notification is via the
email notice.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>Beyond notifications, it&rsquo;s a way to stay in touch with an exact set of
family and friends which is otherwise hard to do.  That&rsquo;s because some
are on Facebook, some on Twitter, maybe even on Google+?  Nah,
probably not Google+.  Who knows, but I think email is still
universal.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Its Email]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/01/its-email/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-01T22:53:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/01/its-email</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This is a reposting of a bit I wrote on Fri 2015-05-29.</em></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve gone round and round trying to sort out what&rsquo;s the ideal
communication solution.  For now I&rsquo;ve come back to the simple answer:
email.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>I thought email was over, that it was time to leave it behind,
relegated to just handling commercial spam and first-contact
messages.  However, in searching for some replacement that made sense,
that had a simpler storage architecture, HTTP-only transport, and so
forth, I haven&rsquo;t found a simple solution.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s still true that sender-stored email is an ideal solution, but it
requires the <em>sender</em> to do the work.  It even works, at least when
<em>I&rsquo;m</em> the sender.  However, replies and conversations are a bit more
difficult with sender-stored email than with regular email.</p>

<p>The indie web and micro-formats are also interesting moves in this
direction, but they also represent a lot of work for the participant.</p>

<p>Ultimately, Gmail ends up being an implementation that has nearly all
of the properties of any of the replacements I can imagine,
particularly when all participants are actually on Gmail.  In that
case it is all secure HTTPS to the service, storage is secure and you
can get your data out if you want to leave Gmail.</p>

<ul>
<li>One to one is straightforward.</li>
<li>One to many is BCC.</li>
<li>Many to one is straightforward.</li>
</ul>


<p>And, it turns out that Gmail in it&rsquo;s native format is very
lightweight.  My recent move toward eliminating signing messages and
removing the signature makes it nearly identical to a simple chat.
Gmail&rsquo;s presentation keeps that view clean.</p>

<p>Gmail&rsquo;s Inbox moves a couple of steps closer to the clean and simple
ideal, but then it leaves other features hard to use.  Inbox
superimposes a todo list view on the email that&rsquo;s unwanted, with the
slight redeeming quality that it does provide a way to keep the inbox
looking clean and minimal.  My recent problem with Inbox, which I&rsquo;m
using for kenguyton@gmail.com, was that I had two unread messages that
I simply could not find on the phone app even though it had a badge
saying two items were there, somewhere!  Fortunately, going back to
Inbox on the desktop showed them right up top.  There seems to be some
bug in that system, maybe in the phone-desktop interaction.</p>

<p>So, for now, I&rsquo;m going back to basics.  Email.  I&rsquo;d never have
believed it.</p>

<p>That said, I do use phone text messaging, and more specifically,
iMessage on the iPhone, for the majority of my family communication.
I use Facebook messages and Facebook for some.  I&rsquo;ve never done more
than play with direct messages on Twitter.  We use Hipchat at work
which I dislike a lot.  That model is wrong in several ways. My
biggest complaint there is that Messages aren&rsquo;t threaded.</p>

<h2>References</h2>

<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/09/30/whence-the-chat-paradigm/">Whither the Chat Paradigm</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Squeak - Back to the Future]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/26/squeak-back-to-the-future/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-26T06:45:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/26/squeak-back-to-the-future</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I still love Squeak Smalltalk.  A pointer to this paper was posted on
Hacker News Today.</p>

<p>Back to the Future<br />
The Story of Squeak, A Practical Smalltalk Written in Itself</p>

<p>by</p>

<p>Dan Ingalls, Ted Kaehler, John Maloney, Scott Wallace, Alan Kay</p>

<p><a href="http://ftp.squeak.org/docs/OOPSLA.Squeak.html">Back to the Future</a></p>

<p><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=12577087">Hacker News posting</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Appropriate Uses for SQLite]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/26/appropriate-uses-for-sqlite/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-26T06:41:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/26/appropriate-uses-for-sqlite</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From sqlite.org, <a href="https://sqlite.org/whentouse.html">Appropriate Uses For SQLite</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cosmic Distance Ladder]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/26/cosmic-distance-ladder/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-26T06:40:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/26/cosmic-distance-ladder</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On Medium: <a href="https://medium.com/starts-with-a-bang/is-the-cosmic-distance-ladder-flawed-d4d6dc8b4ce5?source=userActivityShare-c61a82880cfd%E2%80%931474882244">Is the Cosmic Distance Ladder Flawed?</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Variable Fonts]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/26/variable-fonts/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-26T06:35:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/26/variable-fonts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.wired.com/2016/09/apple-google-adobe-microsoft-join-forces-make-typographic-history/?mbid=social_fb">Tech Giants Team Up to Fix Typography’s Biggest Problem | WIRED</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Microsoft FPGAs]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/26/microsoft-fpgas/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-26T06:34:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/26/microsoft-fpgas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.wired.com/2016/09/microsoft-bets-future-chip-reprogram-fly/?mbid=social_fb">Microsoft’s Internet Business Gets a New Kind of Processor | WIRED</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Latest iPhone Home Screen]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/25/latest-iphone-home-screen/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-25T16:46:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/25/latest-iphone-home-screen</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/20160926.0559.iPhone_Homescreen.png"></p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s the most recent image of my iPhone home screen as it continues
to evolve.  I think the most recent, previous image was this one.</p>

<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/09/ios-8-dot-1/">IOS 8.1</a></p>

<!-- More -->


<h2>Vs. the Old Screen</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/20141109_iPhone.jpg"></p>

<p>Instapaper is out.  I still use it on the desktop sometime but, since
I switched to Safari (yep), it has reading mode which is easy and
basically does the same thing.</p>

<p>I really like Read Quick and I&rsquo;m a fan of Clayton and Natalie Morris,
at least when they&rsquo;re on Twit.tv podcasts.  It&rsquo;s a neat idea and it
actually works, but I just wasn&rsquo;t using it.  When I&rsquo;m commuting
(driving) and at other times I&rsquo;m more often listening than reading.  I
just stopped using it very much.</p>

<p>The dreaded Facebook has arrived.  Yeah.  I finally decided to bite
the bullet and try using Facebook for news as well as family goings on
so I listened to Robert Scoble explain to Leo Laporte how to tune
Facebook&rsquo;s news feed, groups, etc.  I&rsquo;ve been using it since February.</p>

<p>I just removed Evernote and put Byword there a few minutes ago.  I&rsquo;m a
fan of Evernote but they seem to be struggling (as the press puts it)
and I decided it was a good time to move another one of my data sinks
to the text-Markdown world.  So now I write notes using Drafts, save
them to Dropbox (where they are titled and formatted) and access them
using various Markdown formatters.  The formatter that allows both
previewing the Markdown but also editing the notes within Dropbox is
Byword.  On the Mac desktop I use Marked for previewing and, of
course, just Emacs in a terminal window to edit.  This has been
working surprisingly well.  The only thing missing right now is that
Byword doesn&rsquo;t render included images.  There are some competing
standards between apps on how that&rsquo;s done, i.e., how images are
included.  There is Multi-markdown and I think it has a standard way,
but Byword doesn&rsquo;t seem to use it.  I&rsquo;m not sure I&rsquo;ve done all of the
required homework on that one, though.</p>

<p>I still have my Evernote account and it&rsquo;s still on my phone, but just
not on the home screen.  I also exported my notes and wrote an XML
parser (well, I used the Python pre-existing XML library) to un-XML
them.</p>

<p>Drafts is a wonderful app I&rsquo;ve been using for a while.  As everyone
that talks about it says, it&rsquo;s just for entering text.  It opens super
fast and it&rsquo;s ready for you just to type.  I have it set up to take
notes and save them to Dropbox with the formatting described above.
It&rsquo;s where my notes went, even when I was using Evernote.  From other
apps&#8217; Share sheets, I can send things to Drafts so it basically
connects all of my apps together.</p>

<p>Finally, Safari.  Chrome just keeps bloating in various ways and I
heard that Safari handled battery life on the iPhone in a much better
way.  That makes sense.  It seems secure enough (but note the most
recent &ldquo;pwn&rdquo; (however you spell it) conference where Chrome withstood
and Safari fell two or three times.  I tried switching to Safari quite
a few months ago, both on the phone and desktop, and I&rsquo;ve been using
it ever since.  There are some Google apps that Chrome handles better,
mainly their finance stock charts, but usually Safari is fine.  Chrome
is still on my phone and I still use it at work.  I wouldn&rsquo;t argue
that Safari is better (except for the memory footprint, maybe faster
and with better battery management where I <em>would</em> argue it&rsquo;s better),
but it&rsquo;s seemed good enough so far.</p>

<h2>References</h2>

<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/09/ios-8-dot-1/">IOS 8.1</a><br />
<a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/02/06/tuning-facebook/">Tuning Facebook</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Triumph of the Nerds]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/24/triumph-of-the-nerds/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-24T14:42:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/24/triumph-of-the-nerds</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the best documentaries on the history of micro computing,
covering 1975 to 1995, is Robert X. Cringley&rsquo;s &ldquo;Triumph of the Nerds.&rdquo;
It&rsquo;s currently on YouTube.</p>

<p><a href="https://youtu.be/sX5g0kidk3Y">Part 1</a><br />
<a href="https://youtu.be/EiffgiRAYUI">Part 2</a><br />
<a href="https://youtu.be/ZFUsYXZSMqs">Part 3</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pictures of Telescopes by Telescopes]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/23/pictures-of-telescopes-by-telescopes/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-23T23:23:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/23/pictures-of-telescopes-by-telescopes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This outstanding article by Emily Gilbert in Medium shows pictures of
observatories made from orbiting telescopes.</p>

<p><a href="https://medium.com/planet-stories/pictures-of-telescopes-by-telescopes-ed0d2bf387c1#.lb1abjpwi">Pictures of Telescopes by Telescopes</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[No Microservices?]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/23/no-microservices/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-23T23:02:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/23/no-microservices</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>An article titled &ldquo;Microservices – Please, don’t&rdquo; caught my eye, but I
think the author has it wrong.  It&rsquo;s true we&rsquo;ve been using the micro
service approach at work, building REST/JSON servers to provice APIs,
and I have been questioning whether this is the best approach.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>This author says that these are &ldquo;truths&rdquo; &ldquo;that people believe about
this approach&hellip;.&rdquo;</p>

<ol>
<li>It keeps the code cleaner</li>
<li>It’s easy to write things that only have one purpose</li>
<li>They’re faster than monoliths</li>
<li>It’s easy for engineers to not all work in the same codebase</li>
<li>It’s the simplest way to handle autoscaling, plus Docker is in here somewhere</li>
</ol>


<p>None of these have ever been my motivation for micro services.   I
never thought 1. was the case.  Clean code is the result of good style
and discipline, and readability in writing code.</p>

<p>Similarly, I&rsquo;m not sure what 2. has to do with micro services.  I can
write modules, objects, or functions that have only one purpose.</p>

<p>I never thought 3. was true but actually the opposite.  We&rsquo;re
replacing a local function call with a network transaction.</p>

<p>Similarly, 4. is also just not true.  Whether micro services are in
the picture or not, I take it as a given that code is properly divided
into reasonable components with well-defined interfaces and that are
loosely coupled.</p>

<p>I doubt that 5. is true, but it might be.  Scale has never been a
consideration in my thinking about micro services.</p>

<p>Here are some reasons that have been part of my thought process.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>The API is language independent.  A program written in Java can
send an HTTP request as easily as a Python program, or a program in
any other language can.</p></li>
<li><p>The API is easy to test with something as simple as curl.</p></li>
<li><p>The API and HTTP request can cross network boundaries and into
different security domains, if permission is set up.</p></li>
<li><p>If a component needs to be recompiled, the micro services don&rsquo;t
need to be recompiled.</p></li>
<li><p>The micro service can be updated independently of the using code and
the clients all get the update immediately and with no changes.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>There are downsides I have worried about, though.  They include
standing up and maintaining so many services along with a lot of extra
network traffic.  It&rsquo;s also true that a well written library module is
easier to use and test in many ways.  The recompiling is not
necessarily a large cost.</p>

<p>On a very recent project at work, we went back to using libraries for
all of the application layers and components.  It&rsquo;s nice not to have
to stand up those services, but I&rsquo;ll find out if I miss some of those
advantages of the micro services.</p>

<h2>References</h2>

<p><a href="http://basho.com/posts/technical/microservices-please-dont/">Microservices – Please, don’t</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Time for Python 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/23/time-for-python-3/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-23T20:07:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/23/time-for-python-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In watching Pycon 2016 vidoes and other reading, I&rsquo;ve been struck with
the notion that it&rsquo;s actually time to move to Python 3.  More than
once in the sessions I&rsquo;ve heard a comment like &ldquo;We&rsquo;ll be using Python
3.  If you haven&rsquo;t moved to Python 3 yet, what&rsquo;s stopping you?&rdquo;</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>Good question.  There&rsquo;s the issue of some libraries not supporting
Python 3 but, in my humble beginnings, I haven&rsquo;t run into any yet.</p>

<p>Strings and UTF-8 are by far the stickiest set of issues I&rsquo;ve
encountered, but it&rsquo;s usually just a case of fixing them.  And really
I&rsquo;ve only tried converting one old program.  For new programs I&rsquo;m more
and more starting them right off in Python 3.</p>

<p>However, it&rsquo;s really recommended that you write code that runs in
both.  That takes a bit more effort and is a little more tricky.</p>

<p>Stay tuned.  I&rsquo;ll maybe update on that part next.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jekyll]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/23/jekyll/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-23T20:05:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/23/jekyll</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m not too familiar with Cloudflare but Jekyll, via Octopress, and
Github pages are what I use for this blog.</p>

<p><a href="http://adgllorente.com/2016/09/put-yourself-on-internet-with-jekyll-github-and-cloudflare/">Put yourself on internet with Jekyll, GitHub and Cloudflare</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Python Videos]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/20/python-videos/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-20T23:42:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/20/python-videos</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Lately I&rsquo;ve been watching some of the videos from Pycon and have found
these to be quite excellent.</p>

<!-- More -->


<ul>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/G-uKNd5TSBw">Keynote &ndash; Guido van Rossum &ndash; PyCon 2015</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/YgtL4S7Hrwo">Guido van Rossum &ndash; Python Language &ndash; PyCon 2016</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/KPzDX5TX5HE">Brett Cannon &ndash; How to make your code Python 2/3 compatible &ndash; PyCon 2015</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/k55d3ZUF3ZQ">Luciano Ramalho &ndash; Pythonic Objects: Implementing Productive APIs</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/6zQAu23bKF8">Harry Percival &ndash; Outside-In TDD &ndash; PyCon 2016</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/RAxiiRPHS9k">Gary Bernhardt Fast Test Slow Test</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/frZrBgWHJdY">Alex Martelli &ndash; Exception and error handling in Python 2 and Python 3 &ndash; PyCon 2016</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/E9wS6LdXM8Y">Thomas Ballinger &ndash; Finding closure with closures &ndash; PyCon 2016</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/bAcfPzxB3dk">Ned Batchelder &ndash; Machete-mode debugging &ndash; PyCon 2016</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[So Long Keith Emerson]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/03/11/so-long-keith-emerson/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-11T18:33:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/03/11/so-long-keith-emerson</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It was in about 1970 when my uncle brought some demo record LPs from a
DJ he knew.  I discovered among them the 1968 electronic Moog album
&ldquo;Switched on Bach.&rdquo;  Another album that I really loved listening to
was &ldquo;The Five Bridges Suite&rdquo; by The Nice.</p>

<p>A couple of years later, in high school, in 1972, my friend Dennis
introduced me to Emerson, Lake and Palmer and their album &ldquo;Trilogy.&rdquo;
At about the same time, my friend BJ  their first album, &ldquo;Emerson, Lake
and Palmer&rdquo; and I was as blown away.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>Progressive rock was blooming at the time.  The eclectic fusion of
classical, rock, jazz, blues and other music forms in long pieces,
sometimes in multiple movements, were made for long album cuts played
on FM radio The Atlanta station 96 Rock played a lot of progressive
rock in 1973-75.  With motifs of science fiction, fantasy, astronomy
and more, it was a perfect fit especially for the college listening
audience.  Bands like Yes, Pink Floyd, Genesis, and, often considered
by many the leader, Emerson, Lake and Palmer, were setting the pace
for this form of music.</p>

<p>It was years later that I finally realized the ELP line up was really
a traditional trio of keyboards, bass and drums.  Think of Vince
Guaraldi&rsquo;s jazz trio music for &ldquo;A Charlie Brown Christmas.&rdquo;  Often
ELP would transition into traditional jazz in just that format.</p>

<p>My favorite performance, that shows off the extreme range of their
playing, is &ldquo;Take A Pebble&rdquo; from a Belgian TV recording in 1971
(linked below), complete with a Moire projection that would make a
bridge science officer proud.  They were not a tight band, sometimes
lacking the precise virtuosity of a group like Chick Corea&rsquo;s Return To
Forever.  Sometimes it seemed like they didn&rsquo;t really like playing
together that much.  Still, their playing was inventive, talented, and
a joy to listen to.  This performance&rsquo;s rough edges and spontaneity
are part of what puts it at the top of my list.</p>

<p>Their music was ambitious, grand and rose high above the popular music
of the day.  Keith Emerson&rsquo;s stage antics were entertaining when I was
an adolescent but later I didn&rsquo;t care for them or for some the songs&#8217;
themes, but I sure was into the music.  That was what I enjoyed
listening to so much then and I still do today.  He introduced me to
composers like Mussorgsky, Aaron Copeland, and others the same way the
Allman Brothers led me to blues music.</p>

<p>ELP&rsquo;s first five albums stand as their main body of work, at least in
my view, but I liked the records that followed, particularly the
two-volume &ldquo;Works&rdquo; even though it was a mixture of pieces by a band
that was ending and solo pieces by its members.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t recall if it was in high school or as a freshman in college
that I made the connection for the first time between ELP and The
Nice&rsquo;s &ldquo;Five Bridges Suite,&rdquo; that album I enjoyed so much.  I went on
to become a fan of the early Nice music and collected several of their
records.  Even then Emerson was mixing Sibelius, Tchaikovsky, and Bach
with Bob Dylan and Coleman Hawkins, and performing live with a full
orchestra.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s surprisingly hard to say good bye to one of the great artists of
the time.</p>

<h2>Links</h2>

<p>Compare.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CBPbG1a6EP8">ELP &ndash; Take a Pebble &ndash; 1971</a></p>

<p><a href="https://youtu.be/7RSRoM_fc9I">The Nice &ndash; Hang on to a Dream &ndash; 1969</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[LIGO and the GW150914 Discovery]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/02/21/ligo-and-the-discovery/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-21T07:12:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/02/21/ligo-and-the-discovery</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I finally found the paper for the recent LIGO discovery of gravity
waves from a black hole merger, event GW150914 at 2015-09-14 09:50:45
+0000 which data implies was the merging of two black holes, one with
mass 36 (+5, -4) solar masses and the other 29 (+4, -4) solar masses
into an object of 62 (+4, -4) solar masses with 3 (+0.5, -0.5) solar
masses radiated away (lost) as emitted gravitational waves.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>B.P. Abbot and collaborators say,</p>

<blockquote><p>Over 0.2 s, the signal increases in frequency and amplitude in about 8
cycles from 35 to 150 Hz, where the amplitude reaches a maximum. The
most plausible explanation for this evolution is the inspiral of two
orbiting masses, m1 and m2, due to gravitational-wave emission.</p></blockquote>

<p>The source redshift was measured as <em>z</em>=0.09 (+0.03, -0.04).</p>

<p>One interesting outcome in the conclusions is support for massive
black holes.</p>

<blockquote><p>GW150914 demonstrates the existence of stellar-mass black holes more
massive than ≃ 25 solar masses, and establishes that binary black
holes can form in nature and merge within a Hubble time. Binary
black holes have been predicted to form both in isolated binaries
and in dense environments by dynamical interactions.  The
formation of such massive black holes from stellar evolution
requires weak massive-star winds, which are possible in stellar
environments with metallicity lower than ≃ &frac12; the solar value.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="https://dcc.ligo.org/public/0122/P150914/014/LIGO-P150914_Detection_of_GW150914.pdf">The Paper: Observation of Gravitational Waves from a Binary Black Hole Merger by B. P. Abbott et al. (pdf)</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tuning Facebook]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/02/06/tuning-facebook/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-06T12:29:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/02/06/tuning-facebook</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Okay, I&rsquo;ve decided to try using the dreaded Facebook a little more,
particularly after hearing all of the talk about instant articles in
news and more people using Messenger. I knew about this podcast of
Robert Scoble (who&rsquo;s all in on Facebook) trying to teach Leo Laporte
how to use it back in August but had never gotten around to checking
it out.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>If you want to learn how to &ldquo;really use&rdquo; Facebook in it&rsquo;s current
form, I recommend watching it and even working through this stuff.</p>

<p>So, starting around about 2016-01-30, I&rsquo;ve been trying most of what
they discuss there over the past few days and I am seeing my FB
experience much improved. There&rsquo;s a lot you can do to fine tune and
control things. I&rsquo;ll see how the news feeds compare to my Twitter
feed, etc.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=U53iO3b1K-c">Triangulation 169: Robert Scoble&rsquo;s Facebook Lesson</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
