<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2014-10-01T08:42:37-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A History of the Internet]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/01/a-history-of-the-internet/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-01T08:19:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/01/a-history-of-the-internet</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/NSFNET-backbone-T3.png"></p>

<p><a href="http://www.inetdaemon.com/tutorials/internet/history.shtml">History of the Internet</a> at InetDaemon.com is a brief and nice account of how the Internet
began.</p>

<p><em>Image credit: CC BY-SA 3.0 Merit Network, Inc.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Happy Autumnal Equinox 2014!]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/09/23/happy-autumnal-equinox-2014/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-23T04:43:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/09/23/happy-autumnal-equinox-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Happy autumnal equinox at 22:29 EDT on Mon 2014-09-22!</p>

<p>Mon 2014-09-22 22:29:00 -0400<br>
Tue 2014-09-23 02:29:00 +0000</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Venus and Jupiter Super Close Conjunction]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/08/17/venus-and-jupiter-super-close-conjunction/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-17T20:48:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/08/17/venus-and-jupiter-super-close-conjunction</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/jupiter_venus.png"></p>

<p>Tomorrow morning Mon 2014-08-18, the two brightest planets, Jupiter
and Venus, will be about 1/3 of a degree apart.  That&rsquo;s 20 arc
minutes.  This is extremely &ldquo;close&rdquo; on the sky for two planets and
will be a spectacular sight to see.</p>

<p>Not only will they be close together but they will also be near M44
the Beehive Cluster open cluster of stars.</p>

<p>Sky and Telescope Article:  <a href="http://www.skyandtelescope.com/astronomy-news/observing-news/venus-and-jupiter-spectacle-august-18-08132014/?et_mid=687137&amp;rid=247480049">Close Venus-Jupiter Conjunction on August
18th</a> by Bob King from August 13, 2014.</p>

<p><em>Image: Jupiter and Venus from Atlanta at Mon 2014-08-18 05:54:00
 -0400 (5:54 EDT).  The planets are below Castor and Pollux in Gemini.
 Image from Stellarium.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Farewell to Orkut]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/07/04/farewell-to-orkut/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-04T06:08:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/07/04/farewell-to-orkut</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/orkut.png"></p>

<p>I received an email from Google, well it says from Orkut, last night
with the subject line &ldquo;A Farewell to Orkut.&rdquo;</p>

<blockquote><p>After ten years of sparking conversations and forging connections, we
have decided it&rsquo;s time for us to start saying goodbye to Orkut. Over
the past decade, YouTube, Blogger and Google+ have taken off, with
communities springing up in every corner of the world. Because the
growth of these communities has outpaced Orkut&rsquo;s growth, we&rsquo;ve decided
to focus our energy and resources on making these other social
platforms as amazing as possible for everyone who uses them.</p></blockquote>

<p>The anecdotal evidence I&rsquo;ve heard from friends with connections in
Brazil is that most Orkut users have abandoned it for the dreaded
Facebook.  Somehow I don&rsquo;t expect they&rsquo;ve all moved over to Blogger and
Google plus.</p>

<p>In my case, I never used Orkut other than to set up an account and log
on a couple of times.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Happy Summer Solstice]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/06/22/happy-summer-solstice/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-22T07:17:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/06/22/happy-summer-solstice</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Happy Summer Solstice!</p>

<p>Sat 2014-06-21 10:51:00 +0000<br>
Sat 2014-06-21 06:51:00 -0400</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[iPhone After Eight Months]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/06/20/iphone-after-eight-months/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-20T06:17:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/06/20/iphone-after-eight-months</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/20140620_iphone.png"></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s now been eight months since I switched to the iPhone in October
2012.  The honeymoon is over and I&rsquo;ve been chewing on the green grass
for a while.  I can say I&rsquo;m just as happy and pleased with the the 5C
as I was when it was new, maybe even more.</p>

<p>It does everything I need or want it to do.  I have a nice set of apps
I use daily, a simulation and a game here or there, and generally I
can find just about anything I need in an app and it all works fine.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m still using the Gmail and the Google Maps apps for email, maps and
navigation.  Amazon cloud player was just updated and is still my
primary music player.  Netflix works fine but I typically use the
Youtube app for watching videos.</p>

<p>Apple&rsquo;s iMessage works great for texting with images and video with
the rest of the family and we all have iPhones at this point.</p>

<p>The camera continues to make great pictures, as expected.</p>

<p>Here are some of the most recent apps of significance I&rsquo;ve added.
Loom was bought by Dropbox who introduced an app called Carousel, so
I&rsquo;m not using it to automatically upload and archive photos.  Carousel
is nice as an app but there doesn&rsquo;t seem to be a correspondingly nice
web interface other then a plain Dropbox folder with a <em>lot</em> of image
files in it.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not a fan of Facebook.  In fact I don&rsquo;t like it much at all.
However, I have to say that Paper is nicely done, beautiful in some
ways, but a little quirky sometimes.  I like it many times better than
the regular Facebook interface because it&rsquo;s fun to use, but I ignore
the news feed and those other screens.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve become interested in trains lately and Trainz Driver is a fun
simulator.</p>

<p>If you compare the current image of my home screen here to the image I
<a href="http:/m149daily-blog/blog/2013/10/07/transition-to-the-iphone/">posted back in October 2012</a>, you can see that it hasn&rsquo;t changed much.
That&rsquo;s screen one and I only use three screens of apps that are about
&frac12; to 2/3 full.</p>

<p><em>Image: my current iPhone screen one.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Milky Way, Laser, and Meteor]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/04/23/milky-way/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-23T04:23:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/04/23/milky-way</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//images/observing_space.png"></p>

<p>From <a href="https://twitter.com/observingspace/status/457048425553342465">@ObservingSpace</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Milky Way and Lighthouse]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/03/01/milky-way-and-lighthouse/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-01T14:39:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/03/01/milky-way-and-lighthouse</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/milky_way_lighthouse.png"></p>

<p>This is a beautiful picture by <a href="https://twitter.com/nickventonphoto/status/393430064433352704/">Nick Venton Photo</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/nickventonphoto">@nickventonphoto</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Lost Art of the Saturn V]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/03/01/the-lost-art-of-the-saturn-v/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-01T14:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/03/01/the-lost-art-of-the-saturn-v</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/saturn-v-cutaway.jpg"></p>

<p>Wow!  This is an amazing site and article by Amy Shira Teitel.</p>

<p><a href="http://amyshirateitel.com/2011/04/03/the-lost-art-of-the-saturn-v/">The Lost Art of the Saturn V</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Python vs. Javascript]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/03/01/python-vs-javascript/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-01T14:19:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/03/01/python-vs-javascript</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been reluctantly learning some Javascript recently.  While
looking for a good summary of a feature comparison between Python and
Javascript, I found this blog post by Matt Chisholm, <a href="https://blog.glyphobet.net/essay/2557">A tour of the differences between JavaScript and Python</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gravity]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/03/01/gravity/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-01T14:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/03/01/gravity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/20140301_Space_Walk.jpg"></p>

<p>I just watched <em>Gravity</em> this morning.  It was very entertaining and I
liked the movie.</p>

<p>Congratulations are due for executing the physics of objects&#8217; motions
and the look of a so-called &ldquo;zero gravity&rdquo; (in orbit) environment so
well.  It was all believable.  I can&rsquo;t believe they didn&rsquo;t shuttle the
crew up to the ISS and shoot it on site, it was realistic enough.</p>

<p>The behaviour of tethered objects and such were pretty real.</p>

<p>However, there were some technical points to complain about.  Here&rsquo;s a
quick run down.  And, yes, there are lots of spoilers here.</p>

<p><em>Image: <a href="http://spaceflight1.nasa.gov/gallery/images/shuttle/sts-116/html/s116e06645.html">NASA Image</a>. S116-E-06645 (16 Dec. 2006)&mdash;Astronaut Robert
 L. Curbeam, Jr., STS-116 mission specialist, participates in the
 mission&rsquo;s third planned session of extravehicular activity (EVA) as
 construction resumes on the International Space Station.</em></p>

<!-- More -->


<h2>Physics</h2>

<p>A better title for the movie would have been &ldquo;Momentum.&rdquo;  Once they
got past the basics of orbital life and space, the physics wasn&rsquo;t
handled very well in some places.  For example, you don&rsquo;t need a
certain amount of thrust to get to another object.  The amount of
thrust results in a speed which only determines how long it will take
to get there.</p>

<p>Getting to the Chinese space station could be done with just thrusts
from the maneuvering thrusters.  Granted, it could take a while to get
there and there was the race against the orbiting debris (but see
below) and running out of oxygen.  If something is far away in the
orbital environment of space, you don&rsquo;t need a bigger engine the
farther away it is, unless you want to go faster and get there
sooner.  There <em>is</em> an argument to be made for having a lot of fuel
for maneuvering because rendezvous is <em>hard</em>.</p>

<h2>The Worst Flaw</h2>

<p>And while talking about momentum, we may as well get to what I
consider the worst flaw in the movie.  It occurs when Sandra Bullock&rsquo;s
and George Clooney&rsquo;s characters let go of each other and Clooney
floats off into the distance.  At that point neither of them is
moving.  They&rsquo;ve both already stopped (at least in their orbiting
frame of reference).  In reality, when they let go he&rsquo;d just hang
there.</p>

<p>Also, just the slightest tug would have started him moving back toward
the space station.  Similarly, if she could have executed a slight tug
on the parachute lines, she could have started herself or both of them
headed back, even if at a very slow speed.</p>

<p>The real problem to be solved at that moment was to make sure she
didn&rsquo;t lose the parachute line by her foot slipping off of it, or whatever
was her current situation, and also not losing their connection to
each othere.</p>

<h2>Astronaut Behaviour</h2>

<p>I don&rsquo;t think a real astronaut would be as panicked or apparently as
untrained as Sandra Bullock&rsquo;s character.   In real life, an astronaut
would be methodical, matter of fact and execute previously practiced
plans.   They would be more knowledgeable and resourceful.  They would
know where the buttons were though they would probably follow a
manual.  They would think through the problem and execute.</p>

<p>In spite of what we might have in the near future, we don&rsquo;t take
passengers into space yet.  Mission specialists are trained as
astronauts for many months.</p>

<h2>Helmet and Space Suit</h2>

<p>Why, in an emergency situation, in a compromised spacecraft, and with
a threat of further breaching, would you ever take your space suit and
helmet off?  I can buy that maybe you would have trouble getting to
some parts of a space station or craft, but a trained astronaut
wouldn&rsquo;t remove the suit until it was absolutely necessary and then
only as long as required.</p>

<p>Similarly, they would keep the helmet on when in the smaller craft and
they certainly wouldn&rsquo;t leave it bouncing around in the cabin.</p>

<h2>Use The Fire Extinguisher</h2>

<p>A fire in the cabin would quickly use up oxygen.  No one, astronaut or
not, would allow a fire to burn without using a fire extinguisher on
it.  Even if you were seconds away from splashing into the ocean.</p>

<h2>Landing</h2>

<p>Again, an astronaut would be trained well enough to execute a
landing.   They wouldn&rsquo;t open the hatch too quickly.    They would
have a flotation device ready.   They&rsquo;d know and follow the
procedure.  They would use the radio to reply to the broadcasts that
were, in English!, trying to make contact.</p>

<p>They would probably have a survival pack including a radio, marker dye
and/or strobe and other provisions.</p>

<p>I can&rsquo;t imagine they would blow the hatch, sink the capsule and end up
having to swim with nothing to a convenient shore.</p>

<h2>Chute Ejection</h2>

<p>One problem was the Soyuz being bound to the ISS by it&rsquo;s parachute.
I&rsquo;m pretty sure the parachute can be ejected with explosive bolts at
landing.  I don&rsquo;t think she&rsquo;d have had to unbolt it by hand, but could
arm and fire the bolts by pushing a button.</p>

<h2>Collision with Debris</h2>

<p>An accident and collisions are not unreal, but space is big.  Really,
really big.  The chances of such a debris cluster hitting a relatively
microscopic target, even the size of the International Space Station,
are astronomically small.  The debris cloud itself would be expanding
and getting bigger and bigger.  You might impact a single bolt or
piece of junk, and it <em>could</em> be fatal.  However, I don&rsquo;t think you&rsquo;d
have a cloud concentrated enough to stay that close together by the
time it got to the ISS even if their orbits did intersect.</p>

<p>Rendezvousing with another space craft on purpose is extremely hard.
That much random junk doing it by accident is unrealistic.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s also true that a typical orbit at that altitude, I think, has a
period of about 90 minutes.  However, if you rendezvous with something
at the same altitude, it&rsquo;s going to take anything but 90 minutes.  If
two bodies were going in opposite directions it would take at most
about 45 minutes.  If they were going in the same direction but at
slightly different speeds, then it would take a really long time, much
longer than the 90 minutes.  And, if they are going in the same
direction, the speed of impact is much lower, just the difference in
their speeds.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Quote Marks]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/01/28/quote-marks/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-28T23:05:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/01/28/quote-marks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I think for nearly 30 years I&rsquo;ve used TeX style quoting for double
quotes in anything I wrote using ASCII text.</p>

<pre><code> ``Quoted text.''
</code></pre>

<p>Now that I&rsquo;ve adopted Markdown for nearly anything that I enter as
ASCII that&rsquo;s intended to be English text (probably rich text), I&rsquo;ve
also, finally, decided to use the double-quote character.  It&rsquo;s true
that the ASCII double quote doesn&rsquo;t explicitly specify whether a left-
or right-double quote is intended, but the implication is usually
clear enough and (hopefully) rendering code is now smart enough to do
the &ldquo;right thing.&rdquo;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Supernova! SN2014J]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/01/25/supernova-sn2014j/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-25T11:07:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/01/25/supernova-sn2014j</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/supernova.jpg"></p>

<p>For the first time since SN1987A there&rsquo;s a nearby supernova and this
one was apparently caught during it&rsquo;s brightness increase.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.space.com/24369-supernova-star-explosion-amateur-photos.html">Space.com</a><br>
<a href="http://www.cbat.eps.harvard.edu/unconf/followups/J09554214+6940260.html">IAU Central Bureau for Astronomical
Telegrams: PSN
J09554214+6940260</a><br>
<a href="http://www.cnn.com/2014/01/24/opinion/urry-exploding-supernova">Nicely written article by Meg Urry at
CNN.com</a><br></p>

<p>From Meg Urry&rsquo;s article:</p>

<blockquote><p>Type Ia supernovae have happened in our galactic neighborhood only
three times in the last 80 years.</p></blockquote>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>The reason Type Ia supernovae are special is their
uniformity. Basically, they all explode at about the same mass, so
they are all roughly equally luminous. Better understanding the
physics of that explosion and the effect of local galactic environment
will make Type Ia supernovae even better “standard candles” and
improve our understanding of the properties of dark energy and the
cosmological evolution of the universe. The more data we can get, and
the closer the supernova, the better the calibration.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.ucl.ac.uk/maps-faculty/maps-news-publication/maps1405">Discovery story from University College
London</a><br></p>

<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Type_Ia_supernova">Wikipedia article on Type Ia Supernovae</a></p>

<p>Why is this supernova J only 21 days into January, i.e, the 10th
supernova so var this year?   From the International Astronomical
Union (IAU)
<a href="http://www.cbat.eps.harvard.edu/lists/RecentSupernovae.html">here&rsquo;s the list</a>
of discoveries so far.</p>

<p><em>Image credit: UCL/University of London Observatory/Steve Fossey/Ben
 Cooke/Guy Pollack/Matthew Wilde/Thomas Wright (CC BY 3.0)</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Possible Massive Black Hole Duo]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/12/04/possible-massive-black-hole-duo/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-04T05:26:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/12/04/possible-massive-black-hole-duo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Via <a href="https://twitter.com/physorg_com/status/408160199460270081">@physorg_com</a> <a href="http://phys.org/news/2013-12-massive-black-hole-duo-sighting.html">Massive black hole duo: Possible sighting by WISE</a></p>

<blockquote><p>Astronomers have spotted what appear to be two supermassive black
holes at the heart of a remote galaxy, circling each other like dance
partners. The incredibly rare sighting was made with the help of
NASA&rsquo;s Wide-field Infrared Survey Explorer, or WISE.</p></blockquote>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>It is these close-knit black holes, also called black hole binaries,
that have been the hardest to find. The objects are usually too small
to be resolved even by powerful telescopes. Only a few strong
candidates have been identified to date, all relatively nearby. The
new WISE J233237.05-505643.5 is a new candidate, and located much
farther away, at 3.8 billion light-years from Earth.</p>

<p>Radio images with the Australian Telescope Compact Array were key to
identifying the dual nature of WISE J233237.05-505643.5. Supermassive
black holes at the cores of galaxies typically shoot out
pencil-straight jets, but, in this case, the jet showed a zigzag
pattern. According to the scientists, a second massive black hole
could, in essence, be pushing its weight around to change the shape of
the other black hole&rsquo;s jet.</p></blockquote>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;We note some caution in interpreting this mysterious system,&rdquo; said
Daniel Stern of JPL, a co-author of the study. &ldquo;There are several
extremely unusual properties to this system, from the multiple radio
jets to the Gemini data, which indicate a highly perturbed disk of
accreting material around the black hole, or holes. Two merging black
holes, which should be a common event in the universe, would appear to
be simplest explanation to explain all the current observations.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<h2>References</h2>

<p><a href="http://iopscience.iop.org/0004-637X/779/1/41/pdf/0004-637X_779_1_41.pdf">WISE J233237.05–505643.5: A Double-peaked, Broad-lined Active Galactic Nucleus with a Spiral-shaped Radio Morphology</a>, Chao-Wei Tsai et al. 2013 ApJ 779 41<br>
<a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1310.2257">Paper at arXiv</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ISON Sans Nucleus]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/12/01/ison-sans-nucleus/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-01T19:15:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/12/01/ison-sans-nucleus</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Quoting from the <a href="http://www.skyandtelescope.com/observing/objects/comets/Comet-ISON-Updates-193909261.html">Sky and Telescope Updates</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Dan Green of the International Astronomical Union&rsquo;s Central Bureau for
Astronomical Telegrams published a long summary (Electronic Telegram
No. 3731) early today. Excerpts:</p>

<blockquote><p>The comet&rsquo;s nucleus apparently disrupted near perihelion, with the
comet&rsquo;s head fading from perhaps a peak brightness of visual mag –2
some hours before perihelion to well below mag +1 before
perihelion. M. Knight, Lowell Observatory&hellip; [adds] that the brightest
feature in the coma faded steadily after perihelion from about mag 3.1
in a 95&#8221;-radius aperture when the comet first appeared from behind the
SOHO coronagraph occulting disk on Nov. 28.92 to about mag 6.5 on
Nov. 29.98&hellip;..</p>

<p>K.Battams, Naval Research Laboratory, writes that, based on the most
recent LASCO C3 images (Nov. 30.912 UT) &hellip; what remains is very
diffuse, largely transparent to background stars, and fading; it
appears that basically a cloud of dust remains&hellip;.</p>

<p>Z.Sekanina, Jet Propulsion Laboratory &hellip; finds that the comet&rsquo;s
production of dust terminated about 3 hours before perihelion&hellip;</p>

<p>The strong forward-scattering effect (phase angles near 120-130 deg)
has tempered the rate of post-perihelion fading of the comet, but the
merciless inverse-square power law of increasing heliocentric distance
is necessarily the dominant factor in the comet&rsquo;s forthcoming gradual
disappearance&hellip;</p></blockquote></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://groups.yahoo.com/neo/groups/comets-ml/conversations/messages/22839">CBET 3731 via Yahoo Groups</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/bad_astronomy/2013/12/01/comet_ison_post_mortem.html">A post mortem by Phil Plait</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Whither ISON]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/11/30/whither-ison/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-30T19:41:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/11/30/whither-ison</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From CIOC (the NASA <a href="http://www.isoncampaign.org/karl/a-trail-of-questions">Comet ISON Observing Campaign</a>):</p>

<blockquote><p>Will it be naked eye visible? When? How bright?</p>

<p>This is definitely the toughest question but also the most
frequent. We still don&rsquo;t know if it will be naked eye but based on its
current brightness in the LASCO images &ndash; which is around magnitude +5
and fading &ndash; it does seem unlikely that there will be much to see in
the night sky. I suspect that some of the outstanding
astrophotographers around the world will be able to get something, but
I doubt it will be as spectacular as before perihelion. I hope I&rsquo;m
wrong though.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.skyandtelescope.com/observing/ataglance">Sky and Telescope</a><br></p>

<p><a href="http://www.skyandtelescope.com/observing/objects/comets/Comet-ISON-Updates-193909261.html">Sky and Telescope Updates</a><br></p>

<p><a href="http://www.isoncampaign.org/karl/a-trail-of-questions">ISON Campaign: A Trail of Questions</a><br></p>

<p><a href="http://www.universetoday.com/106832/zombie-ison-behaving-like-a-comet-stunned-astronomers-say/">Universe Today</a><br></p>

<p><a href="http://apod.nasa.gov/apod/ap131130.html">APOD</a><br></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comet ISON Post Perihelion]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/11/29/comet-ison-post-perihelion/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-29T14:24:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/11/29/comet-ison-post-perihelion</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/comet_ison_postp.png"></p>

<p>Reports are starting to come in regarding what happened to Comet ISON
C/2012 S1 after passing the perihelion of its orbit.</p>

<p>From
<a href="https://twitter.com/astroengine/status/406342402706665472">@astroengine</a>
and <a href="https://twitter.com/discovery_space/status/406342053455347712">@discovery_space</a>:
 <a href="http://news.discovery.com/space/astronomy/comet-ison-barely-survives-thanksgiving-solar-roast-131129.htm">Comet ISON Barely Survives Thanksgiving Solar
 Roast</a><br></p>

<p>Update from NASA CIOC: <a href="http://www.isoncampaign.org/karl/schroedingers-comet">Schrödinger&rsquo;s Comet</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[More Comet ISON]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/11/24/more-comet-ison/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-24T17:02:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/11/24/more-comet-ison</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>More news and mostly images of Comet ISON C/2012 S1.</p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/earthskyscience/status/404265533240930304">Today&rsquo;s Image form @EarthSky</a>.<br>
<a href="https://twitter.com/chrislintott/status/404698473317928960">Will Gater picture via @chrislintott</a>
<a href="https://twitter.com/willgater/status/404643457924210689">Picture via @willgater</a><br>
<a href="https://twitter.com/chrislintott/status/404684115506909184">And Another via @chrislintott</a><br>
<a href="https://twitter.com/SungrazerComets/status/404282911290953728">From @SungrazerComets</a><br></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comet ISON C/2012 S1]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/11/24/comet-ison-c-slash-2012-s1/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-24T00:03:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/11/24/comet-ison-c-slash-2012-s1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From EarthSky</p>

<blockquote><p>Comet ISON, anticipated by skywatchers for more than a year, is
brightening fast just days from its fateful hairpin swing on November
28 around the broiling surface of the sun. The comet is now a
greenish-white fuzzy “star” in binoculars, low in the east-southeast
at the beginning of dawn. Telescopic photos are showing it with a
long, ribbony tail. The comet has flared with unexpected outbursts of
gas and dust three times already this month.</p></blockquote>

<h2>References</h2>

<p><a href="http://earthsky.org/science-wire/comet-ison-brightening-fast-as-its-moment-of-truth-nears">Comet ISON brightening fast as its moment of truth nears</a><a href="https://twitter.com/earthskyscience/status/403314232701091840">via @earthskyscience</a><br>
<a href="http://www.observatorij.org/cobs/images/latest-lightcurve.png">Latest Light Curve</a><br>
<a href="http://spaceweathergallery.com/indiv_upload.php?upload_id=90223&amp;PHPSESSID=34o31mq8nus0r94icsrtd1mh73">Image by Bob Lukasik from Brasstown Bald 2103-11-20</a><br>
<a href="http://www.isoncampaign.org/karl/updated-ison-encke-movie">ISON Encke Movie</a><br>
<a href="http://www.isoncampaign.org/karl/ison-encke-mercury-home">ISON, Encke, Mercury and Home by Karl Battams</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Evernote Encryption]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/11/15/evernote-encryption/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-15T09:32:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/11/15/evernote-encryption</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Nice!  Evernote let&rsquo;s you encrypt the text in a note!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
