<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2015-01-14T08:18:59-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[NixOS Linux]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/01/14/nixos-linux/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-14T08:04:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/01/14/nixos-linux</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I don&rsquo;t recall hearing of NixOS Linux until a tweet crossed my Twitter
feed about a new release during the week between Christmas and New
Year&rsquo;s.  I looked it up and was fascinating by the new ideas and
approaches there.  Here&rsquo;s my awkward summar.</p>

<ul>
<li>Packages are immutable, like values in a functional language. Making configuration changes involves generating a new package.</li>
<li>Each package instance, each version, is stored on the system in it&rsquo;s
own directory.  Files aren&rsquo;t installed all over the place in /usr/local/lib, /usr/lib, /usr/local/bin, etc.</li>
<li>Due to the above, aliases are much more important than search paths.</li>
<li>Also, the dependency tree for a package is very straightforward.</li>
<li>System configuration is via a functional language and is a single expression in one file.</li>
<li>So you can easily boot and run any configuration, back out changes, etc.</li>
</ul>


<p>I installed it on a Virtual box VM and played with it briefly.  One of
the first negative things I noticed was a ps listing.  Since each
package instance is under a single nixos directory with a directory
named by a long random hash, and since every running process is in a
bin directory (or some such) in one of those, the path to any running
program is a bear.</p>

<p>I pulled down nginx.  That was easy.  But then I went to configure it
and that&rsquo;s where I came face to face with NixOS&#8217; trade off.  You don&rsquo;t
change files in a package.  As I understand it so far, you add code
into the single configuration file that essentially edits, in this
case, the nginx config file in a sort of sed-like way, and produces a
new package instance that is used.  So a nice and simple config file
from nginx was turned into a functional language expression that now
requires me to go learn that language.</p>

<p>I stopped at that point but I&rsquo;m still fascinated by the distribution
and the ideas there.  There are some nice hard lines and properties of
cleanliness here.  Once the investment is made in learning the Nix
config language, it may be straightforward to move on and maintain
systems.  For a simple server instance this may be something to try.</p>

<p>So, I&rsquo;ll move on with it soon and see how it goes.</p>

<p><a href="http://nixos.org/">Nixos.org</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bazaar]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/01/14/bazaar/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-14T07:33:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/01/14/bazaar</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From looking at my development directories, it appears that it was in
early 2008 that I moved my personal source code control system from
CVS to Bazaar.  (Before that I&rsquo;d used RCS and even SCCS) I learned
about Bazaar from a coworker, John.  It was Python-based, the system
used by Canonical for Ubuntu and I found it to work extremely well.
Since then, for seven years now, I&rsquo;ve used it for my personal version
management and also as a shadow version control system at work.</p>

<p>It has been extremely stable for me, fast, and I can&rsquo;t think of any
trouble I&rsquo;ve ever had with Bazaar.  However, lately I&rsquo;ve seen
indications that Bazaar is no longer maintained and may be declining
as a version control choice.  Maybe it was never that popular.</p>

<p>Lately, Git seems to be the version control system of choice and it is
the system I use every day for work.  I&rsquo;m wondering if I should start
using it for my personal work.  The command set and, as they say, &ldquo;the
workflow&rdquo; is different.  It&rsquo;s not friendly to large binary blobs.
That&rsquo;s probably okay.</p>

<p>I already like it less because, if I want to make a branch of a
particular version or another branch to work on, there needs to be a
root branch of sorts, a hub to clone the other branch from.  With
Bazaar you can just branch any branch, merge changes from it, etc.  So
now I&rsquo;ll have to make some local hub to clone, push and pull from.
Yech.  That seems so archaic now.</p>

<p>However, I found this blog post by Jelmer Vernooij who was a primary
developer of Bazaar.  He basically tells the complete history and also
how it&rsquo;s finally been abandoned for the most part.  So, I guess I
should start moving on to git.</p>

<p>I won&rsquo;t even try to convert over my current bzr projects.  There is
Mercurial which may be worth a look.  Ah well.</p>

<blockquote><p>Contributions from people outside of the Canonical Bazaar team had
become rare by mid-2011. In early 2012 the members of the Canonical
Bazaar team were assigned to other projects, though we would still fix
the occasional bug in Bazaar. Martin left Canonical in April 2012.</p>

<p>During my spare time in the first 6 months of 2012 I tried to finish
my remaining in-progress branches. After that, I thought I would see
how it would go.</p>

<p>I think it&rsquo;s time to move on. There are still some things I don&rsquo;t like
about it, but Git is a decent source code management system. Bazaar
isn&rsquo;t going anywhere; no doubt there will be users for a few years to
come, and people contributing fixes, but it hasn&rsquo;t been adopted to the
level I was hoping.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.stationary-traveller.eu/pages/bzr-a-retrospective.html">Bazaar-NG: 7 years of hacking on a distributed version control system</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Intel Gave Stephen Hawking a Voice]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/01/14/how-intel-gave-stephen-hawking-a-voice/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-14T07:28:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/01/14/how-intel-gave-stephen-hawking-a-voice</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From Wired by Joao Medeiros.</p>

<blockquote><p>Hawking is very attached to his voice: in 1988, when Speech Plus gave
him the new synthesizer, the voice was different so he asked them to
replace it with the original. His voice had been created in the early
&lsquo;80s by MIT engineer Dennis Klatt, a pioneer of text-to-speech
algorithms. He invented the DECtalk, one of the first devices to
translate text into speech. He initially made three voices, from
recordings of his wife, daughter and himself. The female’s voice was
called &ldquo;Beautiful Betty&rdquo;, the child’s &ldquo;Kit the Kid&rdquo;, and the male
voice, based on his own, &ldquo;Perfect Paul.&rdquo; &ldquo;Perfect Paul&rdquo; is Hawking&rsquo;s
voice.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.wired.com/2015/01/intel-gave-stephen-hawking-voice/">How Intel Gave Stephen Hawking a Voice</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Happy Winter Solstice 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/12/21/happy-winter-solstice-2014/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-21T05:53:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/12/21/happy-winter-solstice-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Happy winter solstice!  The event occurs today 21 Dec 2014 at 18:03
EST.</p>

<p>Sun 2014-12-21 18:03:00 -0500<br />
Sun 2014-12-21 23:03:00 +0000<br /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/magazine-30549149">Why do mornings still get darker after the winter solstice? from BBC News</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Siracusa on Swift]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/12/20/siracusa-on-swift/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-20T13:05:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/12/20/siracusa-on-swift</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>John Siracusa&rsquo;s review of each OS X version are legendary, but the
10.10 article has a nice dive down into some of the details of the new
Swift language and how it&rsquo;s compiled.  There are some impressive
features here.</p>

<p><a href="http://arstechnica.com/apple/2014/10/os-x-10-10/21/#swift">OS X 10.10 Yosemite: The Ars Technica Review, Swift</a><br />
<a href="https://developer.apple.com/swift/">Introducing Swift at Apple Developer</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Buying a Telescope]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/12/10/buying-a-telescope/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-10T08:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/12/10/buying-a-telescope</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In November, during the 30-day blog challenge, I wrote a series of
posts on buying a telescope.  With slight editing, I&rsquo;ve combined them
into a single document which also has a link in the menu up top.</p>

<p><a href="http://10.0.0.23/m149daily-blog/telescope/">Buying a Telescope</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Go and Swift]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/12/10/go-and-swift/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-10T07:57:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/12/10/go-and-swift</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Scott Rosenberg writes &ldquo;Code of Ages, Go and Swift take another step
up the programming-language ladder.&rdquo;</p>

<p><a href="https://medium.com/backchannel/my-computer-language-is-better-than-yours-58d9c9523644">From Medium</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Warning: Don't Lose Your Apple ID Recovery Key]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/12/10/apple-id-recovery-key/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-10T07:51:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/12/10/apple-id-recovery-key</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Setting up two-factor authentication is a good idea, but it&rsquo;s
important to carefully save your recovery key in a safe place where
you won&rsquo;t lose it.</p>

<p>This story by Owen Williams makes this point clear.</p>

<p><a href="http://thenextweb.com/apple/2014/12/08/lost-apple-id-learnt-hard-way-careful-two-factor-authentication/">From The Next Web, The dark side of Apple’s two-factor authentication</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Robert Truax - Rocketeer]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/12/05/robert-truax-rocketeer/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-05T06:07:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/12/05/robert-truax-rocketeer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In a time of Richard Branson and Virgin Galactic, along with
impressive amateur rocketeers and commercial space ventures, we might
have forgotten about Bob Truax, one of the first commercial, private
rocket jockeys.</p>

<p>From Wikipedia,</p>

<blockquote><p>Truax also designed the Skycycle X-2, which he unsuccessfully tested
on April 15, 1972 and June 24, 1973, and which Evel Knievel
unsuccessfully used at the Snake River Canyon in 1974.</p></blockquote>

<p>And also,</p>

<blockquote><p>The X-3 Volksrocket (other names: Arriba One, Skycycle X-3) was a
reusable space tourism rocket planned by Robert Truax after Evel
Knievel provided a $1,000 research grant for a pilot study. Truax
was looking for volunteers with enough money to help fund the effort
and who wished to fly aboard his rocket. He got thousands of
volunteers, but few of them had the financial resources.</p>

<p>The rocket used surplus components and was tested through 1991.</p></blockquote>

<p>There was actually a TV show based on Truax called <em>Salvage 1</em> and
starring Andy Griffith in 1979.</p>

<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Truax">Wikipedia article on Robert Truax</a>.<br />
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nuW9bsp3Z2w">Salvage 1 Series Pilot on Youtube</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Can You Cross a Wormhole?]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/21/can-you-cross-a-wormhole/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-21T08:04:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/21/can-you-cross-a-wormhole</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Do worm holes even exist?  At Smithsonian.com, Victoria Jaggard
writes the article &ldquo;Would Astronauts Survive an Interstellar Trip Through a
Wormhole?&rdquo;</p>

<p>Given the state of current physics the answer is, No.  The idea of
worm holes has come and gone in the science world, though it never
quite leaves.  The Kerr metric solution to Einstein&rsquo;s general
relativity equations applies to &ldquo;rotating&rdquo; black holes and adds new
twists, however there&rsquo;s still not really a way for humans to get
through.</p>

<p>Just like crossing an event horizon is beyond the edge of our
universe, these ideas are beyond the edge of our science.  Of course
we don&rsquo;t know everything and I have no doubt there are amazing things
still to be discovered.  I&rsquo;d never say it can&rsquo;t happen, just that we
don&rsquo;t have a good mechanism in our current astrophysics toolbox unless
we toss in a little magic.  Just like it is with faster-than-light
travel.</p>

<blockquote><p>Despite his ties to the film, [cosmologist Kip] Thorne is also
pessimistic that a traversable wormhole is even possible, much less
survivable. &ldquo;If they can exist, I doubt very much that they can form
naturally in the astrophysical universe,&rdquo; he writes in the book. But
Thorne appreciates that Christopher and Jonah Nolan, who wrote
Interstellar, were so keen to tell a story that is grounded in
science.</p></blockquote>

<p>There&rsquo;s more to come on this topic and other folks have weighed in.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.smithsonianmag.com/science-nature/would-astronauts-survive-interstellar-trip-through-wormhole-180953269/">Would Astronauts Survive an Interstellar Trip Through a Wormhole?</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sudden Galaxies]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/19/sudden-galaxies/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-19T08:12:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/19/sudden-galaxies</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>A team of astronomers using the Subaru Telescope&rsquo;s Suprime-Cam to
perform the Subaru Ultra-Deep Survey for Lyman-alpha Emitters have
looked back more than [<em>z=7</em>] to find 7 early galaxies that
appeared quite suddenly within 700 million years of the Big Bang. The
team, led by graduate student Akira Konno and Dr. Masami Ouchi
(Associate Professor at the University of Tokyo&rsquo;s ICRR) was looking
for a specific kind of galaxy called a Lyman-alpha emitter (LAE), to
understand the role such galaxies may have played in an event called
&ldquo;cosmic reionization&rdquo;.</p></blockquote>

<p>The team looked at distant galaxies that primarily emit Lyman-alpha
radiation, &ldquo;Lyman-alpha emitters&rdquo; or LAE, and saw fewer than expected,
further back in time.  There&rsquo;s an apparent sudden cutoff at that
redshift.  The redshift corresponds to a distance and time in history
that&rsquo;s model dependent.  The standard big bang model would put this at
about 13.1 billion years and only 700 million years after the big bang
itself.  The cosmological-history implication is that these galaxies
&ldquo;suddenly&rdquo; appear.</p>

<p>One thing is pretty certain.  A cosmological redshift of seven
indicates the universe was about 1/8 it&rsquo;s current size at the time the
light they observed was emitted.  That&rsquo;s 1 / (<em>z</em> + 1).</p>

<blockquote><p>According to the team&rsquo;s analysis, one reason that LAEs appeared very
quickly is cosmic reionization. LAEs in the epoch of cosmic
reionization became darker than the actual luminosity due to the
presence of the neutral hydrogen fog. In the team&rsquo;s analysis of their
observations, they suggest the possibility that the neutral fog
filling the universe was cleared about 13.0 billion years ago and LAEs
suddenly appeared in sight for the first time.&#8221;</p>

<p>&ldquo;However, there are other possibilities to explain why LAEs appeared
suddenly,&rdquo; said Dr. Ouchi, who is the principal investigator of this
program. &ldquo;One is that clumps of neutral hydrogen around LAEs
disappeared. Another is that LAEs became intrinsically bright. The
reason of the intrinsic brightening is that the Lyman-alpha emission
is not efficiently produced by the ionized clouds in a LAE due to the
significant escape of ionizing photons from the galaxy. In either
case, our discovery is an important key to understanding cosmic
reionization and the properties of the LAEs in early universe.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://phys.org/news/2014-11-subaru-telescope-sudden-galaxies-early.html">Subaru Telescope detects sudden appearance of galaxies in the early universe at phys.org</a><br />
<a href="http://www.icrr.u-tokyo.ac.jp/2014/11/19120001.html">Press release from ICRR</a><br />
<a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1404.6066v2.pdf">PDF of paper &ldquo;Accelerated Evolution Of The Lyα Luminosity Function At z >~ 7 Revealed By The Subaru Ultra-Deep Survey For Lyα Emitters AT z = 7.3&rdquo;</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dark and Stormy]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/18/dark-and-stormy/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-18T07:09:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/18/dark-and-stormy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>While looking for earlier posts about kids and programming, I came
across this from a 2005-02-08 post.  Someone sent this to me and I
don&rsquo;t know if it&rsquo;s real or not.  In any event, I enjoyed these.</em></p>

<hr />

<p>These came from the annual &ldquo;Dark and Stormy Night&rdquo; competition. Actual
analogies and metaphors found in high school essays:</p>

<ol>
<li>Her face was a perfect oval, like a circle that had its two sides
gently compressed by a Thigh Master.</li>
</ol>


<!-- More -->


<ol>
<li><p>His thoughts tumbled in his head, making and breaking alliances
like underpants in a dryer without Cling Free.</p></li>
<li><p>He spoke with the wisdom that can only come from experience, like a
guy who went blind because he looked at a solar eclipse without one of
those boxes with a pinhole in it and now goes around the country
speaking at high schools about the dangers of looking at a solar
eclipse without one of those boxes with a pinhole in it.</p></li>
<li><p>She grew on him like she was a colony of E. coli and he was
room-temperature Canadian beef.</p></li>
<li><p>She had a deep, throaty, genuine laugh, like that sound a dog makes
just before it throws up.</p></li>
<li><p>Her vocabulary was as bad as, like, whatever.</p></li>
<li><p>He was as tall as a six-foot-three-inch tree.</p></li>
<li><p>The revelation that his marriage of 30 years had disintegrated
because of his wife&rsquo;s infidelity came as a rude shock, like a
surcharge at a formerly surcharge-free ATM.</p></li>
<li><p>The little boat gently drifted across the pond exactly the way a
bowling
ball wouldn&rsquo;t.</p></li>
<li><p>McBride fell 12 stories, hitting the pavement like a Hefty bag
filled with vegetable soup.</p></li>
<li><p>From the attic came an unearthly howl. The whole scene had an
eerie, surreal quality, like when you&rsquo;re on vacation in another city
and Jeopardy comes on at 7:00 p.m. instead of 7:30.</p></li>
<li><p>Her hair glistened in the rain like a nose hair after a sneeze.</p></li>
<li><p>The hailstones leaped from the pavement, just like maggots when
you fry them in hot grease.</p></li>
<li><p>Long separated by cruel fate, the star-crossed lovers raced across
the grassy field toward each other like two freight trains, one having
left Cleveland at 6:36 p.m. traveling at 55 mph, the other from Topeka
at 4:19 p.m. at a speed of 35 mph.</p></li>
<li><p>They lived in a typical suburban neighborhood with picket fences
that resembled Nancy Kerrigan&rsquo;s teeth.</p></li>
<li><p>John and Mary had never met. They were like two hummingbirds who
had also never met.</p></li>
<li><p>He fell for her like his heart was a mob informant and she was the
East River.</p></li>
<li><p>Even in his last years, Grandpappy had a mind like a steel trap,
only one that had been left out so long, it had rusted shut.</p></li>
<li><p>Shots rang out, as shots are wont to do.</p></li>
<li><p>The plan was simple, like my brother-in-law Phil. But unlike Phil,
this plan just might work.</p></li>
<li><p>The young fighter had a hungry look, the kind you get from not
eating for a while.</p></li>
<li><p>He was as lame as a duck. Not the metaphorical lame duck, either,
but a real duck that was actually lame, maybe from stepping on a land
mine or something.</p></li>
<li><p>The ballerina rose gracefully en pointe and extended one slender
leg behind her, like a dog at a fire hydrant.</p></li>
<li><p>It was an American tradition, like fathers chasing kids around
with power tools.</p></li>
<li><p>He was deeply in love. When she spoke, he thought he heard bells,
as if she were a garbage truck backing up.</p></li>
<li><p>Her eyes were like limpid pools, only they had forgotten to put in
any pH cleanser.</p></li>
<li><p>She walked into my office like a centipede with 98 missing legs.</p></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Programming for Kids]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/18/programming-for-kids/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-18T06:26:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/18/programming-for-kids</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There&rsquo;s a question that have been worrying many of us for quite a few
years now.  How will today&rsquo;s kids learn to program?</p>

<p>In the late 70s and 80s many kids were blessed with a microcomputer in
their home that ran BASIC.  Most folks don&rsquo;t even know or remember
that the first IBM PC booted straight up into BASIC, just like a
Commodore 64. That&rsquo;s where they learned to program.  Those BASIC
computers launched a whole generation of computer programmers.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>But then, as time went on, computers no longer came with BASIC.
Magazines no longer published programs that you had to type in, line
by line, hopefully with an input program that gave a little checksum
for each line to match with the checksum in the original listing.
I&rsquo;ve thought about this for many years and the topic has been raised
by others, even on sites like Slashdot over the years.  How will kids
learn to program?</p>

<p>Java seemed too complex for kids to really latch on to.  There were
plenty of little learning languages here and there, but they didn&rsquo;t
just pop up on the family computer when you turned it on&mdash;-someone had
to go looking for them and install them.</p>

<p>Some people speculated that making web pages might capture the modern
youth&rsquo;s enthusiasm.  But (at least normal) HTML doesn&rsquo;t have the
concept of a conditional if-then clause.  I consider that an essential
element of programming.</p>

<p>I used to think how it would be nice if there was something like a
world, as in object-oriented MUDs, where you could program little
objects to do conditional things.  That would be like building a web
page or something, but you could make things &ldquo;smart&rdquo; so they responded
to changes in their surroundings or to inputs.</p>

<p>Lately I&rsquo;ve been hearing a pattern.  I&rsquo;ve heard it at least a couple
of times and I bet it&rsquo;s happening more.  Kids are learning to program
via the path Minecraft, Scratch, Python.</p>

<p>Minecraft is a game where you can build an program objects.  And it
does have conditionals!  Nearly every kid seems to be playing
Minecraft.</p>

<p>Scratch is a wonderful programming language based on clicking little
objects together that do things.  It&rsquo;s the perfect programming
paradigm for youngsters.  Scratch was developed at the MIT Media Lab.</p>

<p>Finally, there&rsquo;s Python, which I consider the perfect programming
language for a majority of purposes including a first real programming
language.</p>

<p>I think this is the perfect path.  Minecraft is wonderfully engaging
and pretty much universally present.  Scratch has all of the
fundamental elements you need, and it&rsquo;s still fun.  Python is
complete, readily available, and programs can be as easy as BASIC but
can grow into fully developed object-oriented or even functional
applications.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s highly likely I won&rsquo;t even understand what the
Minecraft-Scratch-Python generation produces as adults, but I&rsquo;m sure
it will be wonderful!</p>

<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BASIC">BASIC</a><br />
<a href="https://minecraft.net/">Minecraft</a><br />
<a href="http://scratch.mit.edu/">Scratch</a><br />
<a href="http://monolith149daily.blogspot.com/2008/10/scratch-programming-for-kids.html">My Scratch Programming blog post, 2008-10-02</a><br />
<a href="https://www.python.org/">Python</a><br /></p>

<p>P.S.  Yes, I know that there are, in fact, many tools around for kids
to learn from.  Even Logo and of course BASIC are still around!  They
just aren&rsquo;t universally present by default on the home computer until
someone puts them there.</p>

<p>P.P.S.  And it&rsquo;s also true that the Raspberry Pi was intentionally
created to fill this void with hardware that nearly any kid could
afford and just hook to their TV and power with their phone charger.
(You do need a keyboard and mouse).  Not coincidentally, it comes with
Scratch and Python ready to go and can be configured to boot straight
into those environments.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Indie Web]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/17/indie-web/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-17T08:22:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/17/indie-web</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since I first began the 30-day blogging challenge the indie web
movement was on my list of topics to discus.  My thinking on
it, and related topics, is still unsettled.  I&rsquo;ve read some and, well,
read some more.  Kevin Marks frequently appears on the Twit network
and particularly on <em>This Week in Google</em>, and has talked about the
indie web on many occasions.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a brief and early poll on where I am so far.  I like the basic
principle of owning all of your content.  That&rsquo;s the foundation of
this very site, this blog.  I don&rsquo;t like strongly coupling my various
identities across sites, not that strongly.  I prefer that they be
weakly coupled, if at all.  I&rsquo;m not that interested in discussions,
engagement and feedback.  At least not in the usual way they occur on
the web.</p>

<p>Microformats comprise a clever and intriguing idea.  I think there&rsquo;s value
in this evolved approach to (this part of) the so-called semantic
web.</p>

<p>The microformats movement has eschewed email and gone to using IRC
(Internet Relay Chat) and a wiki for their communication.  This hits
at the communication problems that I spend a lot of my
internet-thinking time on.  Email seems terribly inadequate in many
ways and yet insists being the best fit for many needs, particularly
when Gmail is used.  I agree with not using email for long messages or
long documents&mdash;I&rsquo;ve adopted a similar approach to communication.
(For long documents and messages I email a Google document instead of
a long email message).</p>

<p>I loathe using IRC.  That in itself is worth at least one long blog
post.  We use it at work since I&rsquo;ve been unable to stave off the push
by the millennials (plus or minus) there to use IRC.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s a very nice &ldquo;indie web in a box,&rdquo; With Known, which you can
even get a hosted account with.  At first, that seems anti-indie-web,
but it&rsquo;s all very well done.  The source is open and you can start on
their servers then move onto your own when you wish, similar to using
Wordpress.</p>

<p>So that&rsquo;s a quick update.  There should be more to come.</p>

<p><a href="http://indiewebcamp.com/">Indie Web Camp</a><br />
<a href="http://microformats.org/">Microformats</a><br />
<a href="http://www.kevinmarks.com/">Kevin Marks</a><br />
<a href="http://twit.tv/">Twit.tv</a><br />
<a href="https://withknown.com/">Known</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ray Bradbury - If Only We Had Taller Been]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/12/ray-bradbury/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-12T23:31:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/12/ray-bradbury</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/ray_bradbury.png" title="" ></p>

<p>On 12 November 1971, exactly 43 years ago, Ray Bradbury spoke to an
audience at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory on the eve of Mariner 9
arriving at Mars.  On stage with him were Arthur C. Clarke, Carl
Sagan, Bruce Murray, and Walter Sullivan.  Bradbury read his poem, &ldquo;If
Only We Had Taller Been.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Today, on 12 November 2014, the Philae spacecraft &ldquo;docked&rdquo; with the
comet 67P/Churyumov-Gerasimenko.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EBtZjbTDTDk">Youtube Video &ndash; Ray Bradbury &ndash; If Only We Had Taller Been</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rosetta]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/11/rosetta/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-11T05:12:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/11/rosetta</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/NAVCAM_top_10_at_10_km_3_node_full_image_2.jpg"></p>

<p>From the ESA web site.</p>

<blockquote><p>Rosetta is a cornerstone mission to chase, go into orbit around, and
land on a comet. It is studying the Jupiter-family comet
67P/Churyumov-Gerasimenko with a combination of remote sensing and in
situ measurements. The spacecraft arrived at the comet on 6 August
2014 following a 10-year journey through the Solar System. Between
August and November, the spacecraft has been orbiting the comet and
gathering data to characterise the environment and the comet
nucleus. On 12 November 2014, Rosetta&rsquo;s lander Philae will be deployed
to the surface. Philae carries a suite of instruments for imaging and
sampling the comet nucleus. The Rosetta orbiter will track the comet
through perihelion (August 2015), examining its behaviour before,
during and after.</p></blockquote>

<p>[SIC]:  I saw a pronunciation guide for Philae that said &ldquo;fee-lay.&rdquo;
This is wrong.  The pronunciation rhymes with eye-lee, or &ldquo;highly.&rdquo;
Whenever you see ae, it rhymes with ee as in leek.  For example,
Caesar.  And yes, the UNIX-famous word &ldquo;daemon&rdquo; is pronounced
precisely and exactly like demon. Other pronunciations are wrong.
(<a href="http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/philae">Merriam-Webster</a>,
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philae">Wikipedia</a>).</p>

<p><a href="http://sci.esa.int/rosetta/">ESA Rosetta Site</a><br />
<a href="http://sci.esa.int/rosetta/2279-summary/">Summary</a><br />
<a href="http://www.esa.int/Our_Activities/Space_Science/Rosetta/Highlights/Top_10_at_10_km">Top 10 images from 10 km</a><br />
<a href="http://earthsky.org/space/watch-wednesdays-comet-landing-live-online">EarthSky &ndash; Watch Wednesday’s comet landing live online</a><br /></p>

<p><em>Image: ESA/Rosetta/NAVCAM – CC BY-SA IGO 3.0</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[IOS Reliable Updates]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/10/ios-reliable-updates/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-10T06:42:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/10/ios-reliable-updates</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are two key reasons that I&rsquo;m overjoyed to have made the switch
from Android to IOS and the iPhone.</p>

<p>One is the reliability of OS updates.  There&rsquo;s no worrying about
pure-Google vs. vendor-imposed-UI and junk apps. There&rsquo;s no waiting
for a vendor to either roll out an update or, more likely, just force
you to buy a new phone or wait for your cycle to end to get a new
phone.</p>

<p>The IOS updates are (so far) annual, universal and hassle
free.  And by hassel free I&rsquo;m referring to the above issues.  It&rsquo;s
granted there have been hiccups and bugs, but usually they are
resolved in a reasonable time.  I try to be cautious and wait for a
minor update or to before diving in.  Thus, I skipped 8.0 and waited
for 8.1.</p>

<p>The other joy is from the pictures the iPhones make.  There are
Android phones with better camera specs on paper, and yet, the photos
are often just not up to par.  My Galaxy Nexus made images that ranged
from okay to terrible.  When I go back and look at them now, they look
even worse than I realized.  I know other people disagree but I&rsquo;m
firmly in the camp: There&rsquo;s no contest here.</p>

<p>So, that makes two items removed from the list of things to have to
deal with.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Blog Stats From 30 Days]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/10/blog-stats-from-30-days/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-10T06:35:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/10/blog-stats-from-30-days</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For what it&rsquo;s worth:</p>

<p>30 days<br />
39 posts<br />
10575 words</p>

<p>The words include the blog heading.  That&rsquo;s an average of 271 words
per post and 1757 characters per post.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[After Blogging for 30 Days]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/10/after-blogging-for-30-days/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-10T05:17:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/10/after-blogging-for-30-days</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well, It&rsquo;s now day 31 and I&rsquo;ve finished the <a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">30-day challenge</a> to blog for 30
days.  The original challenge that I read didn&rsquo;t include weekends but I
went ahead and blogged straight through since there&rsquo;s actually more
time to write on the weekend than during the week.</p>

<p>I did manage to put a post up every day with the exception of day 23.
I wrote the day 22 and 23 entries on day 22 using my Kindle HD Fire,
Draft and Dropbox and didn&rsquo;t actually post them until day 24.  I
didn&rsquo;t actually do any writing on day 23.  I&rsquo;ll leave it to the 30-day
blogging judges to decide how to count that.</p>

<p>Some posts were long, some were medium length, some had pictures and
links, some were only a link, a couple were basically just
&ldquo;re-tweets.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Reflecting on the experience I&rsquo;m amazed at how short 30 days is.  It
doesn&rsquo;t seem like there are 30+ posts and it felt like a much shorter
time.  But then, 30 days, months, years do seem to go by super-fast
lately.</p>

<p>I enjoyed the freedom of not hesitating to write the short,
tweet-length posts and then working on the longer ones when I had
something to say.  I didn&rsquo;t work hard to find pictures to add but only
used them when I felt they were appropriate or needed.  Just writing
words was okay and that freedom made it fun and doable.</p>

<p>The thing I liked the least about the experience was the quality of my
writing which I think is considerably decreased from what it used to
be.  I could have put more effort into better writing but I was just
getting some words down.  In essense, I was publishing maybe the
second draft of what I wrote, but not a &ldquo;final draft.&rdquo;  That was the
most dissatisfying part.  I got into the habit of writing but maybe
not writing well or at least better. Maybe that will be the next
challenge I take on, to write at least as well as I think I used to.</p>

<p>Another result of all of this blogging was a better work flow.  I
fixed my process by smoothing out lot of friction in the steps I take
to post.  I wrote a fully-automated script so I can locally publish
the blog (I actually do proof read entries there, spell check and see
how they look), and then push the update to public on Github with a
single command.  I fixed emacs to automatically go into text mode and
made some changes on Github to make pushing easier.</p>

<p>One of the lessons other bloggers shared as they were doing this
process was the appropriateness of the mid-length post.  That means
it&rsquo;s okay to write more than a tweet but less than a long essay.
That&rsquo;s part of the life-blood of journaling.  Sometimes you just pen a
brief entry but that&rsquo;s enough to stake out that day.  Being able to go
beyond 140 characters is a chief advantage that puts blogging above
tweeting while keeping the ability to write as little as desired.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve come to enjoy writing in Markdown even more.  It&rsquo;s simple to use
and, in the end, I have a completely readable and portable collection
of text files that aren&rsquo;t tied to a particular platform or site.  I
can take this site anywhere now.</p>

<p>One down side is that I&rsquo;m running up against the performance of
Octopress.  At this very point it takes 35 seconds of wall clock time
to generate the site.  That&rsquo;s not bad but it seems like a long wait in
computer &ldquo;waiting for a command to finish&rdquo; time.  I think I need to
look into breaking off the archives into a separate site or section so
they are generated independently.  Most of the archive, all of it
really, is static at this point and shouldn&rsquo;t need to be regenerated
for every post.  However, there would be some tricks in blending it in
to the main site, e.g., so that search covers the whole site including
archives.  It might be as simple as a different repo on Github and
posting it as a separate site with a different name but the exact same
look and feel.  There&rsquo;s more research, thinking and maybe
experimenting to do here.</p>

<p>So what next?  I&rsquo;m not going to focus on making sure I post something
every day.  I think I&rsquo;ll keep blogging more than I was for a while.
I&rsquo;m definitely going to take advantage of the freedom to blog anyway
way I wish, long or short, elaborate or trivially simple.  I&rsquo;m going
to read more blogs by other folks that have taken up the challenge and
try to benefit from their lessons learned.</p>

<p>When I started the 30 days, I brainstormed a nice long list of post
ideas in just a few minuts. After managing to cover a lot of them and
adding ideas through the month, amazingly, the list doesn&rsquo;t seem
any shorter.  There&rsquo;s still a lot to write about!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[IOS 8.1]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/09/ios-8-dot-1/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-09T21:53:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/09/ios-8-dot-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/20141109_iPhone.jpg"></p>

<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 30</a></p>

<p>Today I upgraded to IOS 8.1 with no trouble and it&rsquo;s working well so
far.</p>

<p>I am one of those users who doesn&rsquo;t have the 5-GB or so of space on my
iPhone to do an over-the-air upgrade.  In spite of that, you can do an
upgrade without needing the space if you connect your iPhone to your
Mac (or Windows?) running iTunes and use iTunes to do the upgrade.  It
does the downloading and expansion of files on your desktop machine
then installs the upgrade over the USB cable.</p>

<p>The upgrade/install went without any trouble and it took almost
exactly 36 minutes it predicted.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve not used it too much.  So far, all the apps look and work the
same as in IOS 7.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
