<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2014-11-04T07:07:10-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Farewell Tom Magliozzi 1937-2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/04/farewell-tom-magliozzi-1937-2014/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-04T06:40:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/04/farewell-tom-magliozzi-1937-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 25</a>*</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t know when or how I first happened to hear the show <em>Car Talk</em>
but I quickly became a huge fan.  When I couldn&rsquo;t listen to the show
live, I got a subscription through Audible and would download MP3s of
the show and burn them onto CDs to listen to.</p>

<p>Click and Clack were hilarious, their personalities were infectious,
and their ability to diagnose car problems preceeded and exceeded
Dr. House&rsquo;s corresponding ability at playing the medical Sherlock
Holmes.</p>

<p>Probably like most listeners, it was a while before I learned that
they were actually both MIT graduates, Tom had a Ph.D., and that they
both played Bluegrass music.</p>

<p>I haven&rsquo;t been a listener for a few years but I&rsquo;ve always remained a
fan.</p>

<p>This is one of my favorite videos.  Martin Guitar presents Click and
Clack with a special Car Talk edition guitar.  Then they perform.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cBOfm-nj1dU">Martin Guitar Presentation</a></p>

<p>Articles</p>

<p><a href="http://www.cartalk.com/blogs/staff-blog/tom-magliozzi-1937-2014">From the Car Talk Blog</a><br />
<a href="http://online.wsj.com/articles/BL-SEB-84583">Wall Street Journal</a><br />
<a href="http://www.npr.org/2014/11/03/357428287/tom-magliozzi-popular-co-host-of-nprs-car-talk-dies-at-77">NPR</a><br />
<a href="http://www.boston.com/cars/news-and-reviews/2014/11/03/don-drive-like-brother-tom-magliozzi-biggest-hits/cfUZN88nBxurXRnmUS9HsJ/story.html">Boston.com</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Buying a Telescope Part 2b]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/03/buying-a-telescope-part-2b/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-03T06:27:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/03/buying-a-telescope-part-2b</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 24</a></p>

<p>Recommendations continued.</p>

<h2>Binoculars</h2>

<p>The first recommendation is always binoculars.   They are two
telescopes instead of one.  They are the most portable telescopes you
can get and you get two, one for each eye.</p>

<p>The investment is around $100.  It&rsquo;s a good investment because,
regardless of how serious you become as an astronomer, you always have
a need for binoculars.  There are some objects that don&rsquo;t look as good
in a telescope.  A total lunar eclipse is an example.  When I was a
serious deep sky observer, I often found objects or at least the stars
surrounding their location using binoculars.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>Finally, if you decide you don&rsquo;t enjoy astronomy that much, instead of
binoculars getting forgotten in a closet, they are always useful for
things like concerts, sporting events, and nature viewing.</p>

<p>The ideal binocular size for astronomy is 7x50 or 10x50.  That means
the magnification is 7x or 10x and the aperture is 50-mm.  The
aperture divided by the magnification is the diameter of the exit
pupil and having an exit pupil near the size of the dilated pupils of
your dark-adapted eyes is the goal.  The 7mm to 5mm exit pupil sizes
fit the dilated pupil size of young and middle-aged adults fairly
well. Our eyes dilate less as we age.</p>

<p>The binocular should also have a tripod mounting point, usually a hole
in the middle tapped for a &frac14;-20 screw.  You can then buy a binocular
tripod adapter to attach them to a camera tripod.  You can make an
adapter for the cost of a few cents at a hardware store with a &frac14;-20
bolt and nut or two, and a small angle bracket.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve had a pair of Orion Scenix 7x50 binoculars for quite a few years
and I&rsquo;ve been quite happy with them.  They aren&rsquo;t the highest
precision or quality binoculars but they are well-made and do the job
pretty well for my own observing.</p>

<p><a href="http://telescope.com/">Orion telescope.com</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Buying a Telescope Part 2a]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/03/buying-a-telescope-part-2/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-03T01:14:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/03/buying-a-telescope-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 23</a>*</p>

<p>Recommendations.</p>

<h2>Orion</h2>

<p>Since the planetarium days, I&rsquo;ve favored Orion Telescopes as an
excellent and reliable source of reasonably priced and good quality
telescopes.  Their telescopes are well-made, of outstanding quality,
and not the absurdly overpriced telescopes you find at your nearest
big store.</p>

<p>What we used to call those &ldquo;department store&rdquo; telescopes, which
typically were of poor quality and vastly overpriced.  The classic
starter telescope is a 2.4-inch (60-mm) refractor on an altazimuth
mount.  I&rsquo;ve seen the &ldquo;department store&rdquo; versions of these for $250,
even $400.  The are often advertised as 400X or 300X magnification
(which is absurd and meaningless).  That same telescope, of higher
quality, outstanding and appropriate accessories at Orion is $100.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not going to cover all of the different types of telescopes but
just refer you to the web for that.  You should read about refractors
and reflectors.  Equatorial mounts and altazimuth.  Dobsonian,
Newtonian and Schmidt-Cassegrain, Maksutov and catadioptric telescopes
in general.  It sounds like a lot, but the basic ideas are not
complicated.</p>

<h2>*Posting Day</h2>

<p><em>I wrote this post while away from home on Sat 2014-11-01 and didn&rsquo;t
actually post it on day 23 but after midnight at 1:14 on day 24.  I
don&rsquo;t actually have a way to post entries when away from home so I can
only write them and then post them later.  So, in fact, I didn&rsquo;t
actually do any of the work on this post on day 23.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://telescope.com/">Orion telescope.com</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Buying a Telescope - Part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/01/buying-a-telescope-part-1/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-01T10:07:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/01/buying-a-telescope-part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 22</a></p>

<p>Back in the planetarium days I was frequently asked about buying a
telescope, especially around Christmas.  Over the decades since then
people still ask me from time to time and still ask more often around
Christmas.  I had a pretty well-formulated answer eventually and I&rsquo;ve
written it up a number of times.  (I&rsquo;m not sure if I know where any of
those old write ups are).</p>

<p>We&rsquo;ll start with the basics, what&rsquo;s important when it comes to
telescopes:   aperture, mounting and portability.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>Note that magnification, computers and electronics, and accessories
aren&rsquo;t on the list.</p>

<h2>Aperture</h2>

<p>When it comes to telescopes, aperture is more important than anything
else.  Like a bucket in rain, a telescope&rsquo;s most important job is
capturing light raining down from stars, galaxies, planets, etc.
Light carries information and the more light that&rsquo;s gathered the more
you can see.  This is why the next big observatory is always about how
large the aperture of the next telescope is going to be.  In my early
years, the 200-inch Hale Telescope on Mount Palomar was the largest.
These days we call it the five-meter telescope.  Now we have the E-ELT
European Extremely Large Telescope in the queue at 39 meters.</p>

<p>The aperture is simply the diameter of the main lens (on the front) or
the main mirror (in the back) of the telescope.</p>

<p>In the past, most amateur astronomers might have a six- or massive
eight-inch telescope.  A 12- or 16-inch was truly gigantic.  Now, it&rsquo;s
not uncommon for an amateur to have a 24- or 30-inch telescope.  The
10- and 12-inch apertures are not uncommon.</p>

<p>Basically you should get the largest aperture you can afford, that has
a sturdy, stable mounting and is portable enough to use.  That last
part is the trick.</p>

<h2>Mounting</h2>

<p>After the aperture, the next important feature is the mounting.  A
good mounting should be sturdy and solid.   If a telescope shakes,
even a tiny, barely perceptable amount, it degrades the image.</p>

<p>I know of no better example of this than binoculars.  It&rsquo;s a great joy
to take a nice pair of binoculars out and look at the sky.  But put
them on a camera tripod and it&rsquo;s like you suddenly switched to HD.
More details suddenly become visible.  It&rsquo;s because our hand-holding
always shakes at least a tiny amount and it&rsquo;s enough to make a
difference.</p>

<p>A good mounting should also be easy to set up.  Some equatorial
mountings seem like they take 30 mintues to assemble.  Some Dobsonian
mounts take about 10 seconds.</p>

<p>The mounting should also make it easy to move the telescope smoothly
to point it at the objects you want to observe.  It should easily stay
where you point it.</p>

<h2>Portability</h2>

<p>I can&rsquo;t tell you how many times I&rsquo;ve given all of this information to
people, answered their questions, and hear from them that they finally
got their new telescope!  Then later I find out they&rsquo;ve only used it
one or two times and then not since.  Often never.</p>

<p>Many, maybe even most telescopes are bought and only used once or
twice and then abandoned.  One implication of this is that there&rsquo;s a
huge supply of nearly new, &ldquo;used&rdquo; telescopes if one could only find
them.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll address another aspect of this try-and-abandon problem later, but
a huge factor is portability.  The basic rule is, the less a telescope
weighs the more it gets used.  Smaller is better in this sense,
exactly the opposite of aperture.  Having the nicest, big telescope
doesn&rsquo;t do anything for your observing hobby if you never want to take
it out and set it up.  On the other hand, a smaller telescope that
lets you grab and go is an instrument you&rsquo;ll use.  That makes it more
enjoyable regardless of what it&rsquo;s aperture is.</p>

<p>For this reason, it&rsquo;s a good idea to try before you buy.</p>

<p>I truly love my 10-inch Dobsonian telescope.  It will always be my
favorite.  However, sometimes I find that I hesitate to take it with
me.  I find myself thinking I wouldn&rsquo;t mind something more like a
six-inch Dobsonian, purely for portability, convenience, and my back.</p>

<h2>Next</h2>

<p>In Part Two I&rsquo;ll make actual recommendations and in Part Three cover
some details about other things I&rsquo;ve alluded to.</p>

<h2>Colophon</h2>

<p>I wrote this and the Part 2a posts while away from home using a Amazon
Kindle Fire HD, the Amazon Basics Bluetooth keyboard, Draft software,
and saved the files to Dropbox.  I currently don&rsquo;t have a set up for
posting when not at home so I just wrote the entries and posted them
when I returned.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SQRL!]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/31/sqrl/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-31T05:11:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/31/sqrl</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 21</a></p>

<p>For several months now Steve Gibson of GRC.com and Security Now has
been working on a new authentication protocol he named SQRL, the
Secure Quick Reliable Login.  On his web site he describes what
happens when you log into a site, say Amazon, using SQRL (assuming
Amazon adopted it).</p>

<p>The website displays a QR code, described as a &ldquo;SQRL code,&rdquo; beside the
usual userid and password login prompt.</p>

<blockquote><ul>
<li>The user can tap or click directly on the SQRL code to login, or
launch their smartphone&rsquo;s SQRL app, and scan the QR code.</li>
<li>For verification, SQRL displays the domain name contained in the
SQRL code.</li>
<li>After verifying the domain, the user permits the SQRL app to
authenticate their identity.</li>
<li>Leaving the login information blank, the user clicks the “Log in”
button&hellip; and is logged in.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>The approach is highly secure, difficult to attack, easy to implement,
and easy to use.  He describes details at his site.</p>

<p>This is an elegant solution to the problems that come from dealing
with passwords and I hope it continues to climb since it&rsquo;s taken off!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.grc.com/sqrl/sqrl.htm">SQRL at GRC.com</a><br />
<a href="http://twit.tv/show/security-now">Security Now</a><br />
<a href="http://twit.tv/show/security-now/424">Episode 424 on SQRL</a><br />
<a href="http://sqrl.pl/guide/">Sqrl.pl Illustrated Guide</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Are Quasars Dying?]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/30/are-quasars-dying/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-30T06:26:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/30/are-quasars-dying</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 20.1</a></p>

<p>From <a href="http://www.dailygalaxy.com/my_weblog/2014/10/are-quasars-dying-at-the-farthest-reaches-of-the-universe.html">The Daily Galaxy</a>.</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;We have been able to confirm that, indeed, apart from the highly
energetic and rapidly evolving quasars, there is another population
that evolves slowly. This population of quasars appears to follow the
quasar main sequence discovered by Sulentic and colleagues in
2000. There does not even seem to be a strong relation between this
type of quasars, which we see in our environment and those &lsquo;monsters&rsquo;
that started to glow more than ten billion years ago&rdquo;, says Ascensión
del Olmo another IAA-CSIC researcher taking part in the study.</p>

<p>They have, nonetheless, found differences in this population of quiet
quasars. &ldquo;The local quasars present a higher proportion of heavy
elements such as aluminium, iron or magnesium, than the distant
relatives, which most likely reflects enrichment by the birth and
death of successive generations of stars,&rdquo; says Jack W. Sulentic
(IAA-CSIC). &ldquo;This result is an excellent example of the new
perspectives on the universe which the new 10 meter-class of
telescopes such as GTC are yielding,&rdquo; the researcher concludes.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rocket Explodes]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/30/rocket-explodes/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-30T06:16:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/30/rocket-explodes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 20</a></p>

<p>From <a href="http://www.newscientist.com/article/dn26475-cargo-rocket-explosion-is-a-blow-for-commercial-space.html">New Scientist</a>.</p>

<p>The Orbital Sciences Antares rocket&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>&hellip;flying cargo to the International Space Station
exploded just 14 seconds after lift-off last night, creating a
spectacular fireball and shockwave as the fully fuelled rocket crashed
back down onto its launch pad.</p>

<p>No one was hurt when the uncrewed spacecraft was destroyed, but the
loss will dent attempts by the spacecraft&rsquo;s builder, Orbital Sciences
Corporation of Dulles, Virginia, to build confidence in its ability to
supply ISS cargo services to NASA.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The 19-Inch Rack]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/29/the-19-inch-rack/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-29T08:31:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/29/the-19-inch-rack</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/19-in-rack.png" title="" ></p>

<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 19</a></p>

<p>Last night, while driving home, I stopped at an intersection where
work was being done on the traffic signals.  Looking at the open
control box I suddenly realized it was just a 19-inch rack inside the
silver box.  I think I even saw a network switch in there and a
surprising number of mounted devices.  That makes sense.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve worked around the standard 19-in racks in data centers for a long
time.  Even before that, when I was in school, it was common for a
physics lab to have a row of several 19-in racks.  They were usually
filled with instruments, controllers and maybe even an occasional
computer though microcomputers, small enough to fit in a rack, were
just beginning to appear on the scene.</p>

<p>Even large telescopes will have the standard racks mounted right on
the back of the telescope, like the 120-inch telescope here at the
Lick Observatory on Mount Hamilton.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/lick-120.jpg"></p>

<p>Where did they begin?  An on-line article &ldquo;Audio-Video Equipment
Racks&rdquo; credits Westinghouse.</p>

<blockquote><p>The origins of rack mounting dates to the days of industrialist George
Westinghouse way back in 1890. Westinghouse had first designed
19-inch shelving to house relay gear used in his railroad
industry. Eventually, early telephone companies also adopted this
19-inch width.</p></blockquote>

<p>For that reason they are sometimes called &ldquo;relay racks.&rdquo;  Wikipedia
says the relay rack name came from telephony and then appeared in
railroad signaling by 1911.</p>

<p>The Electronic Industries Alliance (EIA) &ldquo;standardized them in its
310-D standard, first published in 1965.&rdquo;  That standard included the
1.75-in rack space height and the 19-in width (482.6 mm).</p>

<p>Wikipedia says,</p>

<blockquote><p>The 19-inch rack format with rack-units of 1.75 inches and holes
tapped for 12-24 screws with alternating spacings of 1.25 inches and
0.5 inch was an established standard by 1934. The EIA standard was
revised again in 1992 to comply with the 1988 public law 100-418,
setting the standard U as 44.5mm (15.9mm + 15.9mm + 12.7mm), making
each &ldquo;U&rdquo; officially 1.752 inches.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.princeton.edu/~achaney/tmve/wiki100k/docs/19-inch_rack.html">19-inch rack</a> at Princeton.edu/~achaney.<br />
<a href="http://www.practical-home-theater-guide.com/equipment-racks-1.html">Audio-Video Equipment Racks &ndash; Part 1</a> in the Practical Home Theatre Guide.<br />
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/19-inch_rack">19-in Rack</a> on Wikipedia.</p>

<p><em>Photo credit: US National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.<br />
Lick photo: by the author.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Inbox: First Impression]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/28/inbox-first-impression/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-28T06:01:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/28/inbox-first-impression</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 18.1</a></p>

<p>I just set up Inbox on a very old, in fact my oldest, earliest, Gmail
account.  Come to think of it, I guess that&rsquo;s appropriate in a way.
Here, briefly, are my very first impressions.</p>

<h2>Short Version</h2>

<p>Inbox is like the dead mouse your cat brings to you.  Thanks but
that&rsquo;s not exactly what I wanted and it&rsquo;s not quite useful to me,
though I appreciate the work you&rsquo;ve done.  I may even be impressed by
it.  It&rsquo;s true I could use something to eat right now, maybe even
something about that size, but that isn&rsquo;t it.</p>

<!-- More -->


<h2>Slightly More Detail</h2>

<p>Minimalist email messages:  Yes.  I like this idea of messages that
can look like tweets but still, maybe, have support for long messages.
Really, though, I think long messages should be a document that is
emailed.</p>

<p>The card thing:  Bah.  I don&rsquo;t use Google Now and I don&rsquo;t want that
much help.</p>

<p>The todo list thing: Thumbs down.  I&rsquo;m in the fifth year of my
highly-evolved GTD system and I don&rsquo;t want help with this from my email
program.  I don&rsquo;t mind it being there, it looks like it would be a
great help for folks that <em>do</em> use email to manage their lives (what a
horrible, horrible concept, though).  There needs to be some way to
get all of those green check marks and todo-listness out of the email if you
don&rsquo;t want to see it there.  Where&rsquo;s the OFF switch??</p>

<p>The automatic grouping thing: Thumbs down again.  Similar to the
above, I&rsquo;ve had complete control of my email with filters and labels
for years.  I don&rsquo;t need help.  Please get your ideas of labels and
filters out of my email!</p>

<p>Finally, it&rsquo;s not really minimal.  Inbox looks minimal and simpler,
but really it sneaks in all of the above cruft.  A program that sort
of looked like Inbox, more minimalist than Gmail, but that didn&rsquo;t
impose a lot of complexity and stuff in return would be worth a closer
look.</p>

<p>I expect changes to Gmail itself along these lines and maybe then
there will be some settings switches (no doubt almost impossibly
buried) to turn some of these &ldquo;helpful&rdquo; features off.</p>

<p>And I should make clear that this is all from my personal point of
view.  For the vast masses, Inbox may be just what folks need so I&rsquo;m
not saying it shouldn&rsquo;t exist and may not be a huge hit.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll find ways to keep playing with Inbox but it will be a while
before I unleash it on the actual Gmail that I use.</p>

<h2>P.S.</h2>

<p>It sure looks like <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CICMxwgm274">Mailboxapp</a> introduced some two years ago.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Programming Languages]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/28/programming-languages/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-28T05:27:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/28/programming-languages</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 18</a></p>

<p>I recently made a list of the program&rsquo;s I&rsquo;ve written that I&rsquo;d consider
my favorites.  Then I made a list of the programming languages I had
used.  I think the result would qualify as a list of my favorite
programming languages.</p>

<ul>
<li>FORTRAN</li>
<li>BASIC</li>
<li>SNOBOL</li>
<li>Pascal</li>
<li>C</li>
<li>Objective-C</li>
<li>Perl</li>
<li>Python</li>
</ul>


<p>I&rsquo;m pretty sure I&rsquo;ve written more code over the years in Perl and
Python.  I&rsquo;m not sure which would be in the lead at this point.</p>

<p>Two other languages, Smalltalk and LISP, are languages I really enjoy
but only in an occasional, recreational sense.  I&rsquo;ve never found either to be
useful for anything very practical.  However, it&rsquo;s a joy to write pure
object-oriented code in the wondrous Smalltalk-80-based environment of
Squeak.  Similarly, it&rsquo;s a thrill to write pure functional programs in
LISP, using Racket Scheme.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Centaurus A]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/27/centaurus-a/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-27T23:10:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/27/centaurus-a</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/centaurus_a.jpg"></p>

<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 17</a></p>

<p>From the <a href="http://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/chandra/multimedia/galaxy-centaurusA.html#.VE8I1It4oU8">NASA Chandra</a> pages.</p>

<blockquote><p>Centaurus A is the fifth brightest galaxy in the sky &mdash; making it an
ideal target for amateur astronomers &mdash; and is famous for the dust
lane across its middle and a giant jet blasting away from the
supermassive black hole at its center. Cen A is an active galaxy about
12 million light years from Earth.</p></blockquote>

<p><em>Image credit: X-ray: NASA/CXC/SAO; Optical: Rolf Olsen; Infrared:
 NASA/JPL-Caltech.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fascinating Satellite Images]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/26/fascinating-satellite-images/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-26T11:18:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/26/fascinating-satellite-images</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 16</a></p>

<p>From <a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/striking-satellite-images-2014-10">Business Insider</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Half Way]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/25/half-way/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-25T07:07:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/25/half-way</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 15.1</a></p>

<p>Well, I&rsquo;m half way to having blogged for 30 days straight.  It&rsquo;s
required keeping up with it but I&rsquo;ve enjoyed it so far.  The fact that
I&rsquo;ve thrown some re-tweets and link postings in there helps.  I like
the mid-length blogging ideas and those really fit my thinking.
Short, quick posts that say something you want to say are fine!</p>

<p>Some other takers of the 30 day challenge have been reflecting
mid-way.</p>

<p><a href="http://om.co/2014/10/24/swing-scratch/">Om Malik</a><br />
<a href="http://cdevroe.com/blog/10224/blogging-is-back">Colin Devroe</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning Python]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/25/learning-python/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-25T06:14:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/25/learning-python</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 15</a></p>

<p>What&rsquo;s the best way to learn the Python programming language?  I think
the on-line tutorial at python.org is the fastest but it works best if
Python isn&rsquo;t your first language.</p>

<!-- More -->


<h2>Backing Up</h2>

<p>I think Python is nearly the perfect language.  Okay, it&rsquo;s not really
perfect, but it&rsquo;s as close as any I can think of.  There are other
languages that might be better for some extreme, specialized cases
(which will not seem extreme or specialized to anyone who works on
them every day) such as very low-level system programming, programs
where performance is critical, maybe very large corporate software
systems (though I&rsquo;d claim Python still holds it&rsquo;s own here), as just a
few examples.</p>

<p>However, even in those instances, Python does okay.</p>

<p>There are languages for other ways of thinking about programming like
the functional languages Haskell, LISP, etc.</p>

<p>What&rsquo;s great about Python is that it&rsquo;s short, clear, easy to write
once you get the hang of it, very easy to read, and it can handle
programs that range from short little scripts to very large, complex
systems.</p>

<h2>If You&rsquo;ve Programmed Before</h2>

<p>If you&rsquo;ve written programs before, in any programming language, then
you&rsquo;ll probably be fine using the on-line tutorial for Python.  It&rsquo;s
free and on-line at Python&rsquo;s own website,
<a href="https://docs.python.org/2/tutorial/">https://docs.python.org/2/tutorial/</a>.</p>

<p>Start with chapter 1, then do 2-4.  Then skip to chapter 7 with more
input/output.  After than follow up with 5.  You can add the
additional chapters later, as you either need to or are interested.</p>

<h2>If You&rsquo;re a Beginner</h2>

<p>I can&rsquo;t say I&rsquo;ve found any beginning books that I&rsquo;ve looked at and
thought, &ldquo;Yes!  That&rsquo;s the ideal Python book for a beginning
programmer.&rdquo;  I am completely convinced that Python is the best
language for learning to program since Pascal.</p>

<p>The book <em>Learn Python the Hard Way</em> Third Edition by Zed A. Shaw,
Addison-Wesley Professional, 2013, seems pretty good and complete, but
it seems slow and plodding to me.  That approach may be perfect for
you.  Pace is always relative.  The book is free on-line, available as
a PDF you can download, or you can buy the on-line version and get the
accompanying videos or buy the regular book.</p>

<p>There seem to be thousands of vidoes teaching you Python on Youtube.
As far as I&rsquo;ve looked, I&rsquo;ve not found one that I like.  There are many
that are okay, but none that I&rsquo;ve bothered to write the URL down for.</p>

<p>The book <em>Learning Python</em> Fifth Edition by Mark Lutz, O&#8217;Reilly Media,
2013 is 1600 pages! It&rsquo;s hard for me to understand how you could make
a book on Python that long and I have looked it over.  I&rsquo;m not saying
it&rsquo;s not a good book, it&rsquo;s apparently complete and I believe it
includes exercises and the new Python 3 version.  Still, wow!</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re a beginner, I think I&rsquo;d still say take a look at Python&rsquo;s
on-line tutorial and see if it works for you.  Try all of the
examples.  If you run into any trouble, go to one of these other
books for that part or look for some videos on Youtube on the specific
topic.  Then go back and carry on with the tutorial.</p>

<h2>What About Java?</h2>

<p>And what about Java as a first language?  Well, here&rsquo;s the traditional
first program that prints out &ldquo;Hello, World!&rdquo; in Java:</p>

<pre><code>public class HelloWorld {
    public static void main(String[] args) {
        System.out.println("Hello, World!");
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Compare the same program in Python.</p>

<pre><code>print "Hello, World!"
</code></pre>

<p>Now, I understand why the Java program looks they way it does and
there are valid reasons for it&rsquo;s verbosity and what&rsquo;s going on there.
However, I&rsquo;ve used Python in many large programs and haven&rsquo;t missed
the features of Java even once (knock on wood).  I will admit, though,
that I&rsquo;m strangely drawn to Java. I remember when it first came on the
scene. I don&rsquo;t dislike it.  I&rsquo;ve just never found a use for it other
than interacting with systems or services that only support Java.</p>

<h2>References</h2>

<p><a href="https://docs.python.org/2/tutorial/">The Python Tutorial</a><br />
<a href="http://learnpythonthehardway.org/">Learn Python The Hard Way</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fall Colors at Cherokee NC]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/24/fall-colors-at-cherokee-nc/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-24T08:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/24/fall-colors-at-cherokee-nc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 14</a></p>

<p>From <a href="https://twitter.com/wxbrad/status/525623053393207296">@wxbrad</a>.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p>RT Fall colors at Cherokee, NC&#8230; photo from <a href="https://twitter.com/SandersWX">@sanderswx</a> <a href="http://t.co/Wjpsfl4AXe">pic.twitter.com/Wjpsfl4AXe</a></p>&mdash; Brad Panovich (@wxbrad) <a href="https://twitter.com/wxbrad/status/525623053393207296">October 24, 2014</a></blockquote>


<script async src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog///platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ten Years of Ubuntu]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/23/ten-years-of-ubuntu/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-23T06:08:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/23/ten-years-of-ubuntu</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 13.1</a></p>

<p><a href="http://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2014/10/ten-years-of-ubuntu-how-linuxs-beloved-newcomer-became-its-criticized-king/">Ten years of Ubuntu: How Linux’s beloved newcomer became its criticized king</a>.  Ars looks back at the decade in Ubuntu, from Warty Warthog to 25 million users worldwide, by Scott Gilbertson at Ars Technica.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Google's New Gmail Inbox]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/23/googles-new-email-inbox/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-23T05:48:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/23/googles-new-email-inbox</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 13</a></p>

<p>Google is now making available to all users, albeit by invitation only
for now, Inbox, it&rsquo;s new Gmail app.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve barely seen it but initially I&rsquo;m a bit skeptical.  There&rsquo;s a
focus on automatically bundling  your email for you and managing todo
lists.  I already manage my email with a strong and extensive set of
filters and I manage todo lists and things like that via my
implementation of David Allen&rsquo;s GTD.  So I&rsquo;m probably not an intended
user.</p>

<p>It will probably look compelling.  One thing I do like are email-like
systems where the messages look more like short messages in a chat
session rather than email.  When I think about this as a good idea
and then look back at Gmail, it really already goes a long way in that
direction.  The messages in a conversation are nicely minimal.</p>

<p>Inbox also seems to have a little floating circle, in this case a red
dot. This little floating circle, that is both highly annoying and in
the way as far as I&rsquo;m concerned, seems to be a popular gimmick lately.
Witness the little chat circle in Facebook&rsquo;s mobile apps.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m being highly critical of software I&rsquo;ve never even seen, so I may
be wrong about Inbox.  I do like the idea of an even nicer and somehow
simpler email application but I want full control over what&rsquo;s
happening.  And I don&rsquo;t need a new Gmail.  It&rsquo;s actually nearly
perfect already.  I fear that ongoing attempts to move it forward will
begin to degrade what I like about Gmail.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.theverge.com/2014/10/22/7041227/google-inbox-hands-on-this-feels-like-the-future-of-email">Using Google Inbox: this feels like the future of email</a> at the Verge.<br />
<a href="http://readwrite.com/2014/10/22/google-inbox-deconstructing-email">Google May Be About To Blow Up Email With Its &ldquo;Inbox&rdquo; App</a> at Readwrite.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Whither the Self-Driving Car?]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/22/whither-the-self-driving-car/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-22T04:20:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/22/whither-the-self-driving-car</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 12</a></p>

<p>Lee Gomes writes in Slate The autonomous Google car may never actually
happen.</p>

<blockquote><p>For starters, the Google car was able to do so much more than its
predecessors in large part because the company had the resources to do
something no other robotic car research project ever could:  develop
an ingenious but extremely expensive mapping system.  These maps
contain the exact three-dimensional location of streetlights, stop
signs, crosswalks, lane markings, and every other crucial aspect of a
roadway.</p></blockquote>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>&hellip;the maps necessary for the Google car are an order of magnitude
more complicated [than Google Maps].</p></blockquote>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>To create them, a dedicated vehicle outfitted with a bank of sensors
first makes repeated passes scanning the roadway to be mapped.  The
data is <em>[sic]</em> then downloaded, with every square foot of the
landscape pored over by both humans and computers to make sure that
all-important real-world objects have been captured.  This complete
map gets loaded into the car&rsquo;s memory before a journey, and because
it knows from the map about the location of many stationary objects,
it&rsquo;s computer&mdash;essentially a generic PC running Ubuntu Linux&mdash;can
devote more of its energies to tracking moving objects, like other
cars.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/technology/technology/2014/10/google_self_driving_car_it_may_never_actually_happen.html">Driving in Circles by Lee Gomes in Slate</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Short Form Blogging]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/21/short-form-blogging/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-21T08:12:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/21/short-form-blogging</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 11.1</a></p>

<p>Gina Trapani&rsquo;s post on <a href="http://scribbling.net/2014/10/16/short-form-blogging/">Short Form Blogging</a> on Scribbling.net precisely
captures my own current approach to blogging almost perfectly.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fireball Over Tennessee]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/21/fireball-over-tennessee/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-21T07:57:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/21/fireball-over-tennessee</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 11</a></p>

<p><a href="http://youtu.be/wwF5jI48hGM">http://youtu.be/wwF5jI48hGM</a></p>

<p>Posted by <a href="https://twitter.com/spann/status/524528021093773312">James Spann</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Concerning last night&rsquo;s fireball in the southern sky&hellip;
There was a very bright fireball over middle Tennessee last night
(October 20) at 7:57:09 PM CT. Four NASA all sky cameras (located in
Tullahoma, Huntsville, Chickamauga, and North Georgia College) first
detected it at an altitude of 54 miles, moving slightly north of west
at 47,000 miles per hour.The meteor, estimated to weigh around 10
pounds, travelled some 64 miles through the atmosphere before
fragmenting 24 miles above the town of Brentwood, south of
Nashville. At its brightest, the fireball rivaled the first quarter
Moon, gathering a fair amount of attention in the tri-state area.</p>

<p>Via Bill Cooke&hellip; Meteoroid Environments Office, Marshall Space Flight
Center</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
