<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2014-10-17T08:07:49-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why You Should Keep a Journal]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/17/why-you-should-keep-a-journal/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-17T08:03:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/17/why-you-should-keep-a-journal</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 7.1</a></p>

<p>From Lifehacker, &ldquo;<a href="http://lifehacker.com/why-you-should-keep-a-journal-and-how-to-start-yours-1547057185">Why You Should Keep a Journal (and How to Start Yours)</a>.&rdquo;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Mac Mini, iPad, and More]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/17/new-mac-mini/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-17T07:50:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/17/new-mac-mini</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 7</a></p>

<p>From <a href="http://www.theverge.com/2014/10/16/6989443/apple-ipad-mac-event-8-most-important-things">The Verge, &ldquo;The 8 most important announcements from the Apple iPad and Mac event&rdquo;</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Github Side]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/16/the-github-side/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-16T06:39:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/16/the-github-side</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 6</a></p>

<p>On Day 1 (the same Day 6 link above) I said I&rsquo;d write a script.  The
script is called <strong>blog_post.py</strong> and is, of course, in Python 2.7.
When I post a blog on Octopress it basically consists of these steps.</p>

<ol>
<li>Run the <strong>new_post</strong> command to create a file.</li>
<li>Edit the file to write the post with Emacs, using the Markdown language.</li>
<li>Save the file.</li>
<li>Generate the blog with a <strong>generate</strong> command which updates the
entire static site meaning all of the HTML, CSS, image and other files
used to create the website.</li>
<li>Copy all of those files to a Github directory.</li>
<li>Add, commit and push the Github directory up to Github.</li>
</ol>


<p>The script currently handles the first three steps and all I have to
do is specify the title on the command line.  The remaining steps are
still manual but I plan to add an automatic version of them, or at
least a more-automated version, to the script.</p>

<p>For as much posting as I&rsquo;ve been doing lately, making it this much
more convenient is more important than normal.</p>

<p>Some of you might point out that much of this automation is already
built into Octopress.  I think the fact that I want to deviate from
the out-of-the-box functionality it provide means it&rsquo;s easier just to
write a program in Python I can maintain rather than learning how to
hack the Octopress system.</p>

<p>Speaking of Github, it&rsquo;s the third leg of my switch to Octopress and
Markdown.  It&rsquo;s turned out to be a great hosting solution.  It&rsquo;s free,
reliable, and performs well.  Uploading is super efficient, too, of
course.</p>

<p><a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a><br />
<a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/">Markdown</a><br />
<a href="https://pages.github.com/">Github Pages</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fear the Flashlight?]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/15/fear-the-flashlight/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-15T08:12:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/15/fear-the-flashlight</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/iphone_apps_sphere.jpg"></p>

<p><a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 5</a></p>

<p>Should you fear your flashlight?  There&rsquo;s been a story going around
about the security threat of flashlight apps on your phone.  How
seriously should you take this?</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s nothing particularly dangerous about flashlight apps however
there is a general danger to be cautious of when you install <em>any</em>
apps on your phone.  That&rsquo;s the real lesson to take away here.</p>

<p><em>Image credit: by <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/blakespot/3030107334/">Blake Patterson</a> CC BY 2.0.</em></p>

<!-- More -->


<p></p>

<p>Snopes reports there was one app developer in 2013 that settled a
complaint with the Federal Trade Commission because the app was
collecting information to use for ad targeting.</p>

<h2>The Lesson</h2>

<p>You give apps various permissions to access various types of data and
devices on your phone when you install them.  You have to give the
permission&mdash;both iPhone and Android will ask you when you install a
new app, or I believe the iPhone will sometimes ask when the app wants
to do something, i.e., it wants to access your location data.</p>

<p>One problem is the access and questions tend to be an all-or-nothing
type of question.  If my weather radar app wants to report on my
current location, it wants to access the GPS.  An email app will want
to access all of my contacts information.</p>

<p>One that really annoys me are apps that want to access all of the
contacts information so they can &ldquo;find my friends&rdquo; on their service.
I always refuse those.</p>

<p>If an app wants to do one little thing, the only choice is to ask for
access to that whole part of your phone.  You can see the problem.  If
they divided access rights up into little slices, like &ldquo;access your
current GPS location but not your past location history&rdquo;, there&rsquo;d be
such a long list of permissions people would just ignore them.</p>

<p>But most of us just ignore them anyway.  By now, most people just
click &ldquo;Oh okay&rdquo; and carry on.</p>

<h2>Here&rsquo;s What I Do</h2>

<ul>
<li><p>I only get apps from the app store!  (The App Store for the iPhone
and the Google play store for Android).</p></li>
<li><p>I try to get some indication of how reputable the app developer is.
Have 10,000 downloaded it or just 20?  Are the reviews good?  Have I
heard of the developer or company before?  (Usually not).  Do they
have other apps in the store or just this one?  Does their
description and web site look professional or like a school project?</p></li>
<li><p>When apps ask for permission, if there&rsquo;s a choice, i.e., the app can
be used with or without it, I try to understand why it wants that
permission before I grant it.  If it wants access to my contact list
I never grant it because it&rsquo;s not my business to give away <em>your</em>
name, phone number and email address.  I usually will grant GPS
access.  Camera or microphone access had better have something to do
with what that the app is for.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>The Apple App Store has strict policies about what apps they accept
and there is a review process that each app goes through.  The Google
play store is also supposed to be constantly checking their apps
though they are reputedly not as strict on admitting apps, but
presumably check them for security concerns.</p>

<p>If enough people have downloaded and use an app, then it&rsquo;s more likely
that any mischief has been discovered and reported.</p>

<h2>The Important Caveat</h2>

<p>However, none of these steps are guarantees that you won&rsquo;t get malware
on your phone.  There are clever attackers who can get past all of the
above checks, at least for a while before they are discovered.  For
that reason I don&rsquo;t use any critically important apps on my phone like
banking, etc.  I just don&rsquo;t use a phone for those.  And I&rsquo;m very
cautious about what I log into from my phone even using the web.  I
favor using LTE instead of an unknown, public wifi service.</p>

<p>Fortunately most apps now use HTTPS, SSL for secure connections.</p>

<p>I also just don&rsquo;t install many apps.  I mean I just don&rsquo;t install
willy nilly every app I see, hear about or someone recommends.  It has
to be something I have an interest in or an actual use for.</p>

<h2>Balance</h2>

<p>In the end you&rsquo;re trying to strike a balance between convenience,
features, and function vs. security.  We could replace our front door
with a three-inch steel door and drag concrete Jersey barriers in
front of the house, but that would be too much security for too much
lost convenience.  Probably.</p>

<h2>Final P.S.</h2>

<p>The iPhone has it&rsquo;s own built-in flashlight since IOS 7 (drag up from
the bottom of the screen) so you can uninstall one if you have it.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.snopes.com/computer/internet/flashlight.asp">Flash and Grab at snopes.com</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Twelve Years]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/14/twelve-years/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-14T06:03:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/14/twelve-years</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/Sun_Ultra_5_front.jpg"></p>

<p>Day 4</p>

<p><em>&ldquo;Occasional reports on what in the world I’m doing. You can read here
to find out what I’ve been working on and how it’s going. There might
be clues about what I’m thinking. New things learned will also appear.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m really not going to make all of these posts about blogging, I
promise.  However, I thought I should note this blog is now in it&rsquo;s
12th year.  I always miss the anniversary but it was this past month.
The first post was on Mon 2002-09-16 00:29 -0400.</p>

<p>In the beginning the posts were nearly all work-related reports on
what I was working on.  Then I began to include other topics I found
interesting such as astronomy and computing.</p>

<p>The first posts were written on Blogger, then still owned by Pyra
Labs, co-founded by Ev Williams who later was a co-founder of Twitter.
Google eventually bought Blogger.  I wrote the posts on Blogger but used
it&rsquo;s ftp publishing feature to push the generated pages back to my
desktop workstation, Monolith.</p>

<p>Monolith had an Apache web server running on it, upgraded from the
original NCSA HTTP server software at some point.  The computer had
originally been a NeXTstation then later it&rsquo;s soul had been migrated
to a Sun SPARC 5 workstation.  By this time, when the blog began in
2002, I think it might have been upgraded to a Sun Ultra 5 but I don&rsquo;t
recall the models and timeline precisely.</p>

<p>From Blogger, I migrated to Bloxom, then back to Blogger, fully hosted
at Blogspot, then recently to Octopress.  The pre-Octopress blog is
still on-line.</p>

<p><a href="http://monolith149daily.blogspot.com/2011/09/nine-years-ago.html">Nine Years Ago</a><br />
<a href="http://monolith149daily.blogspot.com/2012/12/ten-years-of-blogging.html">Ten Years of Blogging</a></p>

<p><em>Image credit: <a href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Sun_Ultra_5_front.jpg">Thomas Kaiser</a> CC BY-SA 3.0</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Homebrew Cray 1-A]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/13/homebrew-cray-1-a/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-13T05:51:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/13/homebrew-cray-1-a</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/cray-1a.jpg"></p>

<p>Day 3.1</p>

<p>From <a href="https://twitter.com/newsycombinator/status/521571606536417281">Hacker News @newsycombinator</a></p>

<p>A <a href="http://www.chrisfenton.com/homebrew-cray-1a/">Homebrew Cray-1A</a> by
chrisfenton.com!</p>

<p><em>Image credit: by <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/stiefkind/43091218/">Wolfgang Stief</a> CC BY-NC-ND 2.0.  (No this is not the home brew Cray from the article).</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spell Checking with Gmail]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/13/spell-checking-with-gmail/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-13T05:44:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/13/spell-checking-with-gmail</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Day 3</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not going to make <em>all</em> of these posts about blogging but, while
still on the subject, here&rsquo;s a simple blogging tip.  I use Gmail for spell
checking.</p>

<p>The fact is that I do this just about any time I need good spell
checking.  Ironically, Google documents&#8217; spell checking is lacking so
I even use this approach for them. (At least that used to be the
case).</p>

<p>First, open a new message in a Compose window but don&rsquo;t add any
recipients.  After all, you don&rsquo;t want to accidentally send your text
to someone.  Next, just past the text, say a whole document into the
window and check.  As you find misspelled words, go back and edit the
original.  When finished, just click the trash can icon in the compose
window to discard the message.</p>

<p>For anyone who points out that Gmail spell checking isn&rsquo;t perfect
either, yeah, I know.  It&rsquo;s been the best I&rsquo;ve found over the years,
though.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Octopress After 512 Days]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/12/octopress-after-512-days/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-12T23:10:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/12/octopress-after-512-days</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Day 2</p>

<p>Well, I was supposed to report back in on how it&rsquo;s been going with
Octopress after using it a while.  It&rsquo;s now been 512 days, or one year
and 147 days, or about 17 months which is about one year and five
months.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s basically been going okay.  The process isn&rsquo;t bad.  I put up
posts now and then with varying frequency.  Some are &ldquo;full&rdquo; posts with
picture and permission, some are occasionally long, and some are
short, ~tweet-length updates.</p>

<p>I like Octopress a lot.  The best part is writing in Markdown which
means my source files are all plain text and I have a copy of all of
them, so the blog is already in my possession and easily read without
any software or publishing.</p>

<p>The Octopress scripts are easy to use.  Right now I run a new_post
command to create a file, edit the file with Emacs, then re-generate
the blog and finally push the changes up to Github which is where I
publish it.</p>

<p>Adding an image is hardly more difficult than it was with Blogger.  I
have to download the image and get it into the machine I&rsquo;m writing
on.  Then it&rsquo;s just copying the image to a source directory in the
blog tree and adding one line to the Markdown file.</p>

<p>Yesterday, on Saturday I wrote the beginning of a Python script to
automate running those commands.  So far it handles it all up to
running Emacs on the created file.  Next will come updating the git
repo locally then pushing up the changes.</p>

<p>The biggest down side at the moment is that the archives are organized
in the single page view by date and year, but they aren&rsquo;t physically
organized in the real file tree.  Also there&rsquo;s no way to segment the
blog into archive pieces.  Generate, I think, rebuilds the whole site
basically and, as the site grows, it&rsquo;s taking a while to do a generate
now.  Okay, it takes 25 seconds but it seems like a long while.</p>

<p>As the archive grows to be years long, I believe it will become a big
unweildy.  It would be better if there was a way to segment off pieces
of the archive, e.g., each year, so you don&rsquo;t end up regenerating it
all every time.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m actually pretty sure there is a way to do this, I&rsquo;ll just have to
dig it up when there&rsquo;s time.</p>

<p>See <a href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/06/08/leaping-to-a-new-blogging-platform/">Leaping to a New Blogging Platform</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Blogging for 30 Days]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-11T07:25:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Day 1</p>

<p>I heard it mentioned by Gina Trapani on <em>This Week in Google</em> on
Twit.tv.  There&rsquo;s a challenge going around to blog for 30 days
straight but not on weekends.  She credited it to Om Malik.  He
credited the idea to Matt Mullenweg and he credited it to a challenge
from Colin Devroe, ironically on Twitter.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve blogged off and on for over 12 years now and I&rsquo;ve really slacked
off lately so the thought of posting more has already been on my
mind.  I&rsquo;m already not following the challenge because, well, it&rsquo;s the
weekend. But I&rsquo;ll see what I can do for 30 days.</p>

<p>Just minutes ago, I sat down and almost instantly brainstormed about 20
topics that were already on my mind.  If there&rsquo;s nothing new on my
mind for a particular day I&rsquo;ll have those to fall back on.</p>

<p>The next thing I&rsquo;ll do, I think, is write a script.</p>

<p><a href="http://twit.tv/show/this-week-in-google/270">This Week in Google #270</a><br />
<a href="http://om.co/2014/10/05/30-days-of-blogging/">Om Malik &ndash; 30 Days of Blogging</a><br />
<a href="http://ma.tt/2014/10/streak/">Matt Mullenweg &ndash; Streak</a><br />
<a href="https://twitter.com/cdevroe/status/504630581117063169">Colin Devroe on Twitter</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Diagramming Sentences]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/03/diagramming-sentences/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-03T07:34:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/03/diagramming-sentences</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Huffington Post actually published an article on how to diagram
sentences.  Yes, we did learn this in school and it was a lot of fun.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2014/10/01/diagram-sentence-grammar_n_5908462.html">This Old Grammar Trick Still Works! How To Diagram A Sentence</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A History of the Internet]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/01/a-history-of-the-internet/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-01T08:19:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/01/a-history-of-the-internet</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/NSFNET-backbone-T3.png"></p>

<p><a href="http://www.inetdaemon.com/tutorials/internet/history.shtml">History of the Internet</a> at InetDaemon.com is a brief and nice account of how the Internet
began.</p>

<p><em>Image credit: CC BY-SA 3.0 Merit Network, Inc.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Happy Autumnal Equinox 2014!]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/09/23/happy-autumnal-equinox-2014/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-23T04:43:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/09/23/happy-autumnal-equinox-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Happy autumnal equinox at 22:29 EDT on Mon 2014-09-22!</p>

<p>Mon 2014-09-22 22:29:00 -0400<br>
Tue 2014-09-23 02:29:00 +0000</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Venus and Jupiter Super Close Conjunction]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/08/17/venus-and-jupiter-super-close-conjunction/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-17T20:48:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/08/17/venus-and-jupiter-super-close-conjunction</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/jupiter_venus.png"></p>

<p>Tomorrow morning Mon 2014-08-18, the two brightest planets, Jupiter
and Venus, will be about 1/3 of a degree apart.  That&rsquo;s 20 arc
minutes.  This is extremely &ldquo;close&rdquo; on the sky for two planets and
will be a spectacular sight to see.</p>

<p>Not only will they be close together but they will also be near M44
the Beehive Cluster open cluster of stars.</p>

<p>Sky and Telescope Article:  <a href="http://www.skyandtelescope.com/astronomy-news/observing-news/venus-and-jupiter-spectacle-august-18-08132014/?et_mid=687137&amp;rid=247480049">Close Venus-Jupiter Conjunction on August
18th</a> by Bob King from August 13, 2014.</p>

<p><em>Image: Jupiter and Venus from Atlanta at Mon 2014-08-18 05:54:00
 -0400 (5:54 EDT).  The planets are below Castor and Pollux in Gemini.
 Image from Stellarium.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Farewell to Orkut]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/07/04/farewell-to-orkut/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-04T06:08:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/07/04/farewell-to-orkut</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/orkut.png"></p>

<p>I received an email from Google, well it says from Orkut, last night
with the subject line &ldquo;A Farewell to Orkut.&rdquo;</p>

<blockquote><p>After ten years of sparking conversations and forging connections, we
have decided it&rsquo;s time for us to start saying goodbye to Orkut. Over
the past decade, YouTube, Blogger and Google+ have taken off, with
communities springing up in every corner of the world. Because the
growth of these communities has outpaced Orkut&rsquo;s growth, we&rsquo;ve decided
to focus our energy and resources on making these other social
platforms as amazing as possible for everyone who uses them.</p></blockquote>

<p>The anecdotal evidence I&rsquo;ve heard from friends with connections in
Brazil is that most Orkut users have abandoned it for the dreaded
Facebook.  Somehow I don&rsquo;t expect they&rsquo;ve all moved over to Blogger and
Google plus.</p>

<p>In my case, I never used Orkut other than to set up an account and log
on a couple of times.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Happy Summer Solstice]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/06/22/happy-summer-solstice/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-22T07:17:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/06/22/happy-summer-solstice</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Happy Summer Solstice!</p>

<p>Sat 2014-06-21 10:51:00 +0000<br>
Sat 2014-06-21 06:51:00 -0400</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[iPhone After Eight Months]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/06/20/iphone-after-eight-months/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-20T06:17:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/06/20/iphone-after-eight-months</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/20140620_iphone.png"></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s now been eight months since I switched to the iPhone in October
2012.  The honeymoon is over and I&rsquo;ve been chewing on the green grass
for a while.  I can say I&rsquo;m just as happy and pleased with the the 5C
as I was when it was new, maybe even more.</p>

<p>It does everything I need or want it to do.  I have a nice set of apps
I use daily, a simulation and a game here or there, and generally I
can find just about anything I need in an app and it all works fine.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m still using the Gmail and the Google Maps apps for email, maps and
navigation.  Amazon cloud player was just updated and is still my
primary music player.  Netflix works fine but I typically use the
Youtube app for watching videos.</p>

<p>Apple&rsquo;s iMessage works great for texting with images and video with
the rest of the family and we all have iPhones at this point.</p>

<p>The camera continues to make great pictures, as expected.</p>

<p>Here are some of the most recent apps of significance I&rsquo;ve added.
Loom was bought by Dropbox who introduced an app called Carousel, so
I&rsquo;m not using it to automatically upload and archive photos.  Carousel
is nice as an app but there doesn&rsquo;t seem to be a correspondingly nice
web interface other then a plain Dropbox folder with a <em>lot</em> of image
files in it.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not a fan of Facebook.  In fact I don&rsquo;t like it much at all.
However, I have to say that Paper is nicely done, beautiful in some
ways, but a little quirky sometimes.  I like it many times better than
the regular Facebook interface because it&rsquo;s fun to use, but I ignore
the news feed and those other screens.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve become interested in trains lately and Trainz Driver is a fun
simulator.</p>

<p>If you compare the current image of my home screen here to the image I
<a href="http:/m149daily-blog/blog/2013/10/07/transition-to-the-iphone/">posted back in October 2012</a>, you can see that it hasn&rsquo;t changed much.
That&rsquo;s screen one and I only use three screens of apps that are about
&frac12; to 2/3 full.</p>

<p><em>Image: my current iPhone screen one.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Milky Way, Laser, and Meteor]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/04/23/milky-way/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-23T04:23:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/04/23/milky-way</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//images/observing_space.png"></p>

<p>From <a href="https://twitter.com/observingspace/status/457048425553342465">@ObservingSpace</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Milky Way and Lighthouse]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/03/01/milky-way-and-lighthouse/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-01T14:39:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/03/01/milky-way-and-lighthouse</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/milky_way_lighthouse.png"></p>

<p>This is a beautiful picture by <a href="https://twitter.com/nickventonphoto/status/393430064433352704/">Nick Venton Photo</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/nickventonphoto">@nickventonphoto</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Lost Art of the Saturn V]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/03/01/the-lost-art-of-the-saturn-v/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-01T14:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/03/01/the-lost-art-of-the-saturn-v</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/saturn-v-cutaway.jpg"></p>

<p>Wow!  This is an amazing site and article by Amy Shira Teitel.</p>

<p><a href="http://amyshirateitel.com/2011/04/03/the-lost-art-of-the-saturn-v/">The Lost Art of the Saturn V</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Python vs. Javascript]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/03/01/python-vs-javascript/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-01T14:19:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/03/01/python-vs-javascript</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been reluctantly learning some Javascript recently.  While
looking for a good summary of a feature comparison between Python and
Javascript, I found this blog post by Matt Chisholm, <a href="https://blog.glyphobet.net/essay/2557">A tour of the differences between JavaScript and Python</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
