<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2014-04-23T04:11:56-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Milky Way and Lighthouse]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/03/01/milky-way-and-lighthouse/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-01T14:39:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/03/01/milky-way-and-lighthouse</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/milky_way_lighthouse.png"></p>

<p>This is a beautiful picture by <a href="https://twitter.com/nickventonphoto/status/393430064433352704/">Nick Venton Photo</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/nickventonphoto">@nickventonphoto</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Lost Art of the Saturn V]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/03/01/the-lost-art-of-the-saturn-v/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-01T14:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/03/01/the-lost-art-of-the-saturn-v</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/saturn-v-cutaway.jpg"></p>

<p>Wow!  This is an amazing site and article by Amy Shira Teitel.</p>

<p><a href="http://amyshirateitel.com/2011/04/03/the-lost-art-of-the-saturn-v/">The Lost Art of the Saturn V</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Python vs. Javascript]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/03/01/python-vs-javascript/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-01T14:19:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/03/01/python-vs-javascript</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been reluctantly learning some Javascript recently.  While
looking for a good summary of a feature comparison between Python and
Javascript, I found this blog post by Matt Chisholm, <a href="https://blog.glyphobet.net/essay/2557">A tour of the differences between JavaScript and Python</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gravity]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/03/01/gravity/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-01T14:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/03/01/gravity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/20140301_Space_Walk.jpg"></p>

<p>I just watched <em>Gravity</em> this morning.  It was very entertaining and I
liked the movie.</p>

<p>Congratulations are due for executing the physics of objects&#8217; motions
and the look of a so-called &ldquo;zero gravity&rdquo; (in orbit) environment so
well.  It was all believable.  I can&rsquo;t believe they didn&rsquo;t shuttle the
crew up to the ISS and shoot it on site, it was realistic enough.</p>

<p>The behaviour of tethered objects and such were pretty real.</p>

<p>However, there were some technical points to complain about.  Here&rsquo;s a
quick run down.  And, yes, there are lots of spoilers here.</p>

<p><em>Image: <a href="http://spaceflight1.nasa.gov/gallery/images/shuttle/sts-116/html/s116e06645.html">NASA Image</a>. S116-E-06645 (16 Dec. 2006)&mdash;Astronaut Robert
 L. Curbeam, Jr., STS-116 mission specialist, participates in the
 mission&rsquo;s third planned session of extravehicular activity (EVA) as
 construction resumes on the International Space Station.</em></p>

<!-- More -->


<h2>Physics</h2>

<p>A better title for the movie would have been &ldquo;Momentum.&rdquo;  Once they
got past the basics of orbital life and space, the physics wasn&rsquo;t
handled very well in some places.  For example, you don&rsquo;t need a
certain amount of thrust to get to another object.  The amount of
thrust results in a speed which only determines how long it will take
to get there.</p>

<p>Getting to the Chinese space station could be done with just thrusts
from the maneuvering thrusters.  Granted, it could take a while to get
there and there was the race against the orbiting debris (but see
below) and running out of oxygen.  If something is far away in the
orbital environment of space, you don&rsquo;t need a bigger engine the
farther away it is, unless you want to go faster and get there
sooner.  There <em>is</em> an argument to be made for having a lot of fuel
for maneuvering because rendezvous is <em>hard</em>.</p>

<h2>The Worst Flaw</h2>

<p>And while talking about momentum, we may as well get to what I
consider the worst flaw in the movie.  It occurs when Sandra Bullock&rsquo;s
and George Clooney&rsquo;s characters let go of each other and Clooney
floats off into the distance.  At that point neither of them is
moving.  They&rsquo;ve both already stopped (at least in their orbiting
frame of reference).  In reality, when they let go he&rsquo;d just hang
there.</p>

<p>Also, just the slightest tug would have started him moving back toward
the space station.  Similarly, if she could have executed a slight tug
on the parachute lines, she could have started herself or both of them
headed back, even if at a very slow speed.</p>

<p>The real problem to be solved at that moment was to make sure she
didn&rsquo;t lose the parachute line by her foot slipping off of it, or whatever
was her current situation, and also not losing their connection to
each othere.</p>

<h2>Astronaut Behaviour</h2>

<p>I don&rsquo;t think a real astronaut would be as panicked or apparently as
untrained as Sandra Bullock&rsquo;s character.   In real life, an astronaut
would be methodical, matter of fact and execute previously practiced
plans.   They would be more knowledgeable and resourceful.  They would
know where the buttons were though they would probably follow a
manual.  They would think through the problem and execute.</p>

<p>In spite of what we might have in the near future, we don&rsquo;t take
passengers into space yet.  Mission specialists are trained as
astronauts for many months.</p>

<h2>Helmet and Space Suit</h2>

<p>Why, in an emergency situation, in a compromised spacecraft, and with
a threat of further breaching, would you ever take your space suit and
helmet off?  I can buy that maybe you would have trouble getting to
some parts of a space station or craft, but a trained astronaut
wouldn&rsquo;t remove the suit until it was absolutely necessary and then
only as long as required.</p>

<p>Similarly, they would keep the helmet on when in the smaller craft and
they certainly wouldn&rsquo;t leave it bouncing around in the cabin.</p>

<h2>Use The Fire Extinguisher</h2>

<p>A fire in the cabin would quickly use up oxygen.  No one, astronaut or
not, would allow a fire to burn without using a fire extinguisher on
it.  Even if you were seconds away from splashing into the ocean.</p>

<h2>Landing</h2>

<p>Again, an astronaut would be trained well enough to execute a
landing.   They wouldn&rsquo;t open the hatch too quickly.    They would
have a flotation device ready.   They&rsquo;d know and follow the
procedure.  They would use the radio to reply to the broadcasts that
were, in English!, trying to make contact.</p>

<p>They would probably have a survival pack including a radio, marker dye
and/or strobe and other provisions.</p>

<p>I can&rsquo;t imagine they would blow the hatch, sink the capsule and end up
having to swim with nothing to a convenient shore.</p>

<h2>Chute Ejection</h2>

<p>One problem was the Soyuz being bound to the ISS by it&rsquo;s parachute.
I&rsquo;m pretty sure the parachute can be ejected with explosive bolts at
landing.  I don&rsquo;t think she&rsquo;d have had to unbolt it by hand, but could
arm and fire the bolts by pushing a button.</p>

<h2>Collision with Debris</h2>

<p>An accident and collisions are not unreal, but space is big.  Really,
really big.  The chances of such a debris cluster hitting a relatively
microscopic target, even the size of the International Space Station,
are astronomically small.  The debris cloud itself would be expanding
and getting bigger and bigger.  You might impact a single bolt or
piece of junk, and it <em>could</em> be fatal.  However, I don&rsquo;t think you&rsquo;d
have a cloud concentrated enough to stay that close together by the
time it got to the ISS even if their orbits did intersect.</p>

<p>Rendezvousing with another space craft on purpose is extremely hard.
That much random junk doing it by accident is unrealistic.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s also true that a typical orbit at that altitude, I think, has a
period of about 90 minutes.  However, if you rendezvous with something
at the same altitude, it&rsquo;s going to take anything but 90 minutes.  If
two bodies were going in opposite directions it would take at most
about 45 minutes.  If they were going in the same direction but at
slightly different speeds, then it would take a really long time, much
longer than the 90 minutes.  And, if they are going in the same
direction, the speed of impact is much lower, just the difference in
their speeds.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Quote Marks]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/01/28/quote-marks/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-28T23:05:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/01/28/quote-marks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I think for nearly 30 years I&rsquo;ve used TeX style quoting for double
quotes in anything I wrote using ASCII text.</p>

<pre><code> ``Quoted text.''
</code></pre>

<p>Now that I&rsquo;ve adopted Markdown for nearly anything that I enter as
ASCII that&rsquo;s intended to be English text (probably rich text), I&rsquo;ve
also, finally, decided to use the double-quote character.  It&rsquo;s true
that the ASCII double quote doesn&rsquo;t explicitly specify whether a left-
or right-double quote is intended, but the implication is usually
clear enough and (hopefully) rendering code is now smart enough to do
the &ldquo;right thing.&rdquo;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Supernova! SN2014J]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/01/25/supernova-sn2014j/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-25T11:07:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/01/25/supernova-sn2014j</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/supernova.jpg"></p>

<p>For the first time since SN1987A there&rsquo;s a nearby supernova and this
one was apparently caught during it&rsquo;s brightness increase.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.space.com/24369-supernova-star-explosion-amateur-photos.html">Space.com</a><br>
<a href="http://www.cbat.eps.harvard.edu/unconf/followups/J09554214+6940260.html">IAU Central Bureau for Astronomical
Telegrams: PSN
J09554214+6940260</a><br>
<a href="http://www.cnn.com/2014/01/24/opinion/urry-exploding-supernova">Nicely written article by Meg Urry at
CNN.com</a><br></p>

<p>From Meg Urry&rsquo;s article:</p>

<blockquote><p>Type Ia supernovae have happened in our galactic neighborhood only
three times in the last 80 years.</p></blockquote>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>The reason Type Ia supernovae are special is their
uniformity. Basically, they all explode at about the same mass, so
they are all roughly equally luminous. Better understanding the
physics of that explosion and the effect of local galactic environment
will make Type Ia supernovae even better “standard candles” and
improve our understanding of the properties of dark energy and the
cosmological evolution of the universe. The more data we can get, and
the closer the supernova, the better the calibration.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.ucl.ac.uk/maps-faculty/maps-news-publication/maps1405">Discovery story from University College
London</a><br></p>

<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Type_Ia_supernova">Wikipedia article on Type Ia Supernovae</a></p>

<p>Why is this supernova J only 21 days into January, i.e, the 10th
supernova so var this year?   From the International Astronomical
Union (IAU)
<a href="http://www.cbat.eps.harvard.edu/lists/RecentSupernovae.html">here&rsquo;s the list</a>
of discoveries so far.</p>

<p><em>Image credit: UCL/University of London Observatory/Steve Fossey/Ben
 Cooke/Guy Pollack/Matthew Wilde/Thomas Wright (CC BY 3.0)</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Possible Massive Black Hole Duo]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/12/04/possible-massive-black-hole-duo/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-04T05:26:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/12/04/possible-massive-black-hole-duo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Via <a href="https://twitter.com/physorg_com/status/408160199460270081">@physorg_com</a> <a href="http://phys.org/news/2013-12-massive-black-hole-duo-sighting.html">Massive black hole duo: Possible sighting by WISE</a></p>

<blockquote><p>Astronomers have spotted what appear to be two supermassive black
holes at the heart of a remote galaxy, circling each other like dance
partners. The incredibly rare sighting was made with the help of
NASA&rsquo;s Wide-field Infrared Survey Explorer, or WISE.</p></blockquote>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>It is these close-knit black holes, also called black hole binaries,
that have been the hardest to find. The objects are usually too small
to be resolved even by powerful telescopes. Only a few strong
candidates have been identified to date, all relatively nearby. The
new WISE J233237.05-505643.5 is a new candidate, and located much
farther away, at 3.8 billion light-years from Earth.</p>

<p>Radio images with the Australian Telescope Compact Array were key to
identifying the dual nature of WISE J233237.05-505643.5. Supermassive
black holes at the cores of galaxies typically shoot out
pencil-straight jets, but, in this case, the jet showed a zigzag
pattern. According to the scientists, a second massive black hole
could, in essence, be pushing its weight around to change the shape of
the other black hole&rsquo;s jet.</p></blockquote>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;We note some caution in interpreting this mysterious system,&rdquo; said
Daniel Stern of JPL, a co-author of the study. &ldquo;There are several
extremely unusual properties to this system, from the multiple radio
jets to the Gemini data, which indicate a highly perturbed disk of
accreting material around the black hole, or holes. Two merging black
holes, which should be a common event in the universe, would appear to
be simplest explanation to explain all the current observations.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<h2>References</h2>

<p><a href="http://iopscience.iop.org/0004-637X/779/1/41/pdf/0004-637X_779_1_41.pdf">WISE J233237.05–505643.5: A Double-peaked, Broad-lined Active Galactic Nucleus with a Spiral-shaped Radio Morphology</a>, Chao-Wei Tsai et al. 2013 ApJ 779 41<br>
<a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1310.2257">Paper at arXiv</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ISON Sans Nucleus]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/12/01/ison-sans-nucleus/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-01T19:15:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/12/01/ison-sans-nucleus</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Quoting from the <a href="http://www.skyandtelescope.com/observing/objects/comets/Comet-ISON-Updates-193909261.html">Sky and Telescope Updates</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Dan Green of the International Astronomical Union&rsquo;s Central Bureau for
Astronomical Telegrams published a long summary (Electronic Telegram
No. 3731) early today. Excerpts:</p>

<blockquote><p>The comet&rsquo;s nucleus apparently disrupted near perihelion, with the
comet&rsquo;s head fading from perhaps a peak brightness of visual mag –2
some hours before perihelion to well below mag +1 before
perihelion. M. Knight, Lowell Observatory&hellip; [adds] that the brightest
feature in the coma faded steadily after perihelion from about mag 3.1
in a 95&#8221;-radius aperture when the comet first appeared from behind the
SOHO coronagraph occulting disk on Nov. 28.92 to about mag 6.5 on
Nov. 29.98&hellip;..</p>

<p>K.Battams, Naval Research Laboratory, writes that, based on the most
recent LASCO C3 images (Nov. 30.912 UT) &hellip; what remains is very
diffuse, largely transparent to background stars, and fading; it
appears that basically a cloud of dust remains&hellip;.</p>

<p>Z.Sekanina, Jet Propulsion Laboratory &hellip; finds that the comet&rsquo;s
production of dust terminated about 3 hours before perihelion&hellip;</p>

<p>The strong forward-scattering effect (phase angles near 120-130 deg)
has tempered the rate of post-perihelion fading of the comet, but the
merciless inverse-square power law of increasing heliocentric distance
is necessarily the dominant factor in the comet&rsquo;s forthcoming gradual
disappearance&hellip;</p></blockquote></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://groups.yahoo.com/neo/groups/comets-ml/conversations/messages/22839">CBET 3731 via Yahoo Groups</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/bad_astronomy/2013/12/01/comet_ison_post_mortem.html">A post mortem by Phil Plait</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Whither ISON]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/11/30/whither-ison/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-30T19:41:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/11/30/whither-ison</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From CIOC (the NASA <a href="http://www.isoncampaign.org/karl/a-trail-of-questions">Comet ISON Observing Campaign</a>):</p>

<blockquote><p>Will it be naked eye visible? When? How bright?</p>

<p>This is definitely the toughest question but also the most
frequent. We still don&rsquo;t know if it will be naked eye but based on its
current brightness in the LASCO images &ndash; which is around magnitude +5
and fading &ndash; it does seem unlikely that there will be much to see in
the night sky. I suspect that some of the outstanding
astrophotographers around the world will be able to get something, but
I doubt it will be as spectacular as before perihelion. I hope I&rsquo;m
wrong though.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.skyandtelescope.com/observing/ataglance">Sky and Telescope</a><br></p>

<p><a href="http://www.skyandtelescope.com/observing/objects/comets/Comet-ISON-Updates-193909261.html">Sky and Telescope Updates</a><br></p>

<p><a href="http://www.isoncampaign.org/karl/a-trail-of-questions">ISON Campaign: A Trail of Questions</a><br></p>

<p><a href="http://www.universetoday.com/106832/zombie-ison-behaving-like-a-comet-stunned-astronomers-say/">Universe Today</a><br></p>

<p><a href="http://apod.nasa.gov/apod/ap131130.html">APOD</a><br></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comet ISON Post Perihelion]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/11/29/comet-ison-post-perihelion/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-29T14:24:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/11/29/comet-ison-post-perihelion</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/comet_ison_postp.png"></p>

<p>Reports are starting to come in regarding what happened to Comet ISON
C/2012 S1 after passing the perihelion of its orbit.</p>

<p>From
<a href="https://twitter.com/astroengine/status/406342402706665472">@astroengine</a>
and <a href="https://twitter.com/discovery_space/status/406342053455347712">@discovery_space</a>:
 <a href="http://news.discovery.com/space/astronomy/comet-ison-barely-survives-thanksgiving-solar-roast-131129.htm">Comet ISON Barely Survives Thanksgiving Solar
 Roast</a><br></p>

<p>Update from NASA CIOC: <a href="http://www.isoncampaign.org/karl/schroedingers-comet">Schrödinger&rsquo;s Comet</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[More Comet ISON]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/11/24/more-comet-ison/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-24T17:02:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/11/24/more-comet-ison</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>More news and mostly images of Comet ISON C/2012 S1.</p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/earthskyscience/status/404265533240930304">Today&rsquo;s Image form @EarthSky</a>.<br>
<a href="https://twitter.com/chrislintott/status/404698473317928960">Will Gater picture via @chrislintott</a>
<a href="https://twitter.com/willgater/status/404643457924210689">Picture via @willgater</a><br>
<a href="https://twitter.com/chrislintott/status/404684115506909184">And Another via @chrislintott</a><br>
<a href="https://twitter.com/SungrazerComets/status/404282911290953728">From @SungrazerComets</a><br></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comet ISON C/2012 S1]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/11/24/comet-ison-c-slash-2012-s1/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-24T00:03:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/11/24/comet-ison-c-slash-2012-s1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From EarthSky</p>

<blockquote><p>Comet ISON, anticipated by skywatchers for more than a year, is
brightening fast just days from its fateful hairpin swing on November
28 around the broiling surface of the sun. The comet is now a
greenish-white fuzzy “star” in binoculars, low in the east-southeast
at the beginning of dawn. Telescopic photos are showing it with a
long, ribbony tail. The comet has flared with unexpected outbursts of
gas and dust three times already this month.</p></blockquote>

<h2>References</h2>

<p><a href="http://earthsky.org/science-wire/comet-ison-brightening-fast-as-its-moment-of-truth-nears">Comet ISON brightening fast as its moment of truth nears</a><a href="https://twitter.com/earthskyscience/status/403314232701091840">via @earthskyscience</a><br>
<a href="http://www.observatorij.org/cobs/images/latest-lightcurve.png">Latest Light Curve</a><br>
<a href="http://spaceweathergallery.com/indiv_upload.php?upload_id=90223&amp;PHPSESSID=34o31mq8nus0r94icsrtd1mh73">Image by Bob Lukasik from Brasstown Bald 2103-11-20</a><br>
<a href="http://www.isoncampaign.org/karl/updated-ison-encke-movie">ISON Encke Movie</a><br>
<a href="http://www.isoncampaign.org/karl/ison-encke-mercury-home">ISON, Encke, Mercury and Home by Karl Battams</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Evernote Encryption]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/11/15/evernote-encryption/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-15T09:32:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/11/15/evernote-encryption</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Nice!  Evernote let&rsquo;s you encrypt the text in a note!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[M103 The Christmas Tree Cluster]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/10/11/m103-the-christmas-tree-cluster/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-11T07:34:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/10/11/m103-the-christmas-tree-cluster</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/m103mg_border.jpg" title="" ></p>

<p>Last night we visted the Fernbank Observatory.  In the course of
looking at a very nice open cluster, NGC 457 I believe, in Cassiopeia,
I was reminded of one of my favorites there, M103.  I always called it
the Christmas Tree cluster and enjoyed showing it to folks.</p>

<p>At the site One-Minute Astronomer
<a href="http://oneminuteastronomer.com/1098/3-clusters-cassiopeia/">oneminuteastronomer.com</a>,
Brian Ventrudo describes M103 as</p>

<blockquote><p>&hellip;the last object in Messier’s original catalog (it was later padded
to include 6 more objects).  It’s also easy to find, about 1 degree
northeast of Ruchbah (or delta Cass).  At 8,500 light years away, it’s
one of the most distant open clusters in Messier’s catalog.  In a
small scope, the cluster is unmistakably triangular and displays
perhaps two dozen stars.  The star triple star Struve 131 is the
bright star at the north vertex of the cluster; you can easily resolve
all three stars in Struve 131 in a scope, even at low power.</p></blockquote>

<p><em>Image credit: by Margin Germano at <a href="http://martingermano.com/">martingermano.com</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Transition to the iPhone]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/10/07/transition-to-the-iphone/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-07T09:06:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/10/07/transition-to-the-iphone</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/iphone_screen.png" title="" ></p>

<p>I can now summarize my previous post up in one sentence:  Android had
become tiring and I find the iPhone delightful.</p>

<p>The new iPhone 5C arrived on Wed 2013-10-02 and I found the transition
from the almost-two-year-old Android Galaxy Nexus 4.2.2 easy and
painless.  So far I&rsquo;m happy using a new device with a fresh new
interface and all that I consider essential.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>I ordered the iPhone 5C on-line at the Apple Store.  The process was
simple and integration with my Verizon account and changes were
straightforward.  There was no charge for shipping and the device
shipped by UPS and arrived in two days, i.e., I ordered it on Monday
and it arrived on Wednesday.  Somehow, Apple got the idea it should
have arrived on Tuesday and sent an apologetic email alert about a
shipping delay.</p>

<p>Transitioning the phone over to my Verizon account after turning it on
was equally simple and only involved entering my phone number and the
other typical identifying information Verizon wants.</p>

<p>Syncing my Gmail/Google contact list to the phone was a quick web
search and simply adding that account to the Settings for the phone.
I enabled contact syncing (but not email!) and much later, this
morning in fact, I turned on calendar syncing.  I didn&rsquo;t sync email
because I&rsquo;m using the Gmail app and not the iPhone email app.</p>

<h2>Apps</h2>

<p>For installing apps I logged into my existing Apple account with no
problem.  In the first evening I was able to easily install nearly
every app I consider essential, including all of the Google apps like
Gmail, Maps, Chrome and more.</p>

<p>I continued to pull down apps over the next few days as I thought of
them, needed them, or just had time to&mdash;the demand paging
approach.</p>

<p>Amazon Cloud player was also an easy install and works just as it does
on the Android.  It will stream from the cloud or download songs,
albums, or playlists to the phone to play them locally.</p>

<p>With a quick search of some on-line recommendations I settled on the
excellent program, Downcast, for downloading and playing podcasts.
Though I liked Doggcatcher on Android, I think Downcast is actually
much better.</p>

<p>I figured out how to rearrange the apps on the screens so that the
important apps were on the bottom bar (Amazon Cloud Player, Phone,
Messages, Chrome), how to put apps into folders, etc.  As expected,
there&rsquo;s still fiddling around left to do to get the arrangement of
apps and organization of the screens balanced so they work best for
me, but it&rsquo;s very workable right now.</p>

<h2>Anticipated Problems</h2>

<p>For the most part, things I worried about the most haven&rsquo;t been any
trouble at all.</p>

<p>Having no back button doesn&rsquo;t really cause a problem.  Apps usually
provide their own back button, or some equivalent, when you&rsquo;d need
one.  It&rsquo;s usually in the upper left corner.  And there&rsquo;s bailing out
with the home button but I rarely find myself using that as an
alternative to a back button.</p>

<p>Other changes in using a different interface just haven&rsquo;t been a
problem.  The new UI has been easy and fast to learn.  I like it a lot
and, since I didn&rsquo;t have IOS 6 as a reference, I don&rsquo;t have anything
to complain about regarding differences.</p>

<p>Surprisingly I don&rsquo;t miss the widgets at all.  There&rsquo;s a nice economy
of focus to only seeing information when you want to see it.  There&rsquo;s
not the distraction of some random Facebook update and, well, I guess
I just didn&rsquo;t really depend that much on the other widgets.  So, I
thought widgets were really neat, I still do, but I&rsquo;ve found they
aren&rsquo;t essential.  Perhaps that means they&rsquo;re really clutter, but I
like them enough I wouldn&rsquo;t suggest they be removed from Android.</p>

<p>One of the advantages of Android is the ability to customize almost
anything and everything.  It&rsquo;s probably my personal stage of phone
usage, but I don&rsquo;t want to do that kind of hacking, I just want
something that works.</p>

<h2>No perfect box</h2>

<p>Here&rsquo;s the worst thing about the iPhone 5C: the box.  Most Apple
products come in packaging that&rsquo;s so nice you hate to throw it away.
The 5C came in a somewhat annoying, oversized, retro-like plastic
case.  And the worst sin of all, it was sealed with tape that left
behind a pet-roller-like sticky band which makes you want to throw
whole thing away as quickly as possible.  The opposite effect of the
typical packaging.</p>

<p>Yes, it&rsquo;s not that important, really.  Just bothersome.</p>

<h2>Missing out on the Nexus 5</h2>

<p>I don&rsquo;t mind.  If the leaked LG information is accurate, the Nexus 5
isn&rsquo;t attention-grabbing to me.  I have more to say in another post
about why that may be.  If I&rsquo;d waited and then sprung for the Moto X
or Nexus 5, I&rsquo;d have a phone nearly the same as what I had.  It might
perform better from some ratchet clicks of CPU specs, but I don&rsquo;t know
if I&rsquo;d notice.  Maybe.</p>

<h2>Reality check</h2>

<p>I know I&rsquo;m still grazing on the greener grass at the start of a
new-phone honeymoon.  The real test will be how its working after one,
six and 12 months.  But I have to say, being able to fall right in
with all that I consider essential right there and a nice solid
interface and hardware, I can&rsquo;t see the complaints yet.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting an iPhone?]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/09/28/getting-an-iphone/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-28T12:56:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/09/28/getting-an-iphone</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/iphone5c.png" title="" ></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m thinking about getting an iPhone.  I know this is a shocking
thought.  I&rsquo;ve never had an iPhone before.  The only smart phones I&rsquo;ve
ever owned were the Android phones, starting with the G1.  I currently
have a Samsung Galaxy Nexus with (get out the phone, tap settings,
about phone, ah&hellip;) 4.2.2.  I&rsquo;d been planning to get a Samsung S4 or
S3.  I think the HTC One is currently the best Android phone hardware
out there.</p>

<!-- More -->


<h2>It has to be Google</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve come to one critical conclusion about Android phones.  I&rsquo;ll only
accept a &ldquo;pure Google&rdquo; phone.  Currently that would be the Moto X for
the newest.  I&rsquo;ve heard that Verizon&rsquo;s add-ons for the S4 are
unbearable.</p>

<p>My thinking had been that I&rsquo;d just download one of the ROMs and flash
an S4 into a more pure-Google experience, but that&rsquo;s looking like more
bother and annoyance than I&rsquo;m interested in.  In fact, the Android
experience seems to come with a growing amount of annoyance, in spite
of the great things about it.  The signal to noise ratio is getting
worse.  That&rsquo;s one reason I&rsquo;m thinking about changing.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s probably a new, pure Google phone soon to come, maybe under
the Nexus name.  It might be worth waiting for, but I&rsquo;m inclined not
to wait.</p>

<p>The S3 doesn&rsquo;t seem significantly different from my current,
two-year-old Galaxy Nexus.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s true that I&rsquo;m completely ensconced in the Google system of apps,
especially on my phone with Gmail Google Voice.  However, the web
experiences and apps on the iPhone seem acceptable.  The Google apps
on IOS may lag the Android world, but I&rsquo;m not looking for the latest
and greatest.  Lately I fear the continuous feature roll-outs from
Google.  I don&rsquo;t find that much delight in what&rsquo;s coming out
lately.  If IOS as a platform slows that down some, I may just count
that as a huge advantage.</p>

<h2>Iphone looks interesting and sufficient</h2>

<p>The iPhone seems both interesting and sufficient.  The new interface
looks pleasant.  It promises to bring some consistency and it has the
new, thin fonts (that Android recently brought) that I like.  Google
destroyed the nice clock the Android used to have with the stupid,
bold-face hour display.  If the IOS 7 UI is consistent and performs
well, that will meet my needs.</p>

<h2>Best Cameras</h2>

<p>The iPhones undoubtedly make the best pictures.  My family all have
iPhones now and their pictures are consistently better than those I
make with my phone.</p>

<h2>Reliable behaviour</h2>

<p>Android has been multitasking, in what I would consider a pure way,
since the beginning and I&rsquo;ve always appreciated that.  However, these
days, for whatever reason, I find myself constantly tapping things
where nothing happens.  Or the delay is so long I&rsquo;m not sure whether a
tap registered or not.  I&rsquo;ll take reliable behaviour over pure
multitasking and whatever else is going on there.</p>

<p>That said, I completely admit that this could be a false difference.
Finding out will be part of this &ldquo;experiment.&rdquo;</p>

<h2>Apps and Widgets</h2>

<p>As far as I can tell, all of the apps that I consider essential to my
daily phone life are available.  I&rsquo;ll really miss the widgets,
particularly my analog clock and the weather widget.  I&rsquo;ll also miss
the little app that shows the time in various time zones with a little
globe, showing the day-night part of the earth, that I can spin around
with my finger.  I expect there&rsquo;s surely some similar IOS app there.
I&rsquo;ll find out.</p>

<p>I think the GPS navigation may not be as good, and that may be a huge
loss.  I&rsquo;ll have to see if that&rsquo;s the case and if I can live with
that.</p>

<h2>The smaller screen</h2>

<p>How will the smaller screen be?  This might be my biggest question.
Whenever I look at one of the family&rsquo;s phones, I never think, Wow,
that screen is really small.  I can barely look at it.  Generally I
don&rsquo;t even notice.  Apparent screen size has to do with viewing
distance.  If holding the screen closer enough to cancel any
difference isn&rsquo;t noticeable, it shouldn&rsquo;t matter.  This is something
I&rsquo;ll find out.  Update: Actually, I&rsquo;ve now held my Galaxy Nexus and an
iPhone 5c side by side and I barely had to move the screen a phone
thickness to match apparent sizes, actually solid angles.</p>

<h2>It&rsquo;s an experiment</h2>

<p>This will be an experiment.  I know the grass always looks greener on
the other side and I don&rsquo;t doubt that&rsquo;s true here.  I have complaints
and things annoy me.  My live snow fall wall paper is starting to
crash and it&rsquo;s starting to misbehave in other ways.  Still, I can
always return back to that phone, and a future pure Android phone, if
I can&rsquo;t stand the iPhone world.</p>

<p>If I do make this leap (I haven&rsquo;t committed yet), I&rsquo;ll write some
update on what I think about the progress.</p>

<h2>In summary</h2>

<p>My reasons for changing.</p>

<ul>
<li>I&rsquo;ll only accept a pure Google phone for Android.</li>
<li>The current options really don&rsquo;t outshine my two-year-old 32-GB Galaxy Nexus.</li>
<li>Android signal-to-noise (delight vs. annoyance) is getting progressively worse.</li>
<li>IOS has Google apps.</li>
<li>IOS also has all of my other essential apps.</li>
<li>The iPhone has better cameras.</li>
<li>I&rsquo;m convinced the UI behaviour is more reliable and stable.</li>
</ul>


<p>Some possible down sides.</p>

<ul>
<li>I&rsquo;ll miss the widgets.</li>
<li>GPS navigation may not be good enough.</li>
<li>The smaller screen.</li>
<li>Something I haven&rsquo;t thought of.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Foucault Pendulum]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/09/22/the-foucault-pendulum/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-22T06:37:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/09/22/the-foucault-pendulum</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/20130922_Berry_Pendulum.jpg"></p>

<p>The old planetarium adjoined the science hall of the museum and
the center piece exhibit there was a Foucault pendulum.  It was a
wonderful demonstration of the rotation of the earth.  The planetarium
office was on the third floor and also attached to the side of the
cylindrical section of the building containing the planetarium.  It
was my office until I moved into a brand new, below ground suite of
staff offices beneath the exhibit halls.  The interesting thing was
that the pendulum was suspended from the ceiling of that third floor
office.  Yes, the room had an opening in the floor, appropriately
surrounded by a rail for safety.</p>

<p>One of the Google Doodles for this past week was the Foucault
pendulum.  I looked at it a day or so after it was on the main search
page.  I didn&rsquo;t look at any of the explanations it might have linked
to, but it reminded me of trying to explain the pendulum to folks in
the exhibit hall.  The time it takes the pendulum to apparently rotate
is a very difficult concept and I&rsquo;ve been trying to think of a good
way to explain it for many decades.  Over the past few years, I think
I finally hit upon a reasonable and understandable explanation.</p>

<p><em>Image credit: Foucault pendulum at Berry College in Rome, Georgia
by <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/courtneymcgough/2318810863/">Courney McGough</a>
CC BY-NC-ND 2.0. Note, this is not the particular pendulum discussed in this
post.</em></p>

<!-- More -->


<h2>The Easy Part</h2>

<p>Basically, the Foucault pendulum demonstrates that the earth is
rotating.  A pendulum always tries to swing in the same direction.
Imagine holding a pendulum over a rotating phonograph record (that&rsquo;s a
vinyl record, you know, music, for you young folk).  Also imagine
placing your favorite, tiny action figure near the outside of the
record.  To the little figure, it will look like the pendulum,
swinging constantly in the same direction, is rotating, changing it&rsquo;s
direction.  That proves the record is turning.  This is how a Foucault
pendulum would behave at the North Pole and it&rsquo;s simple to understand.</p>

<p>However, things are different at the equator.  Imagine starting a
pendulum at the equator swinging north-south.  Now as the earth
rotates, the pendulum can continue to happily swing north and south
without any change in it&rsquo;s direction, all the way around the course
of a day.  The pendulum itself would be traveling <em>around</em> the earth,
but not <em>rotating</em>, relative to the ground beneath it, as it went.</p>

<h2>The Weird Part</h2>

<p>So the pendulum would appear to rotate once every 24 hours at the
pole, but at the equator it would never rotate, it would take infinite
time.  What&rsquo;s worse, between the two extremes it takes longer and
longer to rotate as one moves from the pole to lower latitudes.</p>

<p>In Atlanta, for example, at about 34 degrees latitude, the pendulum
would take about 43 hours to go around once.  How can that be since
the earth rotates in 24 hours?</p>

<h2>Try Driving</h2>

<p>Imagine the earth as a smooth sphere, no mountains or oceans, like a
globe.  And imagine you&rsquo;re going to drive around the earth in a car.
To make it interesting, we&rsquo;ll drive fast enough to make it around the
earth in 24 hours.  At the equator, this is easy.  We point the car
east and take off an 1000 miles per hour, or so.</p>

<p>What about 34 degrees above the equator?  There, we want to drive
along a parallel line, a parallel of latitude.  If we point our car
east and set off straight ahead, we won&rsquo;t follow the parallel.
Instead the car will follow a great circle (like a tilted equator).
It will cross the real equator &frac14; of the way around, hit 34 degrees
<em>south</em> latitude on the opposite side, and arrive again at it&rsquo;s
starting point.</p>

<p>To follow the parallel at 34 degrees, we have to turn the steering
wheel slightly to the left to stay on track.  Aircraft and ship&rsquo;s
pilots understand this.  Usually they like to travel along great
circles.</p>

<p>So if we cut our steering wheel to the left a little and drove at an
appropriate speed, we&rsquo;d make it around the parallel in 24 hours.  Now,
what if we took the car off of the earth-sized sphere and set it down
on an infinite plane?  With the steering wheel cut to the left that
same amount and traveling at the speed we used before, how long would
it take the car to drive around in a circle?  The answer is about the
43 hours it took the Foucault pendulum to go around.</p>

<p>Well, think about it.  If we took our car from the equator, with it&rsquo;s
steering wheel pointed straight ahead, it wouldn&rsquo;t go around in a
circle at all.  It would just drive off toward infinity.</p>

<p>For what it&rsquo;s worth, our car at the north pole would have to turn the
steering almost 90 degrees to the left and drive in donuts around the
pole.  In that case, just like the pendulum, the car would go around
in about 24 hours on the plane, if we drove (in this case very slowly)
at a speed to make it around the pole in 24 hours.</p>

<h2>Moving vs. Turning</h2>

<p>Notice that as the car is farther north, it&rsquo;s driving more slowly but
turning more.  That&rsquo;s what&rsquo;s really going on here.  At the equator,
you really don&rsquo;t turn <em>about a vertical axis</em> at all.  You head off
toward the east as if you&rsquo;re standing on a moving sidewalk.  Sure,
you&rsquo;re turning about the earth&rsquo;s axis, but not around your <em>own</em> axis
pointed straight up.  At the equator it&rsquo;s all moving and no turning.</p>

<p>At the pole, it&rsquo;s all turning but no moving.  You don&rsquo;t move or you&rsquo;d
leave the pole.  As you go from the equator to the pole, your motion
around the earth becomes more a turning motion and less a moving
motion.  You can tell there&rsquo;s less &ldquo;moving&rdquo; because the parallels are
smaller and smaller.  You don&rsquo;t have as far to go.</p>

<p>For the mathematical types, the time it takes the pendulum to rotate
is 24 hours divided by the sine of the latitude.</p>

<h2>That Crazy World of Geometry</h2>

<p>This is just one example of how much trouble we get into if we leave
the comfortable world of Euclid&rsquo;s plane geometry and try to do things
in a crazy world of say a sphere or saddle-shape.  And that&rsquo;s just for
a two-dimensional surface (of sorts).  If you get into other
geometries in three and more dimensions, then you&rsquo;re in the crazy
world that Einstein and his successors used to explain gravity purely
in terms of geometry&mdash;no forces needed.</p>

<h2>Back in the exhibit hall</h2>

<p>Each morning I&rsquo;d manually start the massive pendulum on it&rsquo;s
three-story cable swinging north-south.  Later in the day, it&rsquo;s
direction would have visibly changed.  Traditionally, an exhibit will
have little blocks that the pendulum can knock over as it changes
direction.  It&rsquo;s good enough to show that the earth truly is rotating
without understanding all of the above.  And it&rsquo;s pretty clever,
really, to be able to show such a large effect with such a simple
experiment.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Happy Autumnal Equinox!]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/09/21/happy-autumnal-equinox/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-21T23:39:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/09/21/happy-autumnal-equinox</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On Sunday afternoon at 16:44 EDT.</p>

<p>Sun 2013-09-22 20:44:00 +0000
Sun 2013-09-22 16:44:00 -0400</p>

<p>(Times are to the nearest minute).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Do We Know When Voyager Reaches Interstellar Space?]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/09/14/how-do-we-know-when-voyager-reaches-interstellar-space/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-14T19:44:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/09/14/how-do-we-know-when-voyager-reaches-interstellar-space</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/voyager_pia17462main_8k.jpg"></p>

<p><a href="http://www.jpl.nasa.gov/news/news.php?release=2013-278">From the Jet Propulsion Laboratory</a>.</p>

<blockquote><p>Whether and when NASA&rsquo;s Voyager 1 spacecraft, humankind&rsquo;s most distant
object, broke through to interstellar space, the space between stars,
has been a thorny issue. For the last year, claims have surfaced every
few months that Voyager 1 has &ldquo;left our solar system.&rdquo; Why has the
Voyager team held off from saying the craft reached interstellar space
until now?</p></blockquote>

<!-- More -->


<p>&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>Then on April 9, 2013, it happened: Voyager 1&rsquo;s plasma wave instrument
picked up local plasma oscillations. Scientists think they probably
stemmed from a burst of solar activity from a year before, a burst
that has become known as the St. Patrick&rsquo;s Day Solar Storms. The
oscillations increased in pitch through May 22 and indicated that
Voyager was moving into an increasingly dense region of plasma. This
plasma had the signatures of interstellar plasma, with a density more
than 40 times that observed by Voyager 2 in the heliosheath.</p>

<p>Gurnett and Kurth began going through the recent data and found a
fainter, lower-frequency set of oscillations from Oct. 23 to Nov. 27,
2012. When they extrapolated back, they deduced that Voyager had first
encountered this dense interstellar plasma in August 2012, consistent
with the sharp boundaries in the charged particle and magnetic field
data on August 25.</p>

<p>Stone called three meetings of the Voyager team. They had to decide
how to define the boundary between our solar bubble and interstellar
space and how to interpret all the data Voyager 1 had been sending
back. There was general agreement Voyager 1 was seeing interstellar
plasma, based on the results from Gurnett and Kurth, but the sun still
had influence. One persisting sign of solar influence, for example,
was the detection of outside particles hitting Voyager from some
directions more than others. In interstellar space, these particles
would be expected to hit Voyager uniformly from all directions.</p></blockquote>

<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/voyger_pia17046-640.jpg"></p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;In the end, there was general agreement that Voyager 1 was indeed
outside in interstellar space,&rdquo; Stone said. &ldquo;But that location comes
with some disclaimers &ndash; we&rsquo;re in a mixed, transitional region of
interstellar space. We don&rsquo;t know when we&rsquo;ll reach interstellar space
free from the influence of our solar bubble.&rdquo;</p>

<p>So, would the team say Voyager 1 has left the solar system? Not
exactly &ndash; and that&rsquo;s part of the confusion. Since the 1960s, most
scientists have defined our solar system as going out to the Oort
Cloud, where the comets that swing by our sun on long timescales
originate. That area is where the gravity of other stars begins to
dominate that of the sun. It will take about 300 years for Voyager 1
to reach the inner edge of the Oort Cloud and possibly about 30,000
years to fly beyond it. Informally, of course, &ldquo;solar system&rdquo;
typically means the planetary neighborhood around our sun. Because of
this ambiguity, the Voyager team has lately favored talking about
interstellar space, which is specifically the space between each
star&rsquo;s realm of plasma influence.</p></blockquote>

<p><em>Image credits: NASA/JPL-Caltech</em></p>

<h2>Other articles</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.universetoday.com/104717/its-official-voyager-1-is-now-in-interstellar-space/">It’s Official: Voyager 1 Is Now In Interstellar Space</a> in Universe Today</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thirty Years Since We Watched Voyager on TV]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/09/14/thirty-years-since-voyager/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-14T08:42:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/09/14/thirty-years-since-voyager</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//postimages/20130914_saturn.jpg"></p>

<p><em>[This is a re-post of a blog post I first wrote and posted in
 2010-11-12 in <a href="http://monolith149daily.blogspot.com/2010/11/thirty-years-since-we-watched-voyager.html">Monolith149 Daily</a>.
 I&rsquo;ve made some slight edits to the text.]</em></p>

<p>I was the director of the planetarium at the time and had received a
letter from NASA that they were broadcasting live coverage of the
Voyager 1 encounter via satellite.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>When I was a kid, reading library books about the solar system, there
would often be a chapter at the end of the book on the Grand Tour of
the Planets.  A favorable alignment of the four gas giants, Jupiter,
Saturn, Uranus and Neptune, would allow a single spacecraft to visit
each of them using gravitational assist, in the distant future of the
1980s.</p>

<p>Fast-forward to 1977, either 5 Sep 1977 (Voyager 2) or 20 Aug 1977
(Voyager 1), I forget which.* It&rsquo;s morning and I&rsquo;m lying on the sofa
after being at the museum&rsquo;s observatory all night.  I&rsquo;m watching the
Voyager spacecraft launch on TV.  With those launches, the Grand Tour
became a reality and Voyager 2 visited all four planets.</p>

<p>However, it was Voyager 1 that visited Jupiter and Saturn first.  The
spacecraft stole some of Jupiter&rsquo;s orbital momentum, causing Jupiter
to fall just a little bit toward the sun, as it accelerated on to
Saturn</p>

<p>The event was going to happen on 12 Nov 1980.  There was no NASA
channel at the time so I had to call the local cable operator (Cox)
and ask them to tune into the particular satellite and transponder
that NASA had arranged and to feed the coverage out over a spare
channel on their cable plant.  It took some convincing since they were
reluctant to actually commit a channel, even for a one-time event.  In
the end, I think I ended up talking to a guy in a control shack,
probably running their dish farm, who impressed me as not wanting to
be bothered with events from other planets.  My memory is that I never
got an absolute firm commitment but something more like a shaky okay
which was more than a little worrisome.</p>

<p>Next, it was necessary to find a video tape recorder and it turned out
there was one I could borrow from the board of education.  I drove
down to their dusty equipment warehouse to pick it up.  Or maybe it
was just the road by the warehouse that was dusty.  It was an old
&frac34;-inch U-Matic machine, a video cassette size frequently used
by TV stations in those days.  The &frac12;-in cassettes were just starting
to become popular as the VHS vs. Betamax battle was raging.</p>

<p>We hauled the recorder over to the house of one of our staff members&#8217;
parents to record the coverage since they had cable.  The encounter
was in the middle of the day and several of the planetarium staff were
crowded into their den, watching the show.</p>

<p>It was a heady time indeed as we watched those black and white
pictures scroll slowly in because the data download rates from the
space probe were slower than the modems of the time.  Of course they
were not digitally post-processed yet&mdash;they were pretty raw
images&mdash;so there were just the beginning hints of some of the amazing
sites to come.  The coverage cameras showed ecstatic scientists
watching the same images appear on their control room monitors and
there were several interviews with Ed Stone, Carl Sagan and others who
were seeing their own life-long fantasies come true.</p>

<p>Sometimes you suddenly arrive at those moments when you get goosebumps
and a lump in your throat, when you know you&rsquo;re experiencing pinnacle
achievements in human history.  This was one of them.</p>

<p>As the pictures crawled in, I believe it was possible, even in those
first images, to see the spokes in the rings, the braided F-ring, and
some of the other jaw-dropping, never-imagined features of Saturn
up-close.</p>

<p>After recording the fly-by, we borrowed a TV from one of the local TV
shops.  It was just a standard 19-in, or slightly larger, CRT.  We set
it up in the planetarium and opened to the public for a replay of the
&ldquo;live&rdquo; Voyager-Saturn encounter.  I remember we had a bit of
difficulty because the video tape recorder had a separate RF
modulator, the size of a small, chunky game cartridge, that had to be
physically plugged into the back of the machine before we could get a
signal to the TV.</p>

<p>I guess we had enough lead time to advertise the event using the usual
TV and newspaper avenues because there was a pretty good turnout.
There were college professors, amateur astronomers and many other
enthusiastic folks from the community who were just as thrilled
as the crew at JPL to see these first images coming back from the
ringed planet, even though our replay was delayed by hours.</p>

<p>As I recall there were encounter events over two or three days as
Voyager flew by some of Saturn&rsquo;s moons and made its way across
Saturn&rsquo;s &ldquo;miniature solar system,&rdquo; so we had probably two and possibly
three nights of replay.</p>

<p>Today Voyager 1 is over 115 AU (astronomical units) from the Sun.  By
definition, the Earth is 1 AU from the Sun.  Pluto is, on average, about 40
AU distant.  Voyager 1 is the most distant, active spacecraft in the solar
system and it&rsquo;s still collecting and transmitting data.</p>

<p>&ldquo;In four to six years, Voyager 1 is expected to cross beyond the
heliosheath, the outer layer of the bubble around our solar system
that is composed of ionized atoms streaming outward from our sun,&rdquo;
reports a news release from NASA this past October [2010].</p>

<p>We&rsquo;ve come a long way from those solar system books from the library,
written in days when artists never even thought to include clouds when
illustrating the Earth as seen from space.  I&rsquo;ve been amazed to see so
many of those funny but always awe-inspiring artist&rsquo;s conceptions come
to reality.  It will be fascinating to see which ones come next.</p>

<p align="center">
*&nbsp;*&nbsp;*
</p>


<p>It was just past the turn of the century and I&rsquo;d never thought about
it before even after a couple of years or so.  It was a friend who
pointed out to me that the two vehicles sitting in our driveway were a
Voyager and a Saturn.</p>

<p>__________<br>
* No that&rsquo;s not a typo.  Due to the solar system and mission mechanics
involved, Voyager 2 was actually launched before Voyager 1.</p>

<p><em>Image Credit</em></p>

<p><em>Ghostly Spokes in the Rings</em></p>

<p><em>Scientists first saw these somewhat wedge-shaped, transient clouds of tiny particles known as “spokes” in images from NASA&rsquo;s Voyager spacecraft. They dubbed these features in Saturn&rsquo;s B ring “spokes” because they looked like bicycle spokes. An electrostatic charge, the way static electricity on Earth can raise the hair on your arms, appears to be levitating tiny ring particles above the ring plane, but scientists are still figuring out how the particles get that charge as they analyze images from NASA&rsquo;s Cassini spacecraft.</em></p>

<p><em>The image on the left was obtained by Voyager 2 on Aug. 22, 1981. The
image on the right was obtained by Cassini on Nov. 2, 2008.</em></p>

<p><em>Image credit: NASA/JPL and NASA/JPL/SSI</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
