<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: technology | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/technology/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2014-12-10T08:14:08-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Whither the Self-Driving Car?]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/22/whither-the-self-driving-car/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-22T04:20:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/22/whither-the-self-driving-car</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 12</a></p>

<p>Lee Gomes writes in Slate The autonomous Google car may never actually
happen.</p>

<blockquote><p>For starters, the Google car was able to do so much more than its
predecessors in large part because the company had the resources to do
something no other robotic car research project ever could:  develop
an ingenious but extremely expensive mapping system.  These maps
contain the exact three-dimensional location of streetlights, stop
signs, crosswalks, lane markings, and every other crucial aspect of a
roadway.</p></blockquote>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>&hellip;the maps necessary for the Google car are an order of magnitude
more complicated [than Google Maps].</p></blockquote>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>To create them, a dedicated vehicle outfitted with a bank of sensors
first makes repeated passes scanning the roadway to be mapped.  The
data is <em>[sic]</em> then downloaded, with every square foot of the
landscape pored over by both humans and computers to make sure that
all-important real-world objects have been captured.  This complete
map gets loaded into the car&rsquo;s memory before a journey, and because
it knows from the map about the location of many stationary objects,
it&rsquo;s computer&mdash;essentially a generic PC running Ubuntu Linux&mdash;can
devote more of its energies to tracking moving objects, like other
cars.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/technology/technology/2014/10/google_self_driving_car_it_may_never_actually_happen.html">Driving in Circles by Lee Gomes in Slate</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
