<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: telescopes | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/telescopes/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2014-11-11T05:43:20-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Buying a Telescope - Part 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/06/buying-a-telescope-part-3/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-06T04:58:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/06/buying-a-telescope-part-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 27</a></p>

<p>Some parting thoughts.</p>

<h2>Magnification</h2>

<p>There&rsquo;s a common misconception that telescopes are all about
magnification.  One sure sign of a questionable telescope is one that
puts its magnification up front.  Worse is one that advertises 200x,
300x, and more.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>It works like this.  The main mirror or lens, called the &ldquo;objective,&rdquo;
collects light, information, and produces a real image somewhere in
the back of the telescope.  It&rsquo;s usually inside the eyepiece holder.
It&rsquo;s called a real image because it acts like a little picture
floating there in space.  If you point a telescope at something and
look at the back of it, with no eyepiece, you can see the real image.</p>

<p>The quality of the image, including it&rsquo;s resolution, depends on the
amount of information collected by the objective, generally the larger
the aperture, the more detail is in the image.  The eyepiece is a
little magnifying lens you use to look at the image, just like you use
a magnifier to look at a small object like jewelry or a photograph.</p>

<p>If you imagine taking something with a picture like a newspaper,
magazine or a book (if you can even find one of those), and look at it
with say a 10x or 20x magnifier, you can probably see more details in
the picture.  You might be able to make out something that you missed
without the magnifier.</p>

<p>However, if you then find a 100x or 200x magnifier and look at the
picture, what do you think you&rsquo;ll see?  You&rsquo;ll probably see the dots
the picture is made of, or just a fuzzy blur but you won&rsquo;t see any
more details in the original picture.  There&rsquo;s not enough detail,
resolution, information in the picture for 200x to work.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s the way a telescope real image works.  Even if the manufacturer
includes an eyepiece that gives 200x magnification, you&rsquo;ll just see an
unimpressive blur, if you could ever find the object at that
magnification.</p>

<p>Worse, you&rsquo;re also magnifying the speed at which an object in the
telescope appears to move (as the earth turns).  At 30x to 50x this
isn&rsquo;t that much a problem.  At 100x it&rsquo;s moving but you can keep up.
At higher magnifications, unless you have a mounting with a clock
drive, the object goes screaming by.</p>

<p>The basic rule of thumb is 20x to 30x per inch of aperture for normal
observing, and you might double it to get a closer look.  For a
2.4-inch telescope that means 40x to 80x.  Note in the previous post
that the Orion 2.4-inch has eyepieces for 28x and 70x.  That&rsquo;s
perfect!  200x or 400x for a 2.4 is absurd.</p>

<p>For the 4.5-inch telescope, 90x to 180x in theory are good.  It&rsquo;s
eyepieces at 36x and 91x are okay, but you could add an accessory to
take the 91x up to 150x to 200x but I&rsquo;d expect you to use those
magnifications rarely.</p>

<p>Back in the old observatory where we had a 14-inch Celestron
Schmidt-Cassegrain on a permanent pier mounting.  It was an f/11
telescope meaning the focal length was 154-inches (14 x 11) which
equals 3912 mm.  Our typical eyepieces when public observing were a
32-mm and 10-mm.  The 32-mm gave 122x and 24-mm at 162x.
(Magnification is just the telescope focal length divided by the
eyepiece focal length). We might use
a 10-mm or so for 391x, but usually not for the general public.  At
some point, the atmosphere itself limits the detail in the image,
regardless of how large the telescope is.  Astronomers call that
effect the &ldquo;seeing.&rdquo;</p>

<h2>Clock Drives and Tracking</h2>

<p>As discussed above, we&rsquo;re standing on a moving platform, the earth.
For that reason, the whole sky is constantly turning as if we&rsquo;re on a
merry-go-round.  The sun, moon, stars, everything in the sky rises in
the east and sets in the west for this reason. Some telescopes have an
equatorial mounting and a clock drive or computer driven tracking
system to follow the stars across the sky.  If you&rsquo;re just doing
visual observing, and you have a good mounting, you can easily keep
the object you&rsquo;re observing in the field of view.  There&rsquo;s great joy
in visual observing this way.</p>

<p>If you do become interested in some types of visual imaging or more
serious observing of certain types, then you may want to look at a
telescope with a tracking system like this, but I wouldn&rsquo;t start with
one.</p>

<h2>Try Before You Buy</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s a great idea to see what it&rsquo;s like to use a telescope.  Visit
your local planetarium or observatory on an observing night or find a
local astronomy club.  Maybe go to a meeting or two, one where they
offer some presentation or have a speaker on some topic and then,
either at the same meeting or a separate one, where members bring
their telescopes which they&rsquo;ll happily show you along with views of a
variety of objects through them.</p>

<h2>Use the Internet</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve skipped explaining a lot of terms and concepts that surround
amateur astronomy and telescopes.  Excellent explanations are readily
available on the Internet.  Orion has nice tutorials and beginner
guides on their site.  Of course Wikipedia has articles on many topics
surrounding amateur telescopes.  And you&rsquo;ll find other sources.</p>

<p>You should also download the free software for your computer,
<em>Stellarium</em>.  This is a beautiful &ldquo;planetarium program&rdquo; that shows
you the current night sky or the sky from any location, time and date
on earth.  You can use it to learn constellations, what planets are
visible, and every other object in the sky an amateur would be
interested in.  You can also print star maps to take outside.</p>

<p><a href="http://telescope.com/">Orion</a><br />
<a href="http://www.stellarium.org/">Stellarium</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Buying a Telescope - Part 2c]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/05/buying-a-telescope-part-2c/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-05T02:39:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/05/buying-a-telescope-part-2c</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 26</a></p>

<p>Recommendations continued.</p>

<h2>The 2.4-inch Refractor</h2>

<p>I always recommend binoculars as a good way to start observing.
However, if you&rsquo;re a kid who wants a telescope, binoculars might be a
disappointment.  Many astronomers would scoff at the old 2.4-inch
standard but I think this is a fine telescope to start with.  It&rsquo;s the
lowest cost beginner scope and  you can use it to see the beginner
objects.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>My first telescope was a 2.4-inch (60-mm) refractor from Sears with a 700 mm
focal length making it an almost an f/12 focal ratio.  Mine had a
25-mm eyepiece for 28x, a 12.5-mm for 56x (still okay) and an absurd
little 4-mm eyepiece for an unusable 175x.  These were inexpensive
0.965-in &ldquo;toy&rdquo; eyepieces.</p>

<p>Orion has the nicest 2.4-inch (60-mm) I&rsquo;ve seen with serious
accessories and a very reasonable price, $100.</p>

<p>The telescope takes serious, full-sized 1.25-in eyepieces and comes
with the typical 10-mm and 25-mm giving very nice 28x and 70x
magnifications.  It has a solid wood tripod.  If you&rsquo;re on a budget,
this is probably the best bet and I&rsquo;m sure it&rsquo;s better quality and
less expensive than a similar telescope you could walk into a store
down the road and buy.</p>

<p>Be sure to read my post about observing experience, coming soon.</p>

<h2>The Dobsonian 4.5</h2>

<p>I think the Dobsonian is the ideal amateur, visual observing
telescope.  Invented by amateur telescope maker John Dobson, and
achieving hobby-wide popularity around 1980, the Dobsonian changed
everything.  Suddenly, large-aperture amateur telescopes became
affordable.</p>

<p>The Orion SkyQuest XT4.5 Classic 4.5-inch Dobsonian which is, in my
opinion, the perfect beginner telescope.  It&rsquo;s portable, even for
kids, a super-sturday mounting, and has a nice, large aperture that
will allow you to see anything the typical amateur would look for.
Beginner telescopes are usually 2.4 to three or four inches.  This is
4.5!  It has a very nice 6x26 finder scope and two perfect eyepieces,
a 25-mm and 10-mm giving magnifications of 36x and 91x.  The focal
ratio is about f/8 which is classic for a Newtonian reflector like
this.  At the time I&rsquo;m writing this the price is $240 including
standard shipping.</p>

<p>Dobsonians are easy to maneuver, stay where you point them, and
they&rsquo;re just a joy to use.  The only thing this telescope isn&rsquo;t really
ideal for is any type of astrophotography.  There&rsquo;s not a clock drive
so the telescope won&rsquo;t follow the objects in the sky as the earth
rotates.  For visual observing (looking through the telescope) this
isn&rsquo;t a problem.</p>

<p>If I was going to recommended just one telescope, this would be it.</p>

<h2>The 8-inch Schmidt-Cassegrain</h2>

<p>If you have a significant budget and want a telescope that will do it
all but is still portable, I recommend the 8-inch Schmidt-Cassegrain
telescope (SCT).  These telescopes have fine optics, perform well, and
typically make an excellent platform for astro-imaging.  The 8-inch is
still not too heavy so it&rsquo;s still reasonably portable.</p>

<p>I grew up with the Celestron C8 and I have a used one now with the
most-solid, locked-triangle tripod from the 70s and 80s.  I have to
confess that I&rsquo;m not up to date on what the current crop of 8-inch
SCTs are.  Celestron and Meade are the famous names in this arena.
There may be others now.</p>

<p>One nice thing about most of these telescopes is how the the eyepiece
tailpiece is mounted solidly to the back of the telescope.  That means
any camera or equipment you attach will be similarly solid.  The
telescope focuses by moving the whole primary mirror forward and
backward along the baffle tube.  It&rsquo;s a clever design and makes it all
very solid and stable.</p>

<p>These telescopes range in price from $1000 to $2000 roughly, and
probably beyond.</p>

<p><a href="http://telescope.com/">Orion</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
