<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: telescopes | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/telescopes/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2014-11-05T03:45:08-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Buying a Telescope Part 2c]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/05/buying-a-telescope-part-2c/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-05T02:39:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/05/buying-a-telescope-part-2c</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 26</a></p>

<p>Recommendations continued.</p>

<h2>The 2.4-inch Refractor</h2>

<p>I always recommend binoculars as a good way to start observing.
However, if you&rsquo;re a kid who wants a telescope, binoculars might be a
disappointment.  Many astronomers would scoff at the old 2.4-inch
standard but I think this is a fine telescope to start with.  It&rsquo;s the
lowest cost beginner scope and  you can use it to see the beginner
objects.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>My first telescope was a 2.4-inch (60-mm) refractor from Sears with a 700 mm
focal length making it an almost an f/12 focal ratio.  Mine had a
25-mm eyepiece for 28x, a 12.5-mm for 56x (still okay) and an absurd
little 4-mm eyepiece for an unusable 175x.  These were inexpensive
0.965-in &ldquo;toy&rdquo; eyepieces.</p>

<p>Orion has the nicest 2.4-inch (60-mm) I&rsquo;ve seen with serious
accessories and a very reasonable price, $100.</p>

<p>The telescope takes serious, full-sized 1.25-in eyepieces and comes
with the typical 10-mm and 25-mm giving very nice 28x and 70x
magnifications.  It has a solid wood tripod.  If you&rsquo;re on a budget,
this is probably the best bet and I&rsquo;m sure it&rsquo;s better quality and
less expensive than a similar telescope you could walk into a store
down the road and buy.</p>

<p>Be sure to read my post about observing experience, coming soon.</p>

<h2>The Dobsonian 4.5</h2>

<p>I think the Dobsonian is the ideal amateur, visual observing
telescope.  Invented by amateur telescope maker John Dobson, and
achieving hobby-wide popularity around 1980, the Dobsonian changed
everything.  Suddenly, large-aperture amateur telescopes became
affordable.</p>

<p>The Orion SkyQuest XT4.5 Classic 4.5-inch Dobsonian which is, in my
opinion, the perfect beginner telescope.  It&rsquo;s portable, even for
kids, a super-sturday mounting, and has a nice, large aperture that
will allow you to see anything the typical amateur would look for.
Beginner telescopes are usually 2.4 to three or four inches.  This is
4.5!  It has a very nice 6x26 finder scope and two perfect eyepieces,
a 25-mm and 10-mm giving magnifications of 36x and 91x.  The focal
ratio is about f/8 which is classic for a Newtonian reflector like
this.  At the time I&rsquo;m writing this the price is $240 including
standard shipping.</p>

<p>Dobsonians are easy to maneuver, stay where you point them, and
they&rsquo;re just a joy to use.  The only thing this telescope isn&rsquo;t really
ideal for is any type of astrophotography.  There&rsquo;s not a clock drive
so the telescope won&rsquo;t follow the objects in the sky as the earth
rotates.  For visual observing (looking through the telescope) this
isn&rsquo;t a problem.</p>

<p>If I was going to recommended just one telescope, this would be it.</p>

<h2>The 8-inch Schmidt-Cassegrain</h2>

<p>If you have a significant budget and want a telescope that will do it
all but is still portable, I recommend the 8-inch Schmidt-Cassegrain
telescope (SCT).  These telescopes have fine optics, perform well, and
typically make an excellent platform for astro-imaging.  The 8-inch is
still not too heavy so it&rsquo;s still reasonably portable.</p>

<p>I grew up with the Celestron C8 and I have a used one now with the
most-solid, locked-triangle tripod from the 70s and 80s.  I have to
confess that I&rsquo;m not up to date on what the current crop of 8-inch
SCTs are.  Celestron and Meade are the famous names in this arena.
There may be others now.</p>

<p>One nice thing about most of these telescopes is how the the eyepiece
tailpiece is mounted solidly to the back of the telescope.  That means
any camera or equipment you attach will be similarly solid.  The
telescope focuses by moving the whole primary mirror forward and
backward along the baffle tube.  It&rsquo;s a clever design and makes it all
very solid and stable.</p>

<p>These telescopes range in price from $1000 to $2000 roughly, and
probably beyond.</p>

<p><a href="http://telescope.com/">Orion</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
