<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: favorites | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/favorites/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2016-09-23T19:16:32-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[More Short and Medium Length Blogging]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/11/05/more-short-and-medium-length-blogging/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-05T06:34:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/11/05/more-short-and-medium-length-blogging</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Okay, fine, Andy Ihnatko has me spun up again about blogging more with
his disucussion on this week&rsquo;s Macbreak Weekly about blogging more
again and rediscovering MarsEdit  He refers to Jason Snell&rsquo;s Six
Colors, John Gruber&rsquo;s Daring Fireball and Jim Dalrymple&rsquo;s The Loop.
Even Leo said he was doing the same thing on his rejuvenated Leoville.</p>

<p>Okay, I&rsquo;ll try kicking it up a notch, but maybe it&rsquo;s also time to
reflect on my setup with Markdown &ndash; Octopress &ndash; Github pages.</p>

<p><a href="https://twit.tv/shows/macbreak-weekly/episodes/479">Macbreak Weekly #479</a><br />
<a href="http://ihnatko.com/">Andy Ihnatko&rsquo;s Celestial Waste of Bandwidth</a><br />
<a href="https://sixcolors.com/">Six Colors</a><br />
<a href="http://www.loopinsight.com/">The Loop</a><br />
<a href="http://www.leoville.com/">Leoville</a><br />
<a href="http://daringfireball.net/">Daring Fireball</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Blue Moon Definition Was Wrong]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/08/02/blue-moon-definition-was-wrong/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-02T03:14:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/08/02/blue-moon-definition-was-wrong</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This is a blog post I published in Mon 2010-11-22 on the previous
<a href="http://monolith149daily.blogspot.com/2010/11/blue-moon-definition-was-wrong.html">Monolith149 Daily
Site</a>.</em></p>

<p><em>What does this mean?  According to the &ldquo;new incorrect definition&rdquo; the
 blue moon was this past week 31 Jul (based on time zone actually) but
 the next &ldquo;old correct definition&rdquo; blue moon is not actually until 2016-05-21!</em></p>

<p>From a Space.com article by Joe Rao.</p>

<p>I was wrong.  My wife said last night that the moon was a blue moon.
I said, that&rsquo;s not possible because a blue moon is a second full moon
in the same month and that couldn&rsquo;t happen on 21 Nov.  It has to
happen at the very end of a month.  She pointed me at the above
article that explains it.</p>

<p>The short answer is that the two full moons in a month definition is
actually erroneous.</p>

<p>Rao notes that Lawrence J. Lafleur, in <em>Sky and Telescope</em> in 1943,
quotes a 1937 edition of the <em>Maine Farmer&rsquo;s Almanac</em>, stating that a
blue moon is the rare occurance of four full moons in a season instead
of three.  The blue moon is the third moon in that season.</p>

<p>The mistake was apparently made by James Hugh Pruett in a 1946 <em>Sky and
Telescope</em> where he misinterpreted Lafleur&rsquo;s explanation to mean a
second full moon in a single month.  (See the above article for
details).</p>

<p>The wrong explanation was propagated by Deborah Byrd in the radio
program &ldquo;Stardate&rdquo; in 1980 and then the wrong definition, quoting Rao,
&ldquo;went viral.&rdquo;</p>

<p>It all makes me wonder when I first learned of the
two-full-moons-in-a-month definition.  I would have thought it was
long before 1980, but maybe it was after that date.</p>

<p>Well it sort of spoils the whole thing.  Now we&rsquo;ll have to talk about
old-correct-definition blue moons and new-incorrect-definition blue
moons and none of them will seem quite right any more.</p>

<p>This would all be a lot simpler if the moon would just actually turn
blue once in a while.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.space.com/9566-strange-story-sunday-blue-moon.html">The Really Strange Story Behind Sunday&rsquo;s Blue Moon
by Joe Rao, SPACE.com, Skywatching Columnist, 2010-11-19 12:26:00 -0500</a></p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blue_moon">Blue moon from Wikipedia</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Is OS X Yosemite 10.10 is Safe Without Anti Virus?]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/03/20/is-os-x-yosemite-10-dot-10-is-safe-without-anti-virus/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-20T05:11:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/03/20/is-os-x-yosemite-10-dot-10-is-safe-without-anti-virus</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the Apple Support Communities, Linc Davis gives an excellent
answer to this question with a summary of the built-in security
features of OS X 10.10 and the additional precautions you should take.</p>

<blockquote><p>All versions of OS X since 10.6.7 have been able to detect known
Mac malware in downloaded files, and to block insecure web
plugins. This feature is transparent to the user. Internally Apple
calls it &ldquo;XProtect.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>Starting with OS X 10.7.5, there has been a second layer of
built-in malware protection, designated &ldquo;Gatekeeper&rdquo; by Apple. By
default, applications and Installer packages downloaded from the
network will only run if they&rsquo;re digitally signed by a developer with
a certificate issued by Apple. Software certified in this way hasn&rsquo;t
necessarily been tested by Apple, but you can be reasonably sure that
it hasn&rsquo;t been modified by anyone other than the developer. His
identity is known to Apple, so he could be held legally responsible if
he distributed malware. That may not mean much if the developer lives
in a country with a weak legal system (see below.)</p></blockquote>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>Starting with OS X 10.8.3, a third layer of protection has been
added: a &ldquo;Malware Removal Tool&rdquo; (MRT). MRT runs automatically in the
background when you update the OS. It checks for, and removes, malware
that may have evaded the other protections via a Java exploit (see
below.) MRT also runs when you install or update the Apple-supplied
Java runtime (but not the Oracle runtime.) Like XProtect, MRT is
effective against known threats, but not against unknown ones. It
notifies you if it finds malware, but otherwise there&rsquo;s no user
interface to MRT.</p></blockquote>

<p>His answer is the third one down.</p>

<p><a href="https://discussions.apple.com/thread/6624843">Is OS X Yosemite 10.10 is safe without anti virus?</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Buying a Telescope]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/12/10/buying-a-telescope/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-10T08:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/12/10/buying-a-telescope</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In November, during the 30-day blog challenge, I wrote a series of
posts on buying a telescope.  With slight editing, I&rsquo;ve combined them
into a single document which also has a link in the menu up top.</p>

<p><a href="http://10.0.0.23/m149daily-blog/telescope/">Buying a Telescope</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dark and Stormy]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/18/dark-and-stormy/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-18T07:09:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/18/dark-and-stormy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>While looking for earlier posts about kids and programming, I came
across this from a 2005-02-08 post.  Someone sent this to me and I
don&rsquo;t know if it&rsquo;s real or not.  In any event, I enjoyed these.</em></p>

<hr />

<p>These came from the annual &ldquo;Dark and Stormy Night&rdquo; competition. Actual
analogies and metaphors found in high school essays:</p>

<ol>
<li>Her face was a perfect oval, like a circle that had its two sides
gently compressed by a Thigh Master.</li>
</ol>


<!-- More -->


<ol>
<li><p>His thoughts tumbled in his head, making and breaking alliances
like underpants in a dryer without Cling Free.</p></li>
<li><p>He spoke with the wisdom that can only come from experience, like a
guy who went blind because he looked at a solar eclipse without one of
those boxes with a pinhole in it and now goes around the country
speaking at high schools about the dangers of looking at a solar
eclipse without one of those boxes with a pinhole in it.</p></li>
<li><p>She grew on him like she was a colony of E. coli and he was
room-temperature Canadian beef.</p></li>
<li><p>She had a deep, throaty, genuine laugh, like that sound a dog makes
just before it throws up.</p></li>
<li><p>Her vocabulary was as bad as, like, whatever.</p></li>
<li><p>He was as tall as a six-foot-three-inch tree.</p></li>
<li><p>The revelation that his marriage of 30 years had disintegrated
because of his wife&rsquo;s infidelity came as a rude shock, like a
surcharge at a formerly surcharge-free ATM.</p></li>
<li><p>The little boat gently drifted across the pond exactly the way a
bowling
ball wouldn&rsquo;t.</p></li>
<li><p>McBride fell 12 stories, hitting the pavement like a Hefty bag
filled with vegetable soup.</p></li>
<li><p>From the attic came an unearthly howl. The whole scene had an
eerie, surreal quality, like when you&rsquo;re on vacation in another city
and Jeopardy comes on at 7:00 p.m. instead of 7:30.</p></li>
<li><p>Her hair glistened in the rain like a nose hair after a sneeze.</p></li>
<li><p>The hailstones leaped from the pavement, just like maggots when
you fry them in hot grease.</p></li>
<li><p>Long separated by cruel fate, the star-crossed lovers raced across
the grassy field toward each other like two freight trains, one having
left Cleveland at 6:36 p.m. traveling at 55 mph, the other from Topeka
at 4:19 p.m. at a speed of 35 mph.</p></li>
<li><p>They lived in a typical suburban neighborhood with picket fences
that resembled Nancy Kerrigan&rsquo;s teeth.</p></li>
<li><p>John and Mary had never met. They were like two hummingbirds who
had also never met.</p></li>
<li><p>He fell for her like his heart was a mob informant and she was the
East River.</p></li>
<li><p>Even in his last years, Grandpappy had a mind like a steel trap,
only one that had been left out so long, it had rusted shut.</p></li>
<li><p>Shots rang out, as shots are wont to do.</p></li>
<li><p>The plan was simple, like my brother-in-law Phil. But unlike Phil,
this plan just might work.</p></li>
<li><p>The young fighter had a hungry look, the kind you get from not
eating for a while.</p></li>
<li><p>He was as lame as a duck. Not the metaphorical lame duck, either,
but a real duck that was actually lame, maybe from stepping on a land
mine or something.</p></li>
<li><p>The ballerina rose gracefully en pointe and extended one slender
leg behind her, like a dog at a fire hydrant.</p></li>
<li><p>It was an American tradition, like fathers chasing kids around
with power tools.</p></li>
<li><p>He was deeply in love. When she spoke, he thought he heard bells,
as if she were a garbage truck backing up.</p></li>
<li><p>Her eyes were like limpid pools, only they had forgotten to put in
any pH cleanser.</p></li>
<li><p>She walked into my office like a centipede with 98 missing legs.</p></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
