<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: favorites | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/favorites/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2017-08-17T06:37:19-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What's going on inside Lithium Ion Batteries?]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/23/whats-going-on-inside-lithium-ion-batteries/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-23T07:32:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/23/whats-going-on-inside-lithium-ion-batteries</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Steve Gibson from Security Now provided two excellent sources this
week explaining what&rsquo;s happening when lithium ion batteries fail.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>From Paul O’Shea, Editor, <em>Power Electronics News</em> interviewing Nadim
Maluf, CEO of Qnovo, and Robert Nalesnik, VP of Marketing for Qnovo.</p>

<blockquote><p>Now, let’s examine one particular manufacturing defect in which a
slight misalignment between the anode and cathode occurs during the
assembly process. The same structure as above now has the anode layer
shifted slightly to the right. At the misaligned edge, the requisite
overlap of the anode relative to the cathode is now diminished or even
possibly eliminated. The anode/cathode ratio at this spot drops below
the requisite limit for ensuring safety. The result is the onset of
lithium metal at this edge. The lithium metal forms on the anode
edge. As the lithium metal grows in size and thickness, it ultimately
punctures the separator and causes an electrical short between the
anode and cathode. Boom! There is a catastrophic failure.</p>

<p>The tolerance requirements in the manufacturing of lithium-ion
batteries have risen sharply with increasing energy density. Short of
using new materials (which still do not exist in commercial
deployment), increasing the energy density means reducing all the
extra space inside the battery that is not made of anode and cathode
materials. These are the only two materials that store energy;
n> everything else is just overhead. They are still needed for other
functions and safety, but they do not contribute to storing electrical
charge. Therefore, battery designers keep reducing this overhead and,
in the process, make the manufacturing tolerances even tighter. That
is a recipe for many disasters to come unless we start adding a lot
more intelligence to the battery to avoid and mitigate these
undesired situations.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.powerelectronicsnews.com/technology/pushing-to-the-very-edge-of-safe-li-ion-charging">Pushing to the very edge of safe Li-ion charging</a><br /></p>

<p>From the Qnovo blog.</p>

<p><a href="http://qnovo.com/104-perils-4-4-volts/">104. The Perils of 4.4 Volts</a><br />
<a href="http://qnovo.com/103-real-science-behind-exploding-batteries/">103. The Real Science Behind Battery Safety</a><br />
<a href="http://qnovo.com/102-easy-not-right-pick-samsung/">102. It’s Easy, but Not Right, to Pick on Samsung</a><br />
<a href="http://qnovo.com/101-making-sense-100-kwh/">101. Making Sense of 100 kWh</a><br />
<a href="http://qnovo.com/100-state-lithium-ion-battery/">100. The State of the Lithium Ion Battery</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The C Programming Language]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/04/the-c-programming-language/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-04T01:15:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/04/the-c-programming-language</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The classic &ldquo;The C Programming Language&rdquo; by Kernighan and Ritchie is
online in full at the below link.  This is the second edition from
1988.</p>

<p><a href="https://hassanolity.files.wordpress.com/2013/11/the_c_programming_language_2.pdf">The C Programming Language</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Squeak - Back to the Future]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/26/squeak-back-to-the-future/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-26T06:45:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/26/squeak-back-to-the-future</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I still love Squeak Smalltalk.  A pointer to this paper was posted on
Hacker News Today.</p>

<p>Back to the Future<br />
The Story of Squeak, A Practical Smalltalk Written in Itself</p>

<p>by</p>

<p>Dan Ingalls, Ted Kaehler, John Maloney, Scott Wallace, Alan Kay</p>

<p><a href="http://ftp.squeak.org/docs/OOPSLA.Squeak.html">Back to the Future</a></p>

<p><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=12577087">Hacker News posting</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ducking Into a Nearby Phone Booth]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/01/23/ducking-into-a-nearby-phone-booth/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-23T14:31:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/01/23/ducking-into-a-nearby-phone-booth</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was recently wondering about the origin of Superman finding a phone
booth to change in.  I found one source on the origin and it was
surprising.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>Why was I wondering about this in the first place?  It&rsquo;s because I was
thinking about the John Williams soundtrack from the 1978 movie.  I
recalled the scene where Clark Kent stops and glances at the little hood-like
phone booth and keeps going, looking for a place to change.  I
wondered where the changing in a phone booth meme came from since I
didn&rsquo;t recall Superman ever actually changing in a phone booth in any
of the comics or TV shows, etc.</p>

<p>A quick search online pulled up some interesting history including a
post by Steve Younis on supermanhoempage.com called &lsquo;Superman and the
Phone Booth."</p>

<blockquote><p>In the Golden Age of comic books Clark Kent didn&rsquo;t use a phone booth
to change into Superman. Actually right throughout every era of
Superman comics the phone booth change has rarely been seen.</p></blockquote>

<p>The first time Superman changes is (spoiler):</p>

<blockquote><p>The answer lies way back in 1941.</p>

<p>To my knowledge, Clark Kent first changed to Superman inside a phone
booth in &ldquo;The Mechanical Monsters&rdquo;, the second of 17 Superman
cartoons produced by Fleischer Studios for Paramount Pictures. It
was released to cinemas on November 28 in 1941.</p></blockquote>

<p>I was pretty much unaware of the Fleischer Studios Superman
animations.  They&rsquo;re very well done and influenced some of the more
recent TV animations in style.</p>

<p>I recommend finding &ldquo;The Mechanical Monsters&rdquo; on Youtube and watching it.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.supermanhomepage.com/other/other.php?topic=phonebooth">Superman and the Phone Booth</a>
<a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Superman_(1940s_cartoons">Superman 1940s cartoons</a>)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[More Short and Medium Length Blogging]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/11/05/more-short-and-medium-length-blogging/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-05T06:34:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/11/05/more-short-and-medium-length-blogging</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Okay, fine, Andy Ihnatko has me spun up again about blogging more with
his disucussion on this week&rsquo;s Macbreak Weekly about blogging more
again and rediscovering MarsEdit  He refers to Jason Snell&rsquo;s Six
Colors, John Gruber&rsquo;s Daring Fireball and Jim Dalrymple&rsquo;s The Loop.
Even Leo said he was doing the same thing on his rejuvenated Leoville.</p>

<p>Okay, I&rsquo;ll try kicking it up a notch, but maybe it&rsquo;s also time to
reflect on my setup with Markdown &ndash; Octopress &ndash; Github pages.</p>

<p><a href="https://twit.tv/shows/macbreak-weekly/episodes/479">Macbreak Weekly #479</a><br />
<a href="http://ihnatko.com/">Andy Ihnatko&rsquo;s Celestial Waste of Bandwidth</a><br />
<a href="https://sixcolors.com/">Six Colors</a><br />
<a href="http://www.loopinsight.com/">The Loop</a><br />
<a href="http://www.leoville.com/">Leoville</a><br />
<a href="http://daringfireball.net/">Daring Fireball</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
