<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: security | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/security/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2015-10-02T02:47:08-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Is OS X Yosemite 10.10 is Safe Without Anti Virus?]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/03/20/is-os-x-yosemite-10-dot-10-is-safe-without-anti-virus/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-20T05:11:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/03/20/is-os-x-yosemite-10-dot-10-is-safe-without-anti-virus</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the Apple Support Communities, Linc Davis gives an excellent
answer to this question with a summary of the built-in security
features of OS X 10.10 and the additional precautions you should take.</p>

<blockquote><p>All versions of OS X since 10.6.7 have been able to detect known
Mac malware in downloaded files, and to block insecure web
plugins. This feature is transparent to the user. Internally Apple
calls it &ldquo;XProtect.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>Starting with OS X 10.7.5, there has been a second layer of
built-in malware protection, designated &ldquo;Gatekeeper&rdquo; by Apple. By
default, applications and Installer packages downloaded from the
network will only run if they&rsquo;re digitally signed by a developer with
a certificate issued by Apple. Software certified in this way hasn&rsquo;t
necessarily been tested by Apple, but you can be reasonably sure that
it hasn&rsquo;t been modified by anyone other than the developer. His
identity is known to Apple, so he could be held legally responsible if
he distributed malware. That may not mean much if the developer lives
in a country with a weak legal system (see below.)</p></blockquote>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>Starting with OS X 10.8.3, a third layer of protection has been
added: a &ldquo;Malware Removal Tool&rdquo; (MRT). MRT runs automatically in the
background when you update the OS. It checks for, and removes, malware
that may have evaded the other protections via a Java exploit (see
below.) MRT also runs when you install or update the Apple-supplied
Java runtime (but not the Oracle runtime.) Like XProtect, MRT is
effective against known threats, but not against unknown ones. It
notifies you if it finds malware, but otherwise there&rsquo;s no user
interface to MRT.</p></blockquote>

<p>His answer is the third one down.</p>

<p><a href="https://discussions.apple.com/thread/6624843">Is OS X Yosemite 10.10 is safe without anti virus?</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SQRL!]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/31/sqrl/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-31T05:11:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/31/sqrl</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 21</a></p>

<p>For several months now Steve Gibson of GRC.com and Security Now has
been working on a new authentication protocol he named SQRL, the
Secure Quick Reliable Login.  On his web site he describes what
happens when you log into a site, say Amazon, using SQRL (assuming
Amazon adopted it).</p>

<p>The website displays a QR code, described as a &ldquo;SQRL code,&rdquo; beside the
usual userid and password login prompt.</p>

<blockquote><ul>
<li>The user can tap or click directly on the SQRL code to login, or
launch their smartphone&rsquo;s SQRL app, and scan the QR code.</li>
<li>For verification, SQRL displays the domain name contained in the
SQRL code.</li>
<li>After verifying the domain, the user permits the SQRL app to
authenticate their identity.</li>
<li>Leaving the login information blank, the user clicks the “Log in”
button&hellip; and is logged in.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>The approach is highly secure, difficult to attack, easy to implement,
and easy to use.  He describes details at his site.</p>

<p>This is an elegant solution to the problems that come from dealing
with passwords and I hope it continues to climb since it&rsquo;s taken off!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.grc.com/sqrl/sqrl.htm">SQRL at GRC.com</a><br />
<a href="http://twit.tv/show/security-now">Security Now</a><br />
<a href="http://twit.tv/show/security-now/424">Episode 424 on SQRL</a><br />
<a href="http://sqrl.pl/guide/">Sqrl.pl Illustrated Guide</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Google Authenticator for SSH Two-Factor Authentication]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/06/06/google-authenticator-for-ssh-two-factor-authentication/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-06T23:20:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/06/06/google-authenticator-for-ssh-two-factor-authentication</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/Google-Authenticator.png"></p>

<p><a href="http://scottlinux.com/2013/06/02/use-google-authenticator-for-two-factor-ssh-authentication-in-linux/">Use Google Authenticator For Two-Factor SSH Authentication in
Linux</a> at scottlinux.com.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
