<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: security | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/security/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2017-08-17T06:37:19-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Danger: Effective Gmail Phishing]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2017/01/16/danger-effective-gmail-phishing/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-16T22:07:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2017/01/16/danger-effective-gmail-phishing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&ldquo;Wide Impact: Highly Effective Gmail Phishing Technique Being Exploited
by Mark Maunder&rdquo;</p>

<p>This is pretty insidious.  You get a message from someome you know.
It has an attachment.  You try to open it but up pops a Gmail login
page asking you to enter your password again for security.  That Gmail
login page is fake and your password is stolen as soon as you type it
in.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.wordfence.com/blog/2017/01/gmail-phishing-data-uri/">Effective Gmail Phishing</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The IOT Answer is the Hub]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/15/the-iot-answer-is-the-hub/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-15T00:11:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/15/the-iot-answer-is-the-hub</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Steve Gibson said this on a recent episode of <em>Security Now</em>.  He
says, the solution to the IOT security problem is the hub.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>He goes on to point out that all IOT (Internet of things) devices
should connect to a single device in your home that responsibly
handles the communications and security.</p>

<p>Recently, poorly secured, home IOT devices have been credited with
being the medium for massive scale denial of service (DOS) attacks
against well-known web sites.  The flood of cheap and inexpensive
devices like home cameras, wifi-enabled light bulbs, into homes with
very fast outbound network connections have enabled a huge force that
can be used that want to engage in digital vandalism to those who want
to bring a site under a full attack.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.grc.com/securitynow.htm">Security Now at GRC.com</a><br />
<a href="https://twit.tv/shows/security-now">Security Now at twit.tv</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DOS IOT Botnet Attack]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/01/dos-iot-botnet-attack/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-01T00:22:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/01/dos-iot-botnet-attack</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There&rsquo;s been a lot of discussion about the insecurity of the internet
of things (IOT) devices such as security cameras, DVRs, thermostats
and more.  Frankly, many of these are Linux systems that are poorly
prepared from a security standpoint and sometimes blatantly exposed.
Such devices were used in the recent, massive attacks against the DNS
service.</p>

<!-- More -->


<blockquote><p>&ldquo;We&rsquo;re seeing attacks coming from a number of different locations,&rdquo;
Drew said. &ldquo;An Internet of Things botnet called Mirai that we
identified is also involved in the attack.&rdquo;</p>

<p>The botnet, made up of devices like home Wi-Fi routers and Internet
protocol video cameras, is sending massive numbers of requests to
Dyn&rsquo;s DNS service. Those requests look legitimate, so it&rsquo;s difficult
for Dyn&rsquo;s systems to screen them out from normal domain name lookup
requests.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://arstechnica.com/security/2016/10/double-dip-internet-of-things-botnet-attack-felt-across-the-internet/">Double-dip Internet-of-Things botnet attack felt across the Internet</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rowhammer]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/01/rowhammer/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-01T00:18:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/01/rowhammer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Rowhammer is a sophisticated, clever and dangerous way to attack
computers and Android phones.  Dan Goodin reports in <em>Ars Technica.</em></p>

<!-- More -->


<blockquote><p>Researchers have devised an attack that gains unfettered &ldquo;root&rdquo; access
to a large number of Android phones, exploiting a relatively new type
of bug that allows adversaries to manipulate data stored in memory
chips.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://arstechnica.com/security/2016/10/using-rowhammer-bitflips-to-root-android-phones-is-now-a-thing/">Using Rowhammer bitflips to root Android phones is now a thing</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Email Phishing Attack]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/01/email-phishing-attack/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-01T00:10:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/01/email-phishing-attack</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well, in my earlier post on security tips I mentioned links in email.
According to an article in <em>Business Insider</em>, that&rsquo;s exactly how John
Podesta&rsquo;s account was compromised.</p>

<!-- More -->


<blockquote><p>Simply put: Rather than clicking a legitimate link from Google, he
apparently clicked through to a fake website run by hackers. When he
entered his account information, he handed over the keys to his
Gmail.</p></blockquote>

<p>This article by Ben Gilbert goes into some detail about how this was
done.  It was an easy effort by the attacker and could have been
avoided with a bit more care on the part of the user.  He even did the
right thing in reporting it to his IT support but still clicked the
dangerous link in the email.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/hillary-clinton-campaign-john-podesta-got-hacked-by-phishing-2016-10">Hillary Clinton&rsquo;s campaign got hacked by falling for the oldest trick
in the book</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
