<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: security | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/security/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2016-10-17T23:46:42-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Security Basics]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/16/security-tips/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-16T15:40:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/16/security-tips</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The information world is a dangerous place these days.  You can lose
everything in an instant.  There&rsquo;s more at stake.  The biggest one is
probably your personal and family pictures.  The next is personal
financial and other important information, documents, etc.  I don&rsquo;t
know if it&rsquo;s any more dangerous but more of us have more important
information stored on our computers and other devices.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s my own list of the basics.  There&rsquo;s nothing original here.  You
should hear about the same thing from any security or IT professional.</p>

<!-- More -->


<h2>Summary</h2>

<ul>
<li>Don&rsquo;t open links and attachments in email, messages</li>
<li>Keep systems and apps, everything, updated</li>
<li>Keep Internet browsing on Main Street</li>
<li>Make backups, 3, 2, 1 (three copies, two media, one off site)</li>
<li>Use Google Chrome</li>
<li>Use Gmail</li>
<li>Use a password manager like LastPass or 1Password</li>
<li>Never install something you weren&rsquo;t looking for</li>
</ul>


<h2>The Basics</h2>

<h3>Don&rsquo;t open links and attachments in email, messages</h3>

<p>This is one of the biggest threats today.  You click a link and
download an attachment and you&rsquo;ve given malware, an attacking computer
program, access to <em>your</em> computer.  Fortunately most of our systems
today are secure enough that they can&rsquo;t be compromised unless you take
the action yourself so the game is to trick you into running the
evil code.  Sending you email that looks like a legitimate, important
message from your bank or the IRS, or maybe telling you you&rsquo;ve won
something or have an important message, maybe an unpaid bill.</p>

<p>If the message is from a bank or some institution or business, see if
you can get to the same information by going to their web site on your
own, not by clicking in the email, and finding what they&rsquo;re talking
about.  If nothing else, call them.</p>

<p>If it&rsquo;s from a family member, text them or call them and ask if they
sent it to you and if they&rsquo;re sure it&rsquo;s okay.</p>

<p>Many of the largest company security breaches in recent news have been
the result of finally tricking an employee to click on something in an
email message.</p>

<h3>Keep systems and apps, everything, updated</h3>

<p>All software and, in fact, most hardware, is updated regularly.  These
updates are important.  Many people are working hard to find and fix
bugs that could expose you to attack.   On Windows, Mac OS, and Linux,
you should turn on automatic updates so your system is updated on a
regular basis.</p>

<h3>Keep Internet browsing on Main Street</h3>

<p>This means stick to well known and reputable sites: people,
businesses, destinations.  Don&rsquo;t go down the side streets of the
Internet and definitely don&rsquo;t stray into any dark alleys.  As in real
life, it only leads to trouble.</p>

<h2>Make backups, 3, 2, 1</h2>

<p>That means three copies, two media, one off site.  This may be the
second most important thing you can do, maybe the first.  First, this
is just basic data stewardship.  It&rsquo;s gives you the best chance of not
losing it all.  However, with the recent, dramatic rise in ransom
ware, backups are even more important.  Ransom ware gets into your
computer (e.g., by getting you to click a link in email) and encrypts
all of your files.  Then you have to pay a web site anywhere from $100
to $1000 for a key to unlock your files.  There&rsquo;s no other way to get
them back.  However, if you have a recent enough backup then you can
ignore the ransom ware attackers, wipe your computer clean and
restore your files.</p>

<p>Here is the simplest way to do this.  Buy a second, external USB hard
drive which should cost from $60 to $90, attach it to your computer
and use a program that backs up your files to it nightly.  Then
subscribe to a service like Carbonite or Back Blaze. They both charge
about $5 per month.</p>

<h2>Use Google Chrome</h2>

<p>As Internet browsers go, Chrome is the most secure.  This is proven
often and Chrome was the clear winner at this year&rsquo;s annual &ldquo;Pwn to
own&rdquo;
security contest, as it usually is.  Chrome isn&rsquo;t perfect but it will
help keep you safe.</p>

<h2>Use Gmail</h2>

<p>Gmail is the best email period and it&rsquo;s also very safe and will work
hard to help keep you secure.  It&rsquo;s also not perfect, though, so you
still have to follow all of the other guidelines here.  I&rsquo;ve used
Gmail since it came out in 2004, that&rsquo;s 12 years, and it&rsquo;s sad when I
hear people talk about email problems and issues that I haven&rsquo;t even
thought about for those 12 years.</p>

<h2>Use a password manager</h2>

<p>Maybe the two biggest are LastPass and 1Password.  I personally prefer
LastPass but pretty much everything I say here about LastPass applies
to 1Password as well.  You put all of your passwords into LastPass for
everything you use.  If you install it into your browser, it will log
into sites for you automatically.  Make sure every site has a
<em>different</em> and <em>long</em> password, at least 25 characters, usually with
a mixture of upper case, lower case, numerals, and other special
characters.  Lastpass will make up new passwords for you.  Remember,
you won&rsquo;t be typing in these passwords.  Lastpass will do that for
you.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a good practice to use a different user name for each site and it
can also be a random jumble of letters.  Similarly, if you have to
answer security questions for the site, use a jumble of letters for
that.  In other words, don&rsquo;t put your mother&rsquo;s maiden name as &ldquo;Smith&rdquo;
but enter it as &ldquo;GAStiOnOgyRiVEnDETorpoyaL&rdquo;.  Use different answers
for every site.  Put them in the Notes section of that account on
LastPass.</p>

<p>There is one important thing:  Lastpass (and 1Password) uses a master
password to unlock access by you to the rest of your passwords.  You
should make the master password easy to remember and key in, but also
be absolutely sure to write it down and store it in a non-obvious,
very safe place.</p>

<h2>Never install something you weren&rsquo;t looking for</h2>

<p>This is a rule from Steve Gibson of GRC.com and Security Now.  If you
get a pop up message on your computer that says it&rsquo;s time to install
an update or something else, don&rsquo;t do it.  It could be fine, but don&rsquo;t
take the chance.  This is what we mean by &ldquo;something you weren&rsquo;t
looking for.&rdquo;   Instead of clicking on the popup, go to the actual
application or go to the web site and see if you can find whatever the
popup was talking about there.  Maybe go to your system&rsquo;s app store
and see if there are pending updates there.</p>

<h2>What about virus software?</h2>

<p>Did you notice I didn&rsquo;t mention virus software or anything to remove
adware or malware.  Those days are pretty much over.  The types of
attacks and the real problems usually aren&rsquo;t viruses any more.  If you
have Windows, turn on Microsoft&rsquo;s own, built in virus scanning.  It&rsquo;s
sufficient and free.  You definitely don&rsquo;t need anything scanning your
email or web connections, especially if you use Chrome and Gmail.</p>

<p>I do use ad blocking software, Ghostery on the desktop.  I&rsquo;m not
qualified to recommend which ad blocking software is best right now.
Anyway, ad blocking is more about avoiding browsing nuisances of ads
covering a web page you&rsquo;re trying to read and are not so much a
security matter.</p>

<h2>Next</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ll soon follow up with part 2, Bonus Tips.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Block Chain for Authentication]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/01/08/block-chain-for-authentication/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-08T21:39:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/01/08/block-chain-for-authentication</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The latest rage is all about the block chain, made popular by Bitcoin.
It&rsquo;s not exactly authentication but more publication of data in a
sense that it becomes part of a sequential public record.  From that
point on, it can be looked up and verified.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>The clever part is that the public record isn&rsquo;t posted in a particular
place or location but is distributed all over, approximately to
everyone who cares.  Since everyone has a copy, they can be verified
against each other.</p>

<p>As pointed out in the article below, it&rsquo;s like publishing a snippet
about a transaction in a newspaper which is then sent out to all
subscribers.  In this case, though, the newspaper contains all of the
transactions ever published there and just keeps adding to them.  You
can see one of the first problems right there.  This growing &ldquo;ledger&rdquo;
just keeps, well, growing.  It doesn&rsquo;t seem to scale well as they say.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.wired.co.uk/news/archive/2016-01/05/blockchain-is-the-new-signature">How the blockchain will enable self-service government</a> by Brian Forde and Michael Casey of Wired UK.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Is OS X Yosemite 10.10 is Safe Without Anti Virus?]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/03/20/is-os-x-yosemite-10-dot-10-is-safe-without-anti-virus/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-20T05:11:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/03/20/is-os-x-yosemite-10-dot-10-is-safe-without-anti-virus</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the Apple Support Communities, Linc Davis gives an excellent
answer to this question with a summary of the built-in security
features of OS X 10.10 and the additional precautions you should take.</p>

<blockquote><p>All versions of OS X since 10.6.7 have been able to detect known
Mac malware in downloaded files, and to block insecure web
plugins. This feature is transparent to the user. Internally Apple
calls it &ldquo;XProtect.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>Starting with OS X 10.7.5, there has been a second layer of
built-in malware protection, designated &ldquo;Gatekeeper&rdquo; by Apple. By
default, applications and Installer packages downloaded from the
network will only run if they&rsquo;re digitally signed by a developer with
a certificate issued by Apple. Software certified in this way hasn&rsquo;t
necessarily been tested by Apple, but you can be reasonably sure that
it hasn&rsquo;t been modified by anyone other than the developer. His
identity is known to Apple, so he could be held legally responsible if
he distributed malware. That may not mean much if the developer lives
in a country with a weak legal system (see below.)</p></blockquote>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>Starting with OS X 10.8.3, a third layer of protection has been
added: a &ldquo;Malware Removal Tool&rdquo; (MRT). MRT runs automatically in the
background when you update the OS. It checks for, and removes, malware
that may have evaded the other protections via a Java exploit (see
below.) MRT also runs when you install or update the Apple-supplied
Java runtime (but not the Oracle runtime.) Like XProtect, MRT is
effective against known threats, but not against unknown ones. It
notifies you if it finds malware, but otherwise there&rsquo;s no user
interface to MRT.</p></blockquote>

<p>His answer is the third one down.</p>

<p><a href="https://discussions.apple.com/thread/6624843">Is OS X Yosemite 10.10 is safe without anti virus?</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SQRL!]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/31/sqrl/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-31T05:11:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/31/sqrl</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 21</a></p>

<p>For several months now Steve Gibson of GRC.com and Security Now has
been working on a new authentication protocol he named SQRL, the
Secure Quick Reliable Login.  On his web site he describes what
happens when you log into a site, say Amazon, using SQRL (assuming
Amazon adopted it).</p>

<p>The website displays a QR code, described as a &ldquo;SQRL code,&rdquo; beside the
usual userid and password login prompt.</p>

<blockquote><ul>
<li>The user can tap or click directly on the SQRL code to login, or
launch their smartphone&rsquo;s SQRL app, and scan the QR code.</li>
<li>For verification, SQRL displays the domain name contained in the
SQRL code.</li>
<li>After verifying the domain, the user permits the SQRL app to
authenticate their identity.</li>
<li>Leaving the login information blank, the user clicks the “Log in”
button&hellip; and is logged in.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>The approach is highly secure, difficult to attack, easy to implement,
and easy to use.  He describes details at his site.</p>

<p>This is an elegant solution to the problems that come from dealing
with passwords and I hope it continues to climb since it&rsquo;s taken off!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.grc.com/sqrl/sqrl.htm">SQRL at GRC.com</a><br />
<a href="http://twit.tv/show/security-now">Security Now</a><br />
<a href="http://twit.tv/show/security-now/424">Episode 424 on SQRL</a><br />
<a href="http://sqrl.pl/guide/">Sqrl.pl Illustrated Guide</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Google Authenticator for SSH Two-Factor Authentication]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/06/06/google-authenticator-for-ssh-two-factor-authentication/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-06T23:20:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/06/06/google-authenticator-for-ssh-two-factor-authentication</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/Google-Authenticator.png"></p>

<p><a href="http://scottlinux.com/2013/06/02/use-google-authenticator-for-two-factor-ssh-authentication-in-linux/">Use Google Authenticator For Two-Factor SSH Authentication in
Linux</a> at scottlinux.com.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
