<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: observing | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/observing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2017-08-17T06:37:19-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Super Moon -  Super Story]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/15/super-moon-super-story/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-15T06:01:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/15/super-moon-super-story</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/Moon-Earth_distance,_Moon_phases.gif"></p>

<p>The hyped story about the &ldquo;Super Moon&rdquo; is near the top of our on-line
news feeds.  I&rsquo;ll try to untangle the hype from some facts.  It&rsquo;s true
that this <em>full Moon</em> will be the closest since 1948-01-26.</p>

<p>The next closest super Moon will be in 2034, only four years before
our UNIX calendars run out of steam.</p>

<p>But how big a deal is this?  And what&rsquo;s really going on?</p>

<!-- More -->


<h2>Short version</h2>

<p>If you don&rsquo;t want to dive into the details below, here&rsquo;s the long
story short.  Every month the Moon is closer and farther from the
Earth as it follows its elliptical orbit.  Due to the tidal force from
the Sun, sometimes those distances are a little more extreme than
others.</p>

<p>The so-called  &ldquo;Super Moon&rdquo; occurs when the full Moon coincides very
closely with the Moon&rsquo;s closest approach, apogee, to the Earth for the
year.  But it&rsquo;s really only around 3% larger than any other close
approach during the year, and these happen every year.  They just
don&rsquo;t always occur when the Moon is almost exactly full.</p>

<h2>Kepler&rsquo;s first law</h2>

<p>Kepler&rsquo;s first law is that orbits have the shape of an ellipse with
the primary body at one of the two foci.  In this case the Earth is at
the focus.  The ellipse means the Moon moves closer to and farther
away from the Earth as it goes around.  It&rsquo;s closest point is called
the perigee, and the farthest point is the apogee.</p>

<h2>Sun&rsquo;s tidal forces</h2>

<p>Tidal forces stretch things.  The tidal force due to the Sun&rsquo;s and
Moon&rsquo;s gravity stretch the Earth&rsquo;s oceans so they have high points and
low points.  The tidal force of the Sun also stretches the Moon&rsquo;s
orbit.  When the Sun is in the direction of the long ellipse, the Sun
stretches it in a longer ellipse.  The extreme distances are even more
extreme:</p>

<p>apogee = 406,700 km, perigee = 356,400 km.</p>

<p>When the Sun is at right angles to the major axis, the orbit is pulled
into a less eccentric ellipse and the extremes are reduced.</p>

<p>apogee = 404,000 km, perigee = 370,400 km.</p>

<h2>Monthly motions</h2>

<p>Every month the Moon passes apogee and perigee as it orbits the
Earth.  In the excellent diagram above from the Wikipedia article on
the &ldquo;Orbit of the Moon,&rdquo; you can see the varying distance of the
Moon from the Earth plotted.  The minimum points are the perigee,
closest, distance.  Each month, when the Moon is at perigee, it will appear
a bit larger, than when it&rsquo;s farther away.</p>

<p>Notice how the minimum and maximum distances are not as extreme in
April as they are in August.  That&rsquo;s the Sun&rsquo;s tidal effect.</p>

<p>In this diagram, which was for 2014, it looks like the Moon was closest
to the Earth in about the second week of August at perigee.</p>

<h2>Moon phases</h2>

<p>The other thing in this diagram is the phase of the Moon.  The
diagonal lines show the Moon going from new (phase = 0) to full (phase
= 0.5) and back to new each month.  The vertical lines show when the
new Moons occur.</p>

<p>What we&rsquo;re really interested in here is the <em>full Moon</em> so it would
have been nice if there were vertical lines halfway in between the new
Moons to mark the phase = 0.5 full Moons.</p>

<h2>The big deal</h2>

<p>So now we have all the pieces to understand what the big deal is.
It&rsquo;s this.  How close does the full Moon come to the closest perigee
of the year?  Well, it almost never hits it perfectly, but it varies
from year to year.  In the year in the diagram, it looks like the
halfway full-Moon point would fall nearly on the mid-August closest
perigee.</p>

<p>Using the perigee-apogee calculator from below for 2014 we find the
full Moon hit the closest perigee on 2014-08-10 almost exactly, zero
hours difference!  The perigee distance was 356,896 km.</p>

<p>In contrast, this year they missed by about 2 hours on 2016-11-14 at a
distance of 356,511 km.  So the full Moon was off a bit, but the
closest perigee this year was a bit closer.  Why a bit closer?  It has
to do with the angle of the Sun to the ellipse of the Moon&rsquo;s orbit.</p>

<h2>But it isn&rsquo;t really</h2>

<p>So that timing of full Moon and closest perigee of the year is what
it&rsquo;s all about.  But notice that the Moon gets this close every year!
It&rsquo;s just not necessarily at, or exactly at, the time of the full
Moon.  Further, the Moon gets almost that close every month!</p>

<p>As we said above, the closet perigee distance is 356,400 km while the
farthest perigee is 370,400.  That&rsquo;s 3.93% larger from the farthest
perigee to closest.  That&rsquo;s how much the &ldquo;close&rdquo; Moon varies through
the year.</p>

<p>So where did the big 14% come from that I kept seeing in all of these
articles.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s the difference in size between when the Moon is at apogee vs
perigee, and that happens every month, two weeks apart.  Actually it&rsquo;s
about 13.36% when the ellipse is stretched, and about 9.8% when it&rsquo;s
not.</p>

<p>So again, this happens <em>every</em> month, but just not when the Moon is
full.</p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SuperMoon">Wikipedia &ndash; SuperMoon</a><br /></p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orbit_of_the_Moon">Wikipedia &ndash; Orbit of the Moon</a><br /></p>

<p><a href="https://www.fourmilab.ch/Earthview/Moon_ap_per.html">Inconstant Moon</a><br /></p>

<p><a href="https://www.fourmilab.ch/Earthview/pacalc.html">Perigee Apogee Calculator</a><br /></p>

<h2>Image credit</h2>

<p>Distance and Moon phases in 2014, calculated using algorithms from:
Jean Meeus, Astronomical algorithms, Willmann-Bell, Richmond,
Virginia, 1991 Jean Meeus, Astronomical formulae for calculators,
Willmann-Bell, Richmond, Virginia, 1988. Moon phases: 0 (1) &ndash; new Moon
0.25 &ndash; first quarter 0.5 &ndash; full Moon 0.75 &ndash; last quarter</p>

<p>CC BY-SA 3.0</p>

<p>by Darekk2.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Observing Gravitational Waves]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/02/06/observing-gravitational-waves/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-06T12:05:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/02/06/observing-gravitational-waves</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The search for detection of gravitational waves continues.</p>

<p><a href="http://arstechnica.com/science/2016/02/after-100-years-scientists-are-finally-closing-in-on-einsteins-ripples/">Ars Technica article</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[So Long Walter H. Haas]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/04/18/so-long-walter-h-haas/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-18T15:11:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/04/18/so-long-walter-h-haas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>Haas devoted his entire life to the study of the Moon and planets.</p></blockquote>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>At a time when professional astronomers held little regard for amateur
observers beyond their meteor and variable-star reports, Haas changed
the paradigm. First, he published (in 1938, at age 21) his in-depth
observations of brightness changes around major lunar craters. Then,
four years later, he followed with a four-part, 76-page opus titled
&ldquo;Does Anything Ever Happen on the Moon?&rdquo; that appeared in the Journal
of the Royal Astronomical Society of Canada. These became the opening
salvo in a lifelong quest &ldquo;to arouse interest in a neglected branch of
astronomy.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>On March 1, 1947, while still at UNM, he dispatched a self-produced
6-page newsletter titled The Strolling Astronomer. Haas already
envisioned this simple missive becoming something bigger: it was
subtitled &ldquo;Association of Lunar and Planetary Observers&rdquo; and branded
with &ldquo;Volume 1, Number 1.&rdquo; By the second issue, a month later, the
budding ALPO had grown to 41 members. Within six years, the
association boasted 350 members from all around the world.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.skyandtelescope.com/astronomy-news/walter-haas-1917-2015-04072015/">Walter H. Haas (1917–2015) by Kelly Beatty</a><br /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.alpo-astronomy.org/">ALPO</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fireball Over Tennessee]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/21/fireball-over-tennessee/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-21T07:57:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/21/fireball-over-tennessee</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 11</a></p>

<p><a href="http://youtu.be/wwF5jI48hGM">http://youtu.be/wwF5jI48hGM</a></p>

<p>Posted by <a href="https://twitter.com/spann/status/524528021093773312">James Spann</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Concerning last night&rsquo;s fireball in the southern sky&hellip;
There was a very bright fireball over middle Tennessee last night
(October 20) at 7:57:09 PM CT. Four NASA all sky cameras (located in
Tullahoma, Huntsville, Chickamauga, and North Georgia College) first
detected it at an altitude of 54 miles, moving slightly north of west
at 47,000 miles per hour.The meteor, estimated to weigh around 10
pounds, travelled some 64 miles through the atmosphere before
fragmenting 24 miles above the town of Brentwood, south of
Nashville. At its brightest, the fireball rivaled the first quarter
Moon, gathering a fair amount of attention in the tri-state area.</p>

<p>Via Bill Cooke&hellip; Meteoroid Environments Office, Marshall Space Flight
Center</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[M103 The Christmas Tree Cluster]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/10/11/m103-the-christmas-tree-cluster/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-11T07:34:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/10/11/m103-the-christmas-tree-cluster</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/m103mg_border.jpg" title="" ></p>

<p>Last night we visted the Fernbank Observatory.  In the course of
looking at a very nice open cluster, NGC 457 I believe, in Cassiopeia,
I was reminded of one of my favorites there, M103.  I always called it
the Christmas Tree cluster and enjoyed showing it to folks.</p>

<p>At the site One-Minute Astronomer
<a href="http://oneminuteastronomer.com/1098/3-clusters-cassiopeia/">oneminuteastronomer.com</a>,
Brian Ventrudo describes M103 as</p>

<blockquote><p>&hellip;the last object in Messier’s original catalog (it was later padded
to include 6 more objects).  It’s also easy to find, about 1 degree
northeast of Ruchbah (or delta Cass).  At 8,500 light years away, it’s
one of the most distant open clusters in Messier’s catalog.  In a
small scope, the cluster is unmistakably triangular and displays
perhaps two dozen stars.  The star triple star Struve 131 is the
bright star at the north vertex of the cluster; you can easily resolve
all three stars in Struve 131 in a scope, even at low power.</p></blockquote>

<p><em>Image credit: by Margin Germano at <a href="http://martingermano.com/">martingermano.com</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
