<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: astronomy | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/astronomy/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2016-10-04T01:21:45-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bigger Milky Way]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/04/bigger-milky-way/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-04T01:06:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/04/bigger-milky-way</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Brian Clark Howard at National Geographic writes that &ldquo;Our Part of the
Milky Way is Four Times Bigger Than We Thought.&rdquo;</p>

<!-- More -->


<blockquote><p>Published in the journal Science Advances this week, a new study
reported that our surrounding area of stars, gas, and dust—called the
Local Arm, Orion Spur, or Orion–Cygnus Arm—is actually about 20,000
light-years long.</p>

<p>The Local Arm is still considerably shorter than the Milky Way’s four
main arms, which wind around the galaxy&rsquo;s center for roughly 80,000
light-years. The total diameter of the galaxy is often reported as
about 100,000 light-years, although Reid says more recent evidence
suggests it is probably more like 70,000 light-years, at least to the
edge of where star density starts to really drop off.</p></blockquote>

<p>The abstract from the paper in &ldquo;Science Advances,&rdquo; &ldquo;The local spiral
structure of the Milky Way&rdquo; by Ye Xu, et al.</p>

<blockquote><p>The nature of the spiral structure of the Milky Way has long been
debated. Only in the last decade have astronomers been able to
accurately measure distances to a substantial number of high-mass
star-forming regions, the classic tracers of spiral structure in
galaxies. We report distance measurements at radio wavelengths using
the Very Long Baseline Array for eight regions of massive star
formation near the Local spiral arm of the Milky Way. Combined with
previous measurements, these observations reveal that the Local Arm is
larger than previously thought, and both its pitch angle and star
formation rate are comparable to those of the Galaxy’s major spiral
arms, such as Sagittarius and Perseus. Toward the constellation
Cygnus, sources in the Local Arm extend for a great distance along our
line of sight and roughly along the solar orbit. Because of this
orientation, these sources cluster both on the sky and in velocity to
form the complex and long enigmatic Cygnus X region. We also identify
a spur that branches between the Local and Sagittarius spiral arms.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://news.nationalgeographic.com/2016/09/milky-way-local-arm-four-times-bigger-than-expected/">Our Part of the Milky Way Is Four Times Bigger Than We Thought</a></p>

<p><a href="http://advances.sciencemag.org/content/2/9/e1600878">The local spiral structure of the Milky Way</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cosmic Distance Ladder]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/26/cosmic-distance-ladder/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-26T06:40:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/26/cosmic-distance-ladder</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On Medium: <a href="https://medium.com/starts-with-a-bang/is-the-cosmic-distance-ladder-flawed-d4d6dc8b4ce5?source=userActivityShare-c61a82880cfd%E2%80%931474882244">Is the Cosmic Distance Ladder Flawed?</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pictures of Telescopes by Telescopes]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/23/pictures-of-telescopes-by-telescopes/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-23T23:23:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/23/pictures-of-telescopes-by-telescopes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This outstanding article by Emily Gilbert in Medium shows pictures of
observatories made from orbiting telescopes.</p>

<p><a href="https://medium.com/planet-stories/pictures-of-telescopes-by-telescopes-ed0d2bf387c1#.lb1abjpwi">Pictures of Telescopes by Telescopes</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[LIGO and the GW150914 Discovery]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/02/21/ligo-and-the-discovery/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-21T07:12:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/02/21/ligo-and-the-discovery</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I finally found the paper for the recent LIGO discovery of gravity
waves from a black hole merger, event GW150914 at 2015-09-14 09:50:45
+0000 which data implies was the merging of two black holes, one with
mass 36 (+5, -4) solar masses and the other 29 (+4, -4) solar masses
into an object of 62 (+4, -4) solar masses with 3 (+0.5, -0.5) solar
masses radiated away (lost) as emitted gravitational waves.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>B.P. Abbot and collaborators say,</p>

<blockquote><p>Over 0.2 s, the signal increases in frequency and amplitude in about 8
cycles from 35 to 150 Hz, where the amplitude reaches a maximum. The
most plausible explanation for this evolution is the inspiral of two
orbiting masses, m1 and m2, due to gravitational-wave emission.</p></blockquote>

<p>The source redshift was measured as <em>z</em>=0.09 (+0.03, -0.04).</p>

<p>One interesting outcome in the conclusions is support for massive
black holes.</p>

<blockquote><p>GW150914 demonstrates the existence of stellar-mass black holes more
massive than ≃ 25 solar masses, and establishes that binary black
holes can form in nature and merge within a Hubble time. Binary
black holes have been predicted to form both in isolated binaries
and in dense environments by dynamical interactions.  The
formation of such massive black holes from stellar evolution
requires weak massive-star winds, which are possible in stellar
environments with metallicity lower than ≃ &frac12; the solar value.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="https://dcc.ligo.org/public/0122/P150914/014/LIGO-P150914_Detection_of_GW150914.pdf">The Paper: Observation of Gravitational Waves from a Binary Black Hole Merger by B. P. Abbott et al. (pdf)</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Observing Gravitational Waves]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/02/06/observing-gravitational-waves/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-06T12:05:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/02/06/observing-gravitational-waves</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The search for detection of gravitational waves continues.</p>

<p><a href="http://arstechnica.com/science/2016/02/after-100-years-scientists-are-finally-closing-in-on-einsteins-ripples/">Ars Technica article</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
