<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: astronomy | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/astronomy/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2014-12-10T08:03:11-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Buying a Telescope]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/12/10/buying-a-telescope/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-10T08:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/12/10/buying-a-telescope</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In November, during the 30-day blog challenge, I wrote a series of
posts on buying a telescope.  With slight editing, I&rsquo;ve combined them
into a single document which also has a link in the menu up top.</p>

<p><a href="http://10.0.0.23/m149daily-blog/telescope/">Buying a Telescope</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Can You Cross a Wormhole?]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/21/can-you-cross-a-wormhole/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-21T08:04:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/21/can-you-cross-a-wormhole</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Do worm holes even exist?  At Smithsonian.com, Victoria Jaggard
writes the article &ldquo;Would Astronauts Survive an Interstellar Trip Through a
Wormhole?&rdquo;</p>

<p>Given the state of current physics the answer is, No.  The idea of
worm holes has come and gone in the science world, though it never
quite leaves.  The Kerr metric solution to Einstein&rsquo;s general
relativity equations applies to &ldquo;rotating&rdquo; black holes and adds new
twists, however there&rsquo;s still not really a way for humans to get
through.</p>

<p>Just like crossing an event horizon is beyond the edge of our
universe, these ideas are beyond the edge of our science.  Of course
we don&rsquo;t know everything and I have no doubt there are amazing things
still to be discovered.  I&rsquo;d never say it can&rsquo;t happen, just that we
don&rsquo;t have a good mechanism in our current astrophysics toolbox unless
we toss in a little magic.  Just like it is with faster-than-light
travel.</p>

<blockquote><p>Despite his ties to the film, [cosmologist Kip] Thorne is also
pessimistic that a traversable wormhole is even possible, much less
survivable. &ldquo;If they can exist, I doubt very much that they can form
naturally in the astrophysical universe,&rdquo; he writes in the book. But
Thorne appreciates that Christopher and Jonah Nolan, who wrote
Interstellar, were so keen to tell a story that is grounded in
science.</p></blockquote>

<p>There&rsquo;s more to come on this topic and other folks have weighed in.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.smithsonianmag.com/science-nature/would-astronauts-survive-interstellar-trip-through-wormhole-180953269/">Would Astronauts Survive an Interstellar Trip Through a Wormhole?</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sudden Galaxies]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/19/sudden-galaxies/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-19T08:12:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/19/sudden-galaxies</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>A team of astronomers using the Subaru Telescope&rsquo;s Suprime-Cam to
perform the Subaru Ultra-Deep Survey for Lyman-alpha Emitters have
looked back more than [<em>z=7</em>] to find 7 early galaxies that
appeared quite suddenly within 700 million years of the Big Bang. The
team, led by graduate student Akira Konno and Dr. Masami Ouchi
(Associate Professor at the University of Tokyo&rsquo;s ICRR) was looking
for a specific kind of galaxy called a Lyman-alpha emitter (LAE), to
understand the role such galaxies may have played in an event called
&ldquo;cosmic reionization&rdquo;.</p></blockquote>

<p>The team looked at distant galaxies that primarily emit Lyman-alpha
radiation, &ldquo;Lyman-alpha emitters&rdquo; or LAE, and saw fewer than expected,
further back in time.  There&rsquo;s an apparent sudden cutoff at that
redshift.  The redshift corresponds to a distance and time in history
that&rsquo;s model dependent.  The standard big bang model would put this at
about 13.1 billion years and only 700 million years after the big bang
itself.  The cosmological-history implication is that these galaxies
&ldquo;suddenly&rdquo; appear.</p>

<p>One thing is pretty certain.  A cosmological redshift of seven
indicates the universe was about 1/8 it&rsquo;s current size at the time the
light they observed was emitted.  That&rsquo;s 1 / (<em>z</em> + 1).</p>

<blockquote><p>According to the team&rsquo;s analysis, one reason that LAEs appeared very
quickly is cosmic reionization. LAEs in the epoch of cosmic
reionization became darker than the actual luminosity due to the
presence of the neutral hydrogen fog. In the team&rsquo;s analysis of their
observations, they suggest the possibility that the neutral fog
filling the universe was cleared about 13.0 billion years ago and LAEs
suddenly appeared in sight for the first time."</p>

<p>&ldquo;However, there are other possibilities to explain why LAEs appeared
suddenly,&rdquo; said Dr. Ouchi, who is the principal investigator of this
program. &ldquo;One is that clumps of neutral hydrogen around LAEs
disappeared. Another is that LAEs became intrinsically bright. The
reason of the intrinsic brightening is that the Lyman-alpha emission
is not efficiently produced by the ionized clouds in a LAE due to the
significant escape of ionizing photons from the galaxy. In either
case, our discovery is an important key to understanding cosmic
reionization and the properties of the LAEs in early universe.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://phys.org/news/2014-11-subaru-telescope-sudden-galaxies-early.html">Subaru Telescope detects sudden appearance of galaxies in the early universe at phys.org</a><br />
<a href="http://www.icrr.u-tokyo.ac.jp/2014/11/19120001.html">Press release from ICRR</a><br />
<a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1404.6066v2.pdf">PDF of paper &ldquo;Accelerated Evolution Of The Lyα Luminosity Function At z >~ 7 Revealed By The Subaru Ultra-Deep Survey For Lyα Emitters AT z = 7.3&rdquo;</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ray Bradbury - If Only We Had Taller Been]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/12/ray-bradbury/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-12T23:31:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/12/ray-bradbury</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/ray_bradbury.png" title="" ></p>

<p>On 12 November 1971, exactly 43 years ago, Ray Bradbury spoke to an
audience at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory on the eve of Mariner 9
arriving at Mars.  On stage with him were Arthur C. Clarke, Carl
Sagan, Bruce Murray, and Walter Sullivan.  Bradbury read his poem, &ldquo;If
Only We Had Taller Been.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Today, on 12 November 2014, the Philae spacecraft &ldquo;docked&rdquo; with the
comet 67P/Churyumov-Gerasimenko.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EBtZjbTDTDk">Youtube Video &ndash; Ray Bradbury &ndash; If Only We Had Taller Been</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rosetta]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/11/rosetta/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-11T05:12:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/11/rosetta</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/NAVCAM_top_10_at_10_km_3_node_full_image_2.jpg"></p>

<p>From the ESA web site.</p>

<blockquote><p>Rosetta is a cornerstone mission to chase, go into orbit around, and
land on a comet. It is studying the Jupiter-family comet
67P/Churyumov-Gerasimenko with a combination of remote sensing and in
situ measurements. The spacecraft arrived at the comet on 6 August
2014 following a 10-year journey through the Solar System. Between
August and November, the spacecraft has been orbiting the comet and
gathering data to characterise the environment and the comet
nucleus. On 12 November 2014, Rosetta&rsquo;s lander Philae will be deployed
to the surface. Philae carries a suite of instruments for imaging and
sampling the comet nucleus. The Rosetta orbiter will track the comet
through perihelion (August 2015), examining its behaviour before,
during and after.</p></blockquote>

<p>[SIC]:  I saw a pronunciation guide for Philae that said &ldquo;fee-lay.&rdquo;
This is wrong.  The pronunciation rhymes with eye-lee, or &ldquo;highly.&rdquo;
Whenever you see ae, it rhymes with ee as in leek.  For example,
Caesar.  And yes, the UNIX-famous word &ldquo;daemon&rdquo; is pronounced
precisely and exactly like demon. Other pronunciations are wrong.
(<a href="http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/philae">Merriam-Webster</a>,
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philae">Wikipedia</a>).</p>

<p><a href="http://sci.esa.int/rosetta/">ESA Rosetta Site</a><br />
<a href="http://sci.esa.int/rosetta/2279-summary/">Summary</a><br />
<a href="http://www.esa.int/Our_Activities/Space_Science/Rosetta/Highlights/Top_10_at_10_km">Top 10 images from 10 km</a><br />
<a href="http://earthsky.org/space/watch-wednesdays-comet-landing-live-online">EarthSky &ndash; Watch Wednesday’s comet landing live online</a><br /></p>

<p><em>Image: ESA/Rosetta/NAVCAM – CC BY-SA IGO 3.0</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
