<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: iphone | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/iphone/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2014-11-11T05:43:20-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[IOS Reliable Updates]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/10/ios-reliable-updates/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-10T06:42:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/10/ios-reliable-updates</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are two key reasons that I&rsquo;m overjoyed to have made the switch
from Android to IOS and the iPhone.</p>

<p>One is the reliability of OS updates.  There&rsquo;s no worrying about
pure-Google vs. vendor-imposed-UI and junk apps. There&rsquo;s no waiting
for a vendor to either roll out an update or, more likely, just force
you to buy a new phone or wait for your cycle to end to get a new
phone.</p>

<p>The IOS updates are (so far) annual, universal and hassle
free.  And by hassel free I&rsquo;m referring to the above issues.  It&rsquo;s
granted there have been hiccups and bugs, but usually they are
resolved in a reasonable time.  I try to be cautious and wait for a
minor update or to before diving in.  Thus, I skipped 8.0 and waited
for 8.1.</p>

<p>The other joy is from the pictures the iPhones make.  There are
Android phones with better camera specs on paper, and yet, the photos
are often just not up to par.  My Galaxy Nexus made images that ranged
from okay to terrible.  When I go back and look at them now, they look
even worse than I realized.  I know other people disagree but I&rsquo;m
firmly in the camp: There&rsquo;s no contest here.</p>

<p>So, that makes two items removed from the list of things to have to
deal with.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[IOS 8.1]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/09/ios-8-dot-1/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-09T21:53:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/09/ios-8-dot-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/20141109_iPhone.jpg"></p>

<p><a href="/blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 30</a></p>

<p>Today I upgraded to IOS 8.1 with no trouble and it&rsquo;s working well so
far.</p>

<p>I am one of those users who doesn&rsquo;t have the 5-GB or so of space on my
iPhone to do an over-the-air upgrade.  In spite of that, you can do an
upgrade without needing the space if you connect your iPhone to your
Mac (or Windows?) running iTunes and use iTunes to do the upgrade.  It
does the downloading and expansion of files on your desktop machine
then installs the upgrade over the USB cable.</p>

<p>The upgrade/install went without any trouble and it took almost
exactly 36 minutes it predicted.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve not used it too much.  So far, all the apps look and work the
same as in IOS 7.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[iPhone After Eight Months]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/06/20/iphone-after-eight-months/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-20T06:17:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/06/20/iphone-after-eight-months</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/20140620_iphone.png"></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s now been eight months since I switched to the iPhone in October
2012.  The honeymoon is over and I&rsquo;ve been chewing on the green grass
for a while.  I can say I&rsquo;m just as happy and pleased with the the 5C
as I was when it was new, maybe even more.</p>

<p>It does everything I need or want it to do.  I have a nice set of apps
I use daily, a simulation and a game here or there, and generally I
can find just about anything I need in an app and it all works fine.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m still using the Gmail and the Google Maps apps for email, maps and
navigation.  Amazon cloud player was just updated and is still my
primary music player.  Netflix works fine but I typically use the
Youtube app for watching videos.</p>

<p>Apple&rsquo;s iMessage works great for texting with images and video with
the rest of the family and we all have iPhones at this point.</p>

<p>The camera continues to make great pictures, as expected.</p>

<p>Here are some of the most recent apps of significance I&rsquo;ve added.
Loom was bought by Dropbox who introduced an app called Carousel, so
I&rsquo;m not using it to automatically upload and archive photos.  Carousel
is nice as an app but there doesn&rsquo;t seem to be a correspondingly nice
web interface other then a plain Dropbox folder with a <em>lot</em> of image
files in it.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not a fan of Facebook.  In fact I don&rsquo;t like it much at all.
However, I have to say that Paper is nicely done, beautiful in some
ways, but a little quirky sometimes.  I like it many times better than
the regular Facebook interface because it&rsquo;s fun to use, but I ignore
the news feed and those other screens.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve become interested in trains lately and Trainz Driver is a fun
simulator.</p>

<p>If you compare the current image of my home screen here to the image I
<a href="http:/m149daily-blog/blog/2013/10/07/transition-to-the-iphone/">posted back in October 2012</a>, you can see that it hasn&rsquo;t changed much.
That&rsquo;s screen one and I only use three screens of apps that are about
&frac12; to 2/3 full.</p>

<p><em>Image: my current iPhone screen one.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Transition to the iPhone]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/10/07/transition-to-the-iphone/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-07T09:06:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/10/07/transition-to-the-iphone</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/iphone_screen.png" title="" ></p>

<p>I can now summarize my previous post up in one sentence:  Android had
become tiring and I find the iPhone delightful.</p>

<p>The new iPhone 5C arrived on Wed 2013-10-02 and I found the transition
from the almost-two-year-old Android Galaxy Nexus 4.2.2 easy and
painless.  So far I&rsquo;m happy using a new device with a fresh new
interface and all that I consider essential.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>I ordered the iPhone 5C on-line at the Apple Store.  The process was
simple and integration with my Verizon account and changes were
straightforward.  There was no charge for shipping and the device
shipped by UPS and arrived in two days, i.e., I ordered it on Monday
and it arrived on Wednesday.  Somehow, Apple got the idea it should
have arrived on Tuesday and sent an apologetic email alert about a
shipping delay.</p>

<p>Transitioning the phone over to my Verizon account after turning it on
was equally simple and only involved entering my phone number and the
other typical identifying information Verizon wants.</p>

<p>Syncing my Gmail/Google contact list to the phone was a quick web
search and simply adding that account to the Settings for the phone.
I enabled contact syncing (but not email!) and much later, this
morning in fact, I turned on calendar syncing.  I didn&rsquo;t sync email
because I&rsquo;m using the Gmail app and not the iPhone email app.</p>

<h2>Apps</h2>

<p>For installing apps I logged into my existing Apple account with no
problem.  In the first evening I was able to easily install nearly
every app I consider essential, including all of the Google apps like
Gmail, Maps, Chrome and more.</p>

<p>I continued to pull down apps over the next few days as I thought of
them, needed them, or just had time to&mdash;the demand paging
approach.</p>

<p>Amazon Cloud player was also an easy install and works just as it does
on the Android.  It will stream from the cloud or download songs,
albums, or playlists to the phone to play them locally.</p>

<p>With a quick search of some on-line recommendations I settled on the
excellent program, Downcast, for downloading and playing podcasts.
Though I liked Doggcatcher on Android, I think Downcast is actually
much better.</p>

<p>I figured out how to rearrange the apps on the screens so that the
important apps were on the bottom bar (Amazon Cloud Player, Phone,
Messages, Chrome), how to put apps into folders, etc.  As expected,
there&rsquo;s still fiddling around left to do to get the arrangement of
apps and organization of the screens balanced so they work best for
me, but it&rsquo;s very workable right now.</p>

<h2>Anticipated Problems</h2>

<p>For the most part, things I worried about the most haven&rsquo;t been any
trouble at all.</p>

<p>Having no back button doesn&rsquo;t really cause a problem.  Apps usually
provide their own back button, or some equivalent, when you&rsquo;d need
one.  It&rsquo;s usually in the upper left corner.  And there&rsquo;s bailing out
with the home button but I rarely find myself using that as an
alternative to a back button.</p>

<p>Other changes in using a different interface just haven&rsquo;t been a
problem.  The new UI has been easy and fast to learn.  I like it a lot
and, since I didn&rsquo;t have IOS 6 as a reference, I don&rsquo;t have anything
to complain about regarding differences.</p>

<p>Surprisingly I don&rsquo;t miss the widgets at all.  There&rsquo;s a nice economy
of focus to only seeing information when you want to see it.  There&rsquo;s
not the distraction of some random Facebook update and, well, I guess
I just didn&rsquo;t really depend that much on the other widgets.  So, I
thought widgets were really neat, I still do, but I&rsquo;ve found they
aren&rsquo;t essential.  Perhaps that means they&rsquo;re really clutter, but I
like them enough I wouldn&rsquo;t suggest they be removed from Android.</p>

<p>One of the advantages of Android is the ability to customize almost
anything and everything.  It&rsquo;s probably my personal stage of phone
usage, but I don&rsquo;t want to do that kind of hacking, I just want
something that works.</p>

<h2>No perfect box</h2>

<p>Here&rsquo;s the worst thing about the iPhone 5C: the box.  Most Apple
products come in packaging that&rsquo;s so nice you hate to throw it away.
The 5C came in a somewhat annoying, oversized, retro-like plastic
case.  And the worst sin of all, it was sealed with tape that left
behind a pet-roller-like sticky band which makes you want to throw
whole thing away as quickly as possible.  The opposite effect of the
typical packaging.</p>

<p>Yes, it&rsquo;s not that important, really.  Just bothersome.</p>

<h2>Missing out on the Nexus 5</h2>

<p>I don&rsquo;t mind.  If the leaked LG information is accurate, the Nexus 5
isn&rsquo;t attention-grabbing to me.  I have more to say in another post
about why that may be.  If I&rsquo;d waited and then sprung for the Moto X
or Nexus 5, I&rsquo;d have a phone nearly the same as what I had.  It might
perform better from some ratchet clicks of CPU specs, but I don&rsquo;t know
if I&rsquo;d notice.  Maybe.</p>

<h2>Reality check</h2>

<p>I know I&rsquo;m still grazing on the greener grass at the start of a
new-phone honeymoon.  The real test will be how its working after one,
six and 12 months.  But I have to say, being able to fall right in
with all that I consider essential right there and a nice solid
interface and hardware, I can&rsquo;t see the complaints yet.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting an iPhone?]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/09/28/getting-an-iphone/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-28T12:56:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/09/28/getting-an-iphone</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/iphone5c.png" title="" ></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m thinking about getting an iPhone.  I know this is a shocking
thought.  I&rsquo;ve never had an iPhone before.  The only smart phones I&rsquo;ve
ever owned were the Android phones, starting with the G1.  I currently
have a Samsung Galaxy Nexus with (get out the phone, tap settings,
about phone, ah&hellip;) 4.2.2.  I&rsquo;d been planning to get a Samsung S4 or
S3.  I think the HTC One is currently the best Android phone hardware
out there.</p>

<!-- More -->


<h2>It has to be Google</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve come to one critical conclusion about Android phones.  I&rsquo;ll only
accept a &ldquo;pure Google&rdquo; phone.  Currently that would be the Moto X for
the newest.  I&rsquo;ve heard that Verizon&rsquo;s add-ons for the S4 are
unbearable.</p>

<p>My thinking had been that I&rsquo;d just download one of the ROMs and flash
an S4 into a more pure-Google experience, but that&rsquo;s looking like more
bother and annoyance than I&rsquo;m interested in.  In fact, the Android
experience seems to come with a growing amount of annoyance, in spite
of the great things about it.  The signal to noise ratio is getting
worse.  That&rsquo;s one reason I&rsquo;m thinking about changing.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s probably a new, pure Google phone soon to come, maybe under
the Nexus name.  It might be worth waiting for, but I&rsquo;m inclined not
to wait.</p>

<p>The S3 doesn&rsquo;t seem significantly different from my current,
two-year-old Galaxy Nexus.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s true that I&rsquo;m completely ensconced in the Google system of apps,
especially on my phone with Gmail Google Voice.  However, the web
experiences and apps on the iPhone seem acceptable.  The Google apps
on IOS may lag the Android world, but I&rsquo;m not looking for the latest
and greatest.  Lately I fear the continuous feature roll-outs from
Google.  I don&rsquo;t find that much delight in what&rsquo;s coming out
lately.  If IOS as a platform slows that down some, I may just count
that as a huge advantage.</p>

<h2>Iphone looks interesting and sufficient</h2>

<p>The iPhone seems both interesting and sufficient.  The new interface
looks pleasant.  It promises to bring some consistency and it has the
new, thin fonts (that Android recently brought) that I like.  Google
destroyed the nice clock the Android used to have with the stupid,
bold-face hour display.  If the IOS 7 UI is consistent and performs
well, that will meet my needs.</p>

<h2>Best Cameras</h2>

<p>The iPhones undoubtedly make the best pictures.  My family all have
iPhones now and their pictures are consistently better than those I
make with my phone.</p>

<h2>Reliable behaviour</h2>

<p>Android has been multitasking, in what I would consider a pure way,
since the beginning and I&rsquo;ve always appreciated that.  However, these
days, for whatever reason, I find myself constantly tapping things
where nothing happens.  Or the delay is so long I&rsquo;m not sure whether a
tap registered or not.  I&rsquo;ll take reliable behaviour over pure
multitasking and whatever else is going on there.</p>

<p>That said, I completely admit that this could be a false difference.
Finding out will be part of this &ldquo;experiment.&rdquo;</p>

<h2>Apps and Widgets</h2>

<p>As far as I can tell, all of the apps that I consider essential to my
daily phone life are available.  I&rsquo;ll really miss the widgets,
particularly my analog clock and the weather widget.  I&rsquo;ll also miss
the little app that shows the time in various time zones with a little
globe, showing the day-night part of the earth, that I can spin around
with my finger.  I expect there&rsquo;s surely some similar IOS app there.
I&rsquo;ll find out.</p>

<p>I think the GPS navigation may not be as good, and that may be a huge
loss.  I&rsquo;ll have to see if that&rsquo;s the case and if I can live with
that.</p>

<h2>The smaller screen</h2>

<p>How will the smaller screen be?  This might be my biggest question.
Whenever I look at one of the family&rsquo;s phones, I never think, Wow,
that screen is really small.  I can barely look at it.  Generally I
don&rsquo;t even notice.  Apparent screen size has to do with viewing
distance.  If holding the screen closer enough to cancel any
difference isn&rsquo;t noticeable, it shouldn&rsquo;t matter.  This is something
I&rsquo;ll find out.  Update: Actually, I&rsquo;ve now held my Galaxy Nexus and an
iPhone 5c side by side and I barely had to move the screen a phone
thickness to match apparent sizes, actually solid angles.</p>

<h2>It&rsquo;s an experiment</h2>

<p>This will be an experiment.  I know the grass always looks greener on
the other side and I don&rsquo;t doubt that&rsquo;s true here.  I have complaints
and things annoy me.  My live snow fall wall paper is starting to
crash and it&rsquo;s starting to misbehave in other ways.  Still, I can
always return back to that phone, and a future pure Android phone, if
I can&rsquo;t stand the iPhone world.</p>

<p>If I do make this leap (I haven&rsquo;t committed yet), I&rsquo;ll write some
update on what I think about the progress.</p>

<h2>In summary</h2>

<p>My reasons for changing.</p>

<ul>
<li>I&rsquo;ll only accept a pure Google phone for Android.</li>
<li>The current options really don&rsquo;t outshine my two-year-old 32-GB Galaxy Nexus.</li>
<li>Android signal-to-noise (delight vs. annoyance) is getting progressively worse.</li>
<li>IOS has Google apps.</li>
<li>IOS also has all of my other essential apps.</li>
<li>The iPhone has better cameras.</li>
<li>I&rsquo;m convinced the UI behaviour is more reliable and stable.</li>
</ul>


<p>Some possible down sides.</p>

<ul>
<li>I&rsquo;ll miss the widgets.</li>
<li>GPS navigation may not be good enough.</li>
<li>The smaller screen.</li>
<li>Something I haven&rsquo;t thought of.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
