<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: iphone | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/iphone/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2017-02-06T07:33:20-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[IOS 10 Upgrade]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/10/ios-10-upgrade/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-10T00:22:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/10/ios-10-upgrade</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s upgrade week for IOS.  I finally decided to take the plunge and
upgrade IOS 9 to IOS 10 on my iPhone 6S.  Usually I wait until about
the second minor update has come out and we&rsquo;re now at 10.0.2 as of
late last week, so Sunday night was the night.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>Even though the initial problems with over-the-air upgrades was
solved, I&rsquo;m still sticking with using iTunes on my desktop Mac Mini to
do the upgrade.  I grabbed my charging cable, plugged the phone into
the computer, started up iTunes because it&rsquo;s configured not to start
automatically, and first went to do a back up.</p>

<h2>Backup and Download</h2>

<p>Starting at about 22:35, I did an encrypted backup which said it was
taking about 10 minutes but that last 10 seconds seemed to take an
additional five minutes or so.  The encrypted back up will grab the
key chains and such.</p>

<p>From there I clicked the button to proceed with the 10.0.2 install and
it began the download to my computer.  This was the most uncomfortable
part because there&rsquo;s no progress bar or anything to really indicate
it&rsquo;s working.  I was monitoring the network traffic with Activity
Monitor and could see the actual packet rates as it downloaded, but I
would have preferred to have more feedback.</p>

<p>The downloading seemed to finally finish at about 23:40.  I just
happened to look up and notice the message in iTunes that said it was
downloading had changed to click Upgrade to begin the upgrade.</p>

<h2>Install</h2>

<p>The upgrade was much quicker and the progress bars appeared on the
phone as usual.  After only about 14 minutes at 23:54 the phone went
dark for quite a few seconds.  Again I wondered if all was well but
the white reboot screen with the black apple finally appeared.  There
was another progress bar and then I was logging in with my pass code
on the phone at 23:56.</p>

<p>iTunes then popped up a box saying there was an upgrade from the
carrier so I clicked that button and it quickly and silently installed
with no indication that anything happened from the phone itself.</p>

<p>By about midnight I was done.  I fooled around with the phone for
another 15 minutes or so, moved the newly appeared Home app into a
folder, and it was done.</p>

<h2>Post Install</h2>

<p>I just looked at things briefly. The lock screen, swipe-up screen and
the notifications screen are all different.  The new buttons in
Messages were there but it was too late to try any of that.  Also the
wake-up, unlock process is different.  So far it&rsquo;s a little confusing
in the sense that I&rsquo;m not sure what&rsquo;s different.  You push the home
button to unlock the screen which is what I thought I used to do.</p>

<p>If there&rsquo;s anything else interesting enough to follow up on I&rsquo;ll
report back later.</p>

<h2>References</h2>

<p>From iMore <a href="http://m.imore.com/ios-10">iOS 10 review: Cleaner, cleverer, and more convenient</a><br />
From Song-a-Day Jonathon Mann <a href="https://youtu.be/0heNVPPEy24">Video</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Latest iPhone Home Screen]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/25/latest-iphone-home-screen/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-25T16:46:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/25/latest-iphone-home-screen</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/20160926.0559.iPhone_Homescreen.png"></p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s the most recent image of my iPhone home screen as it continues
to evolve.  I think the most recent, previous image was this one.</p>

<p><a href="/blog/2014/11/09/ios-8-dot-1/">IOS 8.1</a></p>

<!-- More -->


<h2>Vs. the Old Screen</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/20141109_iPhone.jpg"></p>

<p>Instapaper is out.  I still use it on the desktop sometime but, since
I switched to Safari (yep), it has reading mode which is easy and
basically does the same thing.</p>

<p>I really like Read Quick and I&rsquo;m a fan of Clayton and Natalie Morris,
at least when they&rsquo;re on Twit.tv podcasts.  It&rsquo;s a neat idea and it
actually works, but I just wasn&rsquo;t using it.  When I&rsquo;m commuting
(driving) and at other times I&rsquo;m more often listening than reading.  I
just stopped using it very much.</p>

<p>The dreaded Facebook has arrived.  Yeah.  I finally decided to bite
the bullet and try using Facebook for news as well as family goings on
so I listened to Robert Scoble explain to Leo Laporte how to tune
Facebook&rsquo;s news feed, groups, etc.  I&rsquo;ve been using it since February.</p>

<p>I just removed Evernote and put Byword there a few minutes ago.  I&rsquo;m a
fan of Evernote but they seem to be struggling (as the press puts it)
and I decided it was a good time to move another one of my data sinks
to the text-Markdown world.  So now I write notes using Drafts, save
them to Dropbox (where they are titled and formatted) and access them
using various Markdown formatters.  The formatter that allows both
previewing the Markdown but also editing the notes within Dropbox is
Byword.  On the Mac desktop I use Marked for previewing and, of
course, just Emacs in a terminal window to edit.  This has been
working surprisingly well.  The only thing missing right now is that
Byword doesn&rsquo;t render included images.  There are some competing
standards between apps on how that&rsquo;s done, i.e., how images are
included.  There is Multi-markdown and I think it has a standard way,
but Byword doesn&rsquo;t seem to use it.  I&rsquo;m not sure I&rsquo;ve done all of the
required homework on that one, though.</p>

<p>I still have my Evernote account and it&rsquo;s still on my phone, but just
not on the home screen.  I also exported my notes and wrote an XML
parser (well, I used the Python pre-existing XML library) to un-XML
them.</p>

<p>Drafts is a wonderful app I&rsquo;ve been using for a while.  As everyone
that talks about it says, it&rsquo;s just for entering text.  It opens super
fast and it&rsquo;s ready for you just to type.  I have it set up to take
notes and save them to Dropbox with the formatting described above.
It&rsquo;s where my notes went, even when I was using Evernote.  From other
apps' Share sheets, I can send things to Drafts so it basically
connects all of my apps together.</p>

<p>Finally, Safari.  Chrome just keeps bloating in various ways and I
heard that Safari handled battery life on the iPhone in a much better
way.  That makes sense.  It seems secure enough (but note the most
recent &ldquo;pwn&rdquo; (however you spell it) conference where Chrome withstood
and Safari fell two or three times.  I tried switching to Safari quite
a few months ago, both on the phone and desktop, and I&rsquo;ve been using
it ever since.  There are some Google apps that Chrome handles better,
mainly their finance stock charts, but usually Safari is fine.  Chrome
is still on my phone and I still use it at work.  I wouldn&rsquo;t argue
that Safari is better (except for the memory footprint, maybe faster
and with better battery management where I <em>would</em> argue it&rsquo;s better),
but it&rsquo;s seemed good enough so far.</p>

<h2>References</h2>

<p><a href="/blog/2014/11/09/ios-8-dot-1/">IOS 8.1</a><br />
<a href="/blog/2016/02/06/tuning-facebook/">Tuning Facebook</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[IOS Reliable Updates]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/10/ios-reliable-updates/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-10T06:42:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/10/ios-reliable-updates</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are two key reasons that I&rsquo;m overjoyed to have made the switch
from Android to IOS and the iPhone.</p>

<p>One is the reliability of OS updates.  There&rsquo;s no worrying about
pure-Google vs. vendor-imposed-UI and junk apps. There&rsquo;s no waiting
for a vendor to either roll out an update or, more likely, just force
you to buy a new phone or wait for your cycle to end to get a new
phone.</p>

<p>The IOS updates are (so far) annual, universal and hassle
free.  And by hassel free I&rsquo;m referring to the above issues.  It&rsquo;s
granted there have been hiccups and bugs, but usually they are
resolved in a reasonable time.  I try to be cautious and wait for a
minor update or to before diving in.  Thus, I skipped 8.0 and waited
for 8.1.</p>

<p>The other joy is from the pictures the iPhones make.  There are
Android phones with better camera specs on paper, and yet, the photos
are often just not up to par.  My Galaxy Nexus made images that ranged
from okay to terrible.  When I go back and look at them now, they look
even worse than I realized.  I know other people disagree but I&rsquo;m
firmly in the camp: There&rsquo;s no contest here.</p>

<p>So, that makes two items removed from the list of things to have to
deal with.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[IOS 8.1]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/09/ios-8-dot-1/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-09T21:53:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/09/ios-8-dot-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/20141109_iPhone.jpg"></p>

<p><a href="/blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 30</a></p>

<p>Today I upgraded to IOS 8.1 with no trouble and it&rsquo;s working well so
far.</p>

<p>I am one of those users who doesn&rsquo;t have the 5-GB or so of space on my
iPhone to do an over-the-air upgrade.  In spite of that, you can do an
upgrade without needing the space if you connect your iPhone to your
Mac (or Windows?) running iTunes and use iTunes to do the upgrade.  It
does the downloading and expansion of files on your desktop machine
then installs the upgrade over the USB cable.</p>

<p>The upgrade/install went without any trouble and it took almost
exactly 36 minutes it predicted.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve not used it too much.  So far, all the apps look and work the
same as in IOS 7.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[iPhone After Eight Months]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/06/20/iphone-after-eight-months/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-20T06:17:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/06/20/iphone-after-eight-months</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/20140620_iphone.png"></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s now been eight months since I switched to the iPhone in October
2012.  The honeymoon is over and I&rsquo;ve been chewing on the green grass
for a while.  I can say I&rsquo;m just as happy and pleased with the the 5C
as I was when it was new, maybe even more.</p>

<p>It does everything I need or want it to do.  I have a nice set of apps
I use daily, a simulation and a game here or there, and generally I
can find just about anything I need in an app and it all works fine.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m still using the Gmail and the Google Maps apps for email, maps and
navigation.  Amazon cloud player was just updated and is still my
primary music player.  Netflix works fine but I typically use the
Youtube app for watching videos.</p>

<p>Apple&rsquo;s iMessage works great for texting with images and video with
the rest of the family and we all have iPhones at this point.</p>

<p>The camera continues to make great pictures, as expected.</p>

<p>Here are some of the most recent apps of significance I&rsquo;ve added.
Loom was bought by Dropbox who introduced an app called Carousel, so
I&rsquo;m not using it to automatically upload and archive photos.  Carousel
is nice as an app but there doesn&rsquo;t seem to be a correspondingly nice
web interface other then a plain Dropbox folder with a <em>lot</em> of image
files in it.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not a fan of Facebook.  In fact I don&rsquo;t like it much at all.
However, I have to say that Paper is nicely done, beautiful in some
ways, but a little quirky sometimes.  I like it many times better than
the regular Facebook interface because it&rsquo;s fun to use, but I ignore
the news feed and those other screens.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve become interested in trains lately and Trainz Driver is a fun
simulator.</p>

<p>If you compare the current image of my home screen here to the image I
<a href="http:/m149daily-blog/blog/2013/10/07/transition-to-the-iphone/">posted back in October 2012</a>, you can see that it hasn&rsquo;t changed much.
That&rsquo;s screen one and I only use three screens of apps that are about
&frac12; to 2/3 full.</p>

<p><em>Image: my current iPhone screen one.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
