<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: comics | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/comics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2016-11-23T02:12:16-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ducking Into a Nearby Phone Booth]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/01/23/ducking-into-a-nearby-phone-booth/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-23T14:31:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/01/23/ducking-into-a-nearby-phone-booth</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was recently wondering about the origin of Superman finding a phone
booth to change in.  I found one source on the origin and it was
surprising.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>Why was I wondering about this in the first place?  It&rsquo;s because I was
thinking about the John Williams soundtrack from the 1978 movie.  I
recalled the scene where Clark Kent stops and glances at the little hood-like
phone booth and keeps going, looking for a place to change.  I
wondered where the changing in a phone booth meme came from since I
didn&rsquo;t recall Superman ever actually changing in a phone booth in any
of the comics or TV shows, etc.</p>

<p>A quick search online pulled up some interesting history including a
post by Steve Younis on supermanhoempage.com called &lsquo;Superman and the
Phone Booth."</p>

<blockquote><p>In the Golden Age of comic books Clark Kent didn&rsquo;t use a phone booth
to change into Superman. Actually right throughout every era of
Superman comics the phone booth change has rarely been seen.</p></blockquote>

<p>The first time Superman changes is (spoiler):</p>

<blockquote><p>The answer lies way back in 1941.</p>

<p>To my knowledge, Clark Kent first changed to Superman inside a phone
booth in &ldquo;The Mechanical Monsters&rdquo;, the second of 17 Superman
cartoons produced by Fleischer Studios for Paramount Pictures. It
was released to cinemas on November 28 in 1941.</p></blockquote>

<p>I was pretty much unaware of the Fleischer Studios Superman
animations.  They&rsquo;re very well done and influenced some of the more
recent TV animations in style.</p>

<p>I recommend finding &ldquo;The Mechanical Monsters&rdquo; on Youtube and watching it.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.supermanhomepage.com/other/other.php?topic=phonebooth">Superman and the Phone Booth</a>
<a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Superman_(1940s_cartoons">Superman 1940s cartoons</a>)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
