<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: space | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/space/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2013-12-01T19:48:43-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Friday Moon Shot]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/09/04/friday-moon-shot/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-04T04:37:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/09/04/friday-moon-shot</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/663539main_wallops-minotaurv-wideangle_br.jpg"></p>

<p>Via <a href="https://twitter.com/PTTU/status/375137266101780481">@PTTU</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.space.com/22635-american-minotaur-5-rocket-launch-debut.html">New American Rocket Making Launch Debut with Friday Moon Shot</a>
By Mike Wall, Senior Writer at Space.com</p>

<blockquote><p>A Minotaur V rocket will carry NASA&rsquo;s Lunar Atmosphere and Dust
Environment Explorer spacecraft (LADEE) on its maiden launch, which is
slated to take place Friday at 11:27 p.m. EDT (0327 GMT) from the
space agency&rsquo;s Wallops Flight Facility in Virginia.</p>

<p>The first three stages of the Minotaur V (and the Minotaur IV) are
solid rocket motors recycled from decommissioned Peacekeeper
intercontinental ballistic missiles. The fourth and fifth stages are
commercial Star motors, which are also flight-proven, [<em>Wallops
launch manager Doug</em>] Voss said.</p>

<p>The $280 million LADEE mission aims to study lunar dust and the moon&rsquo;s
wispy atmosphere from orbit using three science instruments.</p>

<p>[Space.com] Editor&rsquo;s note: Weather permitting, Friday&rsquo;s launch
 could be visible across wide regions of the U.S. East Coast.</p></blockquote>

<!-- more -->


<h2>What is LADEE</h2>

<p>From NASA:</p>

<blockquote><p>NASA&rsquo;s Lunar Atmosphere and Dust Environment Explorer (LADEE) is a
robotic mission that will orbit the moon to gather detailed
information about the lunar atmosphere, conditions near the surface
and environmental influences on lunar dust. A thorough understanding
of these characteristics will address long-standing unknowns, and help
scientists understand other planetary bodies as well.</p>

<p>The LADEE spacecraft&rsquo;s modular common spacecraft bus, or body, is an
innovative way of transitioning away from custom designs and toward
multi-use designs and assembly-line production, which could
drastically reduce the cost of spacecraft development, just as the
Ford Model T did for automobiles. NASA&rsquo;s Ames Research Center
designed, developed, built and tested the spacecraft.</p></blockquote>

<h2>References</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/ladee/main/index.html#.UibyumTlVZ8">NASA LADEE Mission</a><br></p>

<p><em>Image Credit: NASA Wallops/Jackie Adkins</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
