<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: space | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/space/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2014-12-21T06:00:34-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Robert Truax - Rocketeer]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/12/05/robert-truax-rocketeer/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-05T06:07:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/12/05/robert-truax-rocketeer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In a time of Richard Branson and Virgin Galactic, along with
impressive amateur rocketeers and commercial space ventures, we might
have forgotten about Bob Truax, one of the first commercial, private
rocket jockeys.</p>

<p>From Wikipedia,</p>

<blockquote><p>Truax also designed the Skycycle X-2, which he unsuccessfully tested
on April 15, 1972 and June 24, 1973, and which Evel Knievel
unsuccessfully used at the Snake River Canyon in 1974.</p></blockquote>

<p>And also,</p>

<blockquote><p>The X-3 Volksrocket (other names: Arriba One, Skycycle X-3) was a
reusable space tourism rocket planned by Robert Truax after Evel
Knievel provided a $1,000 research grant for a pilot study. Truax
was looking for volunteers with enough money to help fund the effort
and who wished to fly aboard his rocket. He got thousands of
volunteers, but few of them had the financial resources.</p>

<p>The rocket used surplus components and was tested through 1991.</p></blockquote>

<p>There was actually a TV show based on Truax called <em>Salvage 1</em> and
starring Andy Griffith in 1979.</p>

<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Truax">Wikipedia article on Robert Truax</a>.<br />
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nuW9bsp3Z2w">Salvage 1 Series Pilot on Youtube</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rocket Explodes]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/30/rocket-explodes/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-30T06:16:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/30/rocket-explodes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 20</a></p>

<p>From <a href="http://www.newscientist.com/article/dn26475-cargo-rocket-explosion-is-a-blow-for-commercial-space.html">New Scientist</a>.</p>

<p>The Orbital Sciences Antares rocket&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>&hellip;flying cargo to the International Space Station
exploded just 14 seconds after lift-off last night, creating a
spectacular fireball and shockwave as the fully fuelled rocket crashed
back down onto its launch pad.</p>

<p>No one was hurt when the uncrewed spacecraft was destroyed, but the
loss will dent attempts by the spacecraft&rsquo;s builder, Orbital Sciences
Corporation of Dulles, Virginia, to build confidence in its ability to
supply ISS cargo services to NASA.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fascinating Satellite Images]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/26/fascinating-satellite-images/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-26T11:18:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/26/fascinating-satellite-images</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 16</a></p>

<p>From <a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/striking-satellite-images-2014-10">Business Insider</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Lost Art of the Saturn V]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/03/01/the-lost-art-of-the-saturn-v/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-01T14:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/03/01/the-lost-art-of-the-saturn-v</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/saturn-v-cutaway.jpg"></p>

<p>Wow!  This is an amazing site and article by Amy Shira Teitel.</p>

<p><a href="http://amyshirateitel.com/2011/04/03/the-lost-art-of-the-saturn-v/">The Lost Art of the Saturn V</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Do We Know When Voyager Reaches Interstellar Space?]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/09/14/how-do-we-know-when-voyager-reaches-interstellar-space/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-14T19:44:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/09/14/how-do-we-know-when-voyager-reaches-interstellar-space</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/voyager_pia17462main_8k.jpg"></p>

<p><a href="http://www.jpl.nasa.gov/news/news.php?release=2013-278">From the Jet Propulsion Laboratory</a>.</p>

<blockquote><p>Whether and when NASA&rsquo;s Voyager 1 spacecraft, humankind&rsquo;s most distant
object, broke through to interstellar space, the space between stars,
has been a thorny issue. For the last year, claims have surfaced every
few months that Voyager 1 has &ldquo;left our solar system.&rdquo; Why has the
Voyager team held off from saying the craft reached interstellar space
until now?</p></blockquote>

<!-- More -->


<p>&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>Then on April 9, 2013, it happened: Voyager 1&rsquo;s plasma wave instrument
picked up local plasma oscillations. Scientists think they probably
stemmed from a burst of solar activity from a year before, a burst
that has become known as the St. Patrick&rsquo;s Day Solar Storms. The
oscillations increased in pitch through May 22 and indicated that
Voyager was moving into an increasingly dense region of plasma. This
plasma had the signatures of interstellar plasma, with a density more
than 40 times that observed by Voyager 2 in the heliosheath.</p>

<p>Gurnett and Kurth began going through the recent data and found a
fainter, lower-frequency set of oscillations from Oct. 23 to Nov. 27,
2012. When they extrapolated back, they deduced that Voyager had first
encountered this dense interstellar plasma in August 2012, consistent
with the sharp boundaries in the charged particle and magnetic field
data on August 25.</p>

<p>Stone called three meetings of the Voyager team. They had to decide
how to define the boundary between our solar bubble and interstellar
space and how to interpret all the data Voyager 1 had been sending
back. There was general agreement Voyager 1 was seeing interstellar
plasma, based on the results from Gurnett and Kurth, but the sun still
had influence. One persisting sign of solar influence, for example,
was the detection of outside particles hitting Voyager from some
directions more than others. In interstellar space, these particles
would be expected to hit Voyager uniformly from all directions.</p></blockquote>

<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/voyger_pia17046-640.jpg"></p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;In the end, there was general agreement that Voyager 1 was indeed
outside in interstellar space,&rdquo; Stone said. &ldquo;But that location comes
with some disclaimers &ndash; we&rsquo;re in a mixed, transitional region of
interstellar space. We don&rsquo;t know when we&rsquo;ll reach interstellar space
free from the influence of our solar bubble.&rdquo;</p>

<p>So, would the team say Voyager 1 has left the solar system? Not
exactly &ndash; and that&rsquo;s part of the confusion. Since the 1960s, most
scientists have defined our solar system as going out to the Oort
Cloud, where the comets that swing by our sun on long timescales
originate. That area is where the gravity of other stars begins to
dominate that of the sun. It will take about 300 years for Voyager 1
to reach the inner edge of the Oort Cloud and possibly about 30,000
years to fly beyond it. Informally, of course, &ldquo;solar system&rdquo;
typically means the planetary neighborhood around our sun. Because of
this ambiguity, the Voyager team has lately favored talking about
interstellar space, which is specifically the space between each
star&rsquo;s realm of plasma influence.</p></blockquote>

<p><em>Image credits: NASA/JPL-Caltech</em></p>

<h2>Other articles</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.universetoday.com/104717/its-official-voyager-1-is-now-in-interstellar-space/">It’s Official: Voyager 1 Is Now In Interstellar Space</a> in Universe Today</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
