<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: blogging | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/blogging/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2013-11-29T14:39:00-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Google Plus as a Blogging Platform]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/08/17/google-plus-as-a-blogging-platform/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-17T04:40:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/08/17/google-plus-as-a-blogging-platform</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/gplus_blogging.png"></p>

<p>Mike Elgan posts (on G+) &ldquo;Google+ is one of the 15 best blogging
platforms, according to <em>The Next Web</em>.&rdquo;</p>

<p>LOL!  What&rsquo;s funny about this statement is that I can&rsquo;t even think of
five blogging plaforms.  At least that are still relevant, e.g.,
leaving out Movable Type (which I really enjoyed) and LiveJournal.</p>

<p>Further, after looking at the article on <a href="http://thenextweb.com/apps/2013/08/16/best-blogging-services/">The Next Web</a>, I
think the above headline overstates their case.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/thenextweb_blogs.png"></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/thenextweb_gplus.png"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Leaping To A New Blogging Platform]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/06/08/leaping-to-a-new-blogging-platform/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-08T13:29:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/06/08/leaping-to-a-new-blogging-platform</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/octopress-logo.png"></p>

<p>Okay, it&rsquo;s apparently once again time to take the leap.  I&rsquo;m moving
Monolith149 Daily from Blogger, where it&rsquo;s lived since May of 2006.
Its new home is a combination of writing posts in Markdown on a local
machine, generating a static blog using Octopress, and publishing the
blog on Github Pages.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I&rsquo;ve enjoyed the convenience of editing in Blogger and posting on
Blogspot.  However, with Google&rsquo;s incessant and sometimes tone deaf
push toward Google Plus, and other concerns about my data there, I&rsquo;ve
felt a growing urge to make a change.</p>

<p>In spite of that, I&rsquo;m still an avid and nearly hourly user of Google&rsquo;s
vast supply of services and apps such as Gmail and documents.</p>

<h2>So Far</h2>

<p>Before the last move to Blogger in 2006, I was using Blosxom which was
also a text-file-based source system.  As I recall, Blosxom was a Perl
program that dynamically generated web pages on the fly from the text
sources.  It ran on Monolith, which was my desktop computer for a long
time, and was also my web server.  That&rsquo;s because this was in the &ldquo;old
days&rdquo; when the university didn&rsquo;t have a firewall and <em>all</em> of the
desktop computers were on the Internet.  That arrangement also
resulted in all you&rsquo;d expect to follow.</p>

<p>Blosxom began to bog down as the years and number of posts grew. It
also seemed wise then to move my personal blog to a place that didn&rsquo;t
belong to my employer.</p>

<p>Back in 2002 when I began blogging (I recently wrote about the
<a href="http://monolith149daily.blogspot.com/2011/09/nine-years-ago.html">ninth</a>
and
<a href="http://monolith149daily.blogspot.com/2012/12/ten-years-of-blogging.html">tenth</a>
anniversaries), I was writing the blogs on Blogger and keeping the
source there.  But I ftp-published them back to my desktop, Monolith,
where they were served from.</p>

<h2>A New Text Age</h2>

<p>Lately, there&rsquo;s been a lot of buzz from bloggers, and people who look
like bloggers, about Markdown. It&rsquo;s a simple text mark up language
created by John Gruber.  I finally dipped into Markdown a bit when I
began experimenting with Github.  From my point of view, it&rsquo;s nearly
the same as many wiki markup schemes that have been around for a long
time.  It&rsquo;s both very easy and familiar.</p>

<p>I miss some of the ability to do things like adjust text size, change
fonts, etc.  However, it seems to be a fair trade for a format that&rsquo;s
easy to move in the future.  Even in the worst case, Markdown is just
simple, readable text.  The source files themselves provide a useful
record.</p>

<h2>Octopress</h2>

<p>Then I somehow heard about Octopress.  At first I was a little put off
by the work required to install and set up yet another software
package with dependencies that had to be worked out.  It did require
fiddling around with Ruby versions on an Ubuntu 12.04 LTS system and
dealing with something called Gems and bundles.  I&rsquo;ve been happy
enough with Perl and Python over the years to never feel the need to
dive into Ruby.</p>

<p>Once it was all set up and working, it took more reading and
experimenting to get various customizations working.  For example, the
default fonts for article titles were way too big and heavy for my
taste.  It was actually quite easy to make those changes once I&rsquo;d
sorted it out.</p>

<h2>Publishing</h2>

<p>Finally, there was the question of where to publish.  There&rsquo;s Amazon
S3 which is excellent for putting up a static site.  However, there
was not an AWS tool for uploading and updating a hierarchy of files.
There are several external tools and I could certainly write my own
code, but I didn&rsquo;t want to go down those roads.</p>

<p>I briefly looked at Dropbox.  There are some reasonably
well-established services that will serve out a Dropbox folder as a
web site, making it a viable choice.</p>

<p>However, in the end I landed on an unexpected delight: Github Pages.
Octopress actually recommends Github Pages.  I had recently become
very comfortable with using Git and Github.  Github Pages is a
wonderful service that allows publishing a static web site for free.
They even have support for layout and content generation.</p>

<p>It was quite easy and straightforward to set up the Github repo and
before you&rsquo;d know it, I was able to add, commit and push the blog.</p>

<h2>Concerns</h2>

<p>The one thing that has worried me the most the seemingly heavier
lifting required to actually get posts up.  Would that add enough
friction to impede posting? Writing the text is easy, but then follow
the several steps required to publish.  Granted, Octopress actually
has some built-in automation for one-command deployment of new
content, but I haven&rsquo;t adopted its approach yet.  Actually, it can
probably be boiled down to one or two simple shell aliases.</p>

<p>And really, when I think about it, I had to do a lot of switching
between HTML and rich text modes in Blogger to write even a simple
post.  Adding an image to a blog entry was about the same amount of
work as Octopress requires.  So maybe there&rsquo;s not as much friction as
I&rsquo;d feared.</p>

<h2>Finally</h2>

<p>So, here I am, starting Chapter Four of my blogging life.  I&rsquo;ll
continue to write little tweet-length posts and post simple shared
links.  When it became clear a few years ago that Twitter severely
limited users' ability to retrieve an archive of their tweets, I moved
away from originating any important content on Twitter and focused
solely on blogging it.  From there, Feedburner echoed it to my Twitter
account.  Earlier this year, Twitter finally added the ability to
retrieve a complete archive of tweets.</p>

<p>There will inevitably be some style adjustments and changes and, who
knows, there may even be yet another leap sometime down the road.  You
can probably count on it.  When that time comes, it will be
interesting to see how long the investment in Markdown source holds
up.</p>

<h2>Resources</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://monolith149daily.blogspot.com/">Previous Monolith149 Daily</a></li>
<li><a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a></li>
<li><a href="http://blogger.com/">Blogger</a></li>
<li><a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/">Markdown and Daring Fireball</a></li>
<li><a href="http://blosxom.sourceforge.net/">Blosxom</a></li>
<li><a href="http://pages.github.com/">Github Pages</a></li>
<li><a href="https://blog.twitter.com/2012/your-twitter-archive">Your Twitter Archive</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/technology/future_tense/2013/04/life_without_google_when_my_account_was_suspended_i_felt_like_i_d_been_dumped.html">Slate article by Tienlon Ho</a></li>
</ul>


<p><em>Updated 10 Jun 2013 6:47</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
