<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: blogging | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/blogging/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2015-04-18T15:18:40-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[After Blogging for 30 Days]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/10/after-blogging-for-30-days/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-10T05:17:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/10/after-blogging-for-30-days</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well, It&rsquo;s now day 31 and I&rsquo;ve finished the <a href="/blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">30-day challenge</a> to blog for 30
days.  The original challenge that I read didn&rsquo;t include weekends but I
went ahead and blogged straight through since there&rsquo;s actually more
time to write on the weekend than during the week.</p>

<p>I did manage to put a post up every day with the exception of day 23.
I wrote the day 22 and 23 entries on day 22 using my Kindle HD Fire,
Draft and Dropbox and didn&rsquo;t actually post them until day 24.  I
didn&rsquo;t actually do any writing on day 23.  I&rsquo;ll leave it to the 30-day
blogging judges to decide how to count that.</p>

<p>Some posts were long, some were medium length, some had pictures and
links, some were only a link, a couple were basically just
&ldquo;re-tweets.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Reflecting on the experience I&rsquo;m amazed at how short 30 days is.  It
doesn&rsquo;t seem like there are 30+ posts and it felt like a much shorter
time.  But then, 30 days, months, years do seem to go by super-fast
lately.</p>

<p>I enjoyed the freedom of not hesitating to write the short,
tweet-length posts and then working on the longer ones when I had
something to say.  I didn&rsquo;t work hard to find pictures to add but only
used them when I felt they were appropriate or needed.  Just writing
words was okay and that freedom made it fun and doable.</p>

<p>The thing I liked the least about the experience was the quality of my
writing which I think is considerably decreased from what it used to
be.  I could have put more effort into better writing but I was just
getting some words down.  In essense, I was publishing maybe the
second draft of what I wrote, but not a &ldquo;final draft.&rdquo;  That was the
most dissatisfying part.  I got into the habit of writing but maybe
not writing well or at least better. Maybe that will be the next
challenge I take on, to write at least as well as I think I used to.</p>

<p>Another result of all of this blogging was a better work flow.  I
fixed my process by smoothing out lot of friction in the steps I take
to post.  I wrote a fully-automated script so I can locally publish
the blog (I actually do proof read entries there, spell check and see
how they look), and then push the update to public on Github with a
single command.  I fixed emacs to automatically go into text mode and
made some changes on Github to make pushing easier.</p>

<p>One of the lessons other bloggers shared as they were doing this
process was the appropriateness of the mid-length post.  That means
it&rsquo;s okay to write more than a tweet but less than a long essay.
That&rsquo;s part of the life-blood of journaling.  Sometimes you just pen a
brief entry but that&rsquo;s enough to stake out that day.  Being able to go
beyond 140 characters is a chief advantage that puts blogging above
tweeting while keeping the ability to write as little as desired.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve come to enjoy writing in Markdown even more.  It&rsquo;s simple to use
and, in the end, I have a completely readable and portable collection
of text files that aren&rsquo;t tied to a particular platform or site.  I
can take this site anywhere now.</p>

<p>One down side is that I&rsquo;m running up against the performance of
Octopress.  At this very point it takes 35 seconds of wall clock time
to generate the site.  That&rsquo;s not bad but it seems like a long wait in
computer &ldquo;waiting for a command to finish&rdquo; time.  I think I need to
look into breaking off the archives into a separate site or section so
they are generated independently.  Most of the archive, all of it
really, is static at this point and shouldn&rsquo;t need to be regenerated
for every post.  However, there would be some tricks in blending it in
to the main site, e.g., so that search covers the whole site including
archives.  It might be as simple as a different repo on Github and
posting it as a separate site with a different name but the exact same
look and feel.  There&rsquo;s more research, thinking and maybe
experimenting to do here.</p>

<p>So what next?  I&rsquo;m not going to focus on making sure I post something
every day.  I think I&rsquo;ll keep blogging more than I was for a while.
I&rsquo;m definitely going to take advantage of the freedom to blog anyway
way I wish, long or short, elaborate or trivially simple.  I&rsquo;m going
to read more blogs by other folks that have taken up the challenge and
try to benefit from their lessons learned.</p>

<p>When I started the 30 days, I brainstormed a nice long list of post
ideas in just a few minuts. After managing to cover a lot of them and
adding ideas through the month, amazingly, the list doesn&rsquo;t seem
any shorter.  There&rsquo;s still a lot to write about!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[More 30-day Blogging Takers]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/08/more-30-day-blogging-takers/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-08T23:41:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/08/more-30-day-blogging-takers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 29.1</a></p>

<p>Matt Cutts also has taken on the 30-day blogging challenge.  He&rsquo;s
doing it for the month of November.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.mattcutts.com/blog/30-day-challenge-write-every-day/">30 day challenge: writing every day</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Half Way]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/25/half-way/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-25T07:07:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/25/half-way</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 15.1</a></p>

<p>Well, I&rsquo;m half way to having blogged for 30 days straight.  It&rsquo;s
required keeping up with it but I&rsquo;ve enjoyed it so far.  The fact that
I&rsquo;ve thrown some re-tweets and link postings in there helps.  I like
the mid-length blogging ideas and those really fit my thinking.
Short, quick posts that say something you want to say are fine!</p>

<p>Some other takers of the 30 day challenge have been reflecting
mid-way.</p>

<p><a href="http://om.co/2014/10/24/swing-scratch/">Om Malik</a><br />
<a href="http://cdevroe.com/blog/10224/blogging-is-back">Colin Devroe</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Short Form Blogging]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/21/short-form-blogging/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-21T08:12:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/21/short-form-blogging</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 11.1</a></p>

<p>Gina Trapani&rsquo;s post on <a href="http://scribbling.net/2014/10/16/short-form-blogging/">Short Form Blogging</a> on Scribbling.net precisely
captures my own current approach to blogging almost perfectly.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Twelve Years]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/14/twelve-years/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-14T06:03:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/14/twelve-years</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/Sun_Ultra_5_front.jpg"></p>

<p>Day 4</p>

<p><em>&ldquo;Occasional reports on what in the world I’m doing. You can read here
to find out what I’ve been working on and how it’s going. There might
be clues about what I’m thinking. New things learned will also appear.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m really not going to make all of these posts about blogging, I
promise.  However, I thought I should note this blog is now in it&rsquo;s
12th year.  I always miss the anniversary but it was this past month.
The first post was on Mon 2002-09-16 00:29 -0400.</p>

<p>In the beginning the posts were nearly all work-related reports on
what I was working on.  Then I began to include other topics I found
interesting such as astronomy and computing.</p>

<p>The first posts were written on Blogger, then still owned by Pyra
Labs, co-founded by Ev Williams who later was a co-founder of Twitter.
Google eventually bought Blogger.  I wrote the posts on Blogger but used
it&rsquo;s ftp publishing feature to push the generated pages back to my
desktop workstation, Monolith.</p>

<p>Monolith had an Apache web server running on it, upgraded from the
original NCSA HTTP server software at some point.  The computer had
originally been a NeXTstation then later it&rsquo;s soul had been migrated
to a Sun SPARC 5 workstation.  By this time, when the blog began in
2002, I think it might have been upgraded to a Sun Ultra 5 but I don&rsquo;t
recall the models and timeline precisely.</p>

<p>From Blogger, I migrated to Bloxom, then back to Blogger, fully hosted
at Blogspot, then recently to Octopress.  The pre-Octopress blog is
still on-line.</p>

<p><a href="http://monolith149daily.blogspot.com/2011/09/nine-years-ago.html">Nine Years Ago</a><br />
<a href="http://monolith149daily.blogspot.com/2012/12/ten-years-of-blogging.html">Ten Years of Blogging</a></p>

<p><em>Image credit: <a href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Sun_Ultra_5_front.jpg">Thomas Kaiser</a> CC BY-SA 3.0</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
