<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: blogging | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/blogging/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2016-02-06T12:34:54-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Time To Catch Up]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/01/08/time-to-catch-up/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-08T21:20:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/01/08/time-to-catch-up</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Okay, it&rsquo;s time to catch up.  I haven&rsquo;t posted here since November but
I&rsquo;ve been stuffing links away in Evernote so it&rsquo;s time to empty some
of those out and post them, even if they&rsquo;re a few days or weeks old.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Blogging in Twitter Language]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/11/21/blogging-in-twitter-language/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-21T04:49:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/11/21/blogging-in-twitter-language</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There&rsquo;s one thing Twitter has done and that&rsquo;s change the language of
reading news and stories so I&rsquo;m going to try an experiment.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>Regardless of however things work out for Twitter it has had one
unmistakable effect on the way articles, essays, and other writing is
presented.  When you look at Facebook, Apple&rsquo;s News app, and almost
any site like Recode or The Verge, nearly everything looks like a
tweet.  You click on it to read the article.</p>

<p>Now, it&rsquo;s always the case that there&rsquo;s nothing new under the sun.
Headlines with snippets have been popular at least going back to the
80s, if memory serves and I&rsquo;m sure that, if I took the time to do the
research, I could find that story snippets are as old as news
publishing itself.  I believe I recall in the 80s when newspapers
started publishing a sort of index on page two of tweet-looking
headlines and snippets.  Magazines have done the same thing on their
index pages for a long time.</p>

<p>Still, the shift in the look of any story-collecting web site or, more
importantly, phone app has changed so that they all look strikingly
familiar.</p>

<p>So, at the risk of appearing as a trend follower, I&rsquo;m going to try
breaking my blog stories so that there&rsquo;s a shorter blurb on the main
page and you click to read the full story.</p>

<p>I guess there&rsquo;s a risk here when the blog post is mainly there to
share a link since you might have to click twice but maybe not.  Those
posts just won&rsquo;t have the &ldquo;Read More&rdquo; link but the actual story link
itself.  After all I can always do what I want here.  I can grow back
the main page piece as much as I want when I want.  That&rsquo;s part of
what&rsquo;s great about keeping your own blog.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Octopress Blogging: How Its Going]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/11/05/octopres-blogging-how-its-going/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-05T07:02:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/11/05/octopres-blogging-how-its-going</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well, it&rsquo;s been since 2013-06-08, a little less than 2 &frac12; years,
since I moved my blogging platform and workflow to Markdown &ndash;
Octopress &ndash; Github, with a Python program I wrote to handle most of
the process.  I guess I should also state explicitly that I&rsquo;m actually
writing in GNU Emacs.</p>

<p>For the most part I&rsquo;m really happy with the workflow and tools but I
still go through periods where I just don&rsquo;t blog much.  I often
collect links and ideas but never sit down and write about them or
even simply do the &ldquo;tweet-length&rdquo; post.  There are a few barriers to
my blogging and it seems to take something that pushes me over that
wall to get me started again.  Last year it was Gina Trapani writing
about the 30 day blogging challenge that was going around.  Today it&rsquo;s
Ihnatko&rsquo;s mention of getting back into it with his rediscovery of
MarsEdit which really simplified his workflow.</p>

<!-- More -->


<h2>Here are the good parts</h2>

<p>Writing in Emacs is great since that&rsquo;s my preferred editor.</p>

<p>My program-driven workflow is quite effective. I just run
&ldquo;blog_post.py&rdquo; with the proper arguments and it handles moving files
around and running the right programs and tools.</p>

<p>I like having all of my content in Markdown.  That was really one of
the goals in the first place, to have my writing in transportable,
somewhat long-living files that could be easily read even in their
original format.</p>

<p>The blog looks great though it is quite monochromatic and may be due
for an overhaul of some sort.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s important that I own and control all of my content.  I&rsquo;m not
posting it on someone else&rsquo;s blog site.  Okay, granted, I <em>am</em> posting it
on Github&rsquo;s site but the Markdown source remains on my own computer
under my control.</p>

<h2>Then the worst parts</h2>

<p>Right now my workflow is a three-phased affair.</p>

<ol>
<li>Write a post file in Markdown.</li>
<li>Generate the content and publish it on my local server for review.</li>
<li>Push to the public blog hosted on Github.</li>
</ol>


<p>The writing part is great but the generate phase, especially given the
current size of the blog what it is now with 154 posts including this
one, takes around 50 seconds.</p>

<p>One way to mitigate this is to split off a separate, static archive
blog with older posts.  I think taking it up through 2014 and letting
the &ldquo;live&rdquo; version begin with 2015 would do the trick.  With a link to
the old Archive on the main blog, it should be sort of seamless.  This
would affect searching some, though.</p>

<p>I have trouble writing the short posts since I have a tendcy to be
verbose.  I sit there, think more, and write more.  Then I have to
proof read the post, review the locally published version, go back
and fix errors, even include links (which I now put at the bottom),
and occasionally add a picture.</p>

<p>When posting a picture I check the rights and make sure that proper
credit is given.</p>

<p>So all of that amounts to what I might set out to do in maybe 10
minutes becomes an hour and and half of blogging.   Is that a bad
thing?  Maybe not, but it adds to the barrier.</p>

<p>Also, my blogging isn&rsquo;t portable.  If I&rsquo;m not at home where the server
is that I actually write the markdown on, then I can&rsquo;t blog.  Well, to
be fair, of course I can <em>write</em> if I&rsquo;m away from home but I can&rsquo;t
publish.</p>

<p>I could mitigate this if I moved the blogging onto a publicly
accessible machine but then I have the problem of backing up the
files, etc.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve started using Dropbox a little bit for writing files (another
blog post) and I suppose I could write my files there which would make
them accessible from anywhere.  Then, back on the ranch, I could do
the publishing phase.  After all, the blog is already public so having
it there on Dropbox shouldn&rsquo;t be that big a deal.</p>

<p>But then, writing a file in <em>any</em> place and pulling it in later isn&rsquo;t
that hard.</p>

<h2>Next Steps</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m at least going to look into splitting off the archive.  I&rsquo;ll start
the split-off blog and then later on I can migrate more posts onto it.
Maybe a good plact to split is a little more than a year back, say 1
&frac12; years?</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll think more about putting the files on Dropbox though I&rsquo;m not sure
there&rsquo;s a big push to do this since I can always move the files into
my source directory later if I&rsquo;m away from home.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Perfect Blogging Interface]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/11/05/perfect-blogging-interface/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-05T06:58:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/11/05/perfect-blogging-interface</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I like what Andy Ihnatko wrote in his post &ldquo;Life On MarsEdit&rdquo; about
his conception of the perfect blogging interface.</p>

<blockquote><p>What I really want is a system-wide hotkey. No matter where I am or
what I’m doing, tapping it causes a little note card window to pop
up. I type a few sentences, maybe click a Twitter-style icon button to
drop in a photo or paste in a link (which the app automatically grabs
from the frontmost browser window), click the “Post” button, and then
I’m back to what I was doing before I had this brilliant idea for a
quick post.</p></blockquote>

<p>Blogging as easy as tweeting.  That makes perfect sense.</p>

<p><a href="http://ihnatko.com/2015/11/01/life-on-marsedit/">Life On MarsEdit</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[More Short and Medium Length Blogging]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/11/05/more-short-and-medium-length-blogging/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-05T06:34:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/11/05/more-short-and-medium-length-blogging</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Okay, fine, Andy Ihnatko has me spun up again about blogging more with
his disucussion on this week&rsquo;s Macbreak Weekly about blogging more
again and rediscovering MarsEdit  He refers to Jason Snell&rsquo;s Six
Colors, John Gruber&rsquo;s Daring Fireball and Jim Dalrymple&rsquo;s The Loop.
Even Leo said he was doing the same thing on his rejuvenated Leoville.</p>

<p>Okay, I&rsquo;ll try kicking it up a notch, but maybe it&rsquo;s also time to
reflect on my setup with Markdown &ndash; Octopress &ndash; Github pages.</p>

<p><a href="https://twit.tv/shows/macbreak-weekly/episodes/479">Macbreak Weekly #479</a><br />
<a href="http://ihnatko.com/">Andy Ihnatko&rsquo;s Celestial Waste of Bandwidth</a><br />
<a href="https://sixcolors.com/">Six Colors</a><br />
<a href="http://www.loopinsight.com/">The Loop</a><br />
<a href="http://www.leoville.com/">Leoville</a><br />
<a href="http://daringfireball.net/">Daring Fireball</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
