<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: music | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/music/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2016-10-04T01:21:45-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[So Long Keith Emerson]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/03/11/so-long-keith-emerson/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-11T18:33:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/03/11/so-long-keith-emerson</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It was in about 1970 when my uncle brought some demo record LPs from a
DJ he knew.  I discovered among them the 1968 electronic Moog album
&ldquo;Switched on Bach.&rdquo;  Another album that I really loved listening to
was &ldquo;The Five Bridges Suite&rdquo; by The Nice.</p>

<p>A couple of years later, in high school, in 1972, my friend Dennis
introduced me to Emerson, Lake and Palmer and their album &ldquo;Trilogy.&rdquo;
At about the same time, my friend BJ  their first album, &ldquo;Emerson, Lake
and Palmer&rdquo; and I was as blown away.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>Progressive rock was blooming at the time.  The eclectic fusion of
classical, rock, jazz, blues and other music forms in long pieces,
sometimes in multiple movements, were made for long album cuts played
on FM radio The Atlanta station 96 Rock played a lot of progressive
rock in 1973-75.  With motifs of science fiction, fantasy, astronomy
and more, it was a perfect fit especially for the college listening
audience.  Bands like Yes, Pink Floyd, Genesis, and, often considered
by many the leader, Emerson, Lake and Palmer, were setting the pace
for this form of music.</p>

<p>It was years later that I finally realized the ELP line up was really
a traditional trio of keyboards, bass and drums.  Think of Vince
Guaraldi&rsquo;s jazz trio music for &ldquo;A Charlie Brown Christmas.&rdquo;  Often
ELP would transition into traditional jazz in just that format.</p>

<p>My favorite performance, that shows off the extreme range of their
playing, is &ldquo;Take A Pebble&rdquo; from a Belgian TV recording in 1971
(linked below), complete with a Moire projection that would make a
bridge science officer proud.  They were not a tight band, sometimes
lacking the precise virtuosity of a group like Chick Corea&rsquo;s Return To
Forever.  Sometimes it seemed like they didn&rsquo;t really like playing
together that much.  Still, their playing was inventive, talented, and
a joy to listen to.  This performance&rsquo;s rough edges and spontaneity
are part of what puts it at the top of my list.</p>

<p>Their music was ambitious, grand and rose high above the popular music
of the day.  Keith Emerson&rsquo;s stage antics were entertaining when I was
an adolescent but later I didn&rsquo;t care for them or for some the songs'
themes, but I sure was into the music.  That was what I enjoyed
listening to so much then and I still do today.  He introduced me to
composers like Mussorgsky, Aaron Copeland, and others the same way the
Allman Brothers led me to blues music.</p>

<p>ELP&rsquo;s first five albums stand as their main body of work, at least in
my view, but I liked the records that followed, particularly the
two-volume &ldquo;Works&rdquo; even though it was a mixture of pieces by a band
that was ending and solo pieces by its members.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t recall if it was in high school or as a freshman in college
that I made the connection for the first time between ELP and The
Nice&rsquo;s &ldquo;Five Bridges Suite,&rdquo; that album I enjoyed so much.  I went on
to become a fan of the early Nice music and collected several of their
records.  Even then Emerson was mixing Sibelius, Tchaikovsky, and Bach
with Bob Dylan and Coleman Hawkins, and performing live with a full
orchestra.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s surprisingly hard to say good bye to one of the great artists of
the time.</p>

<h2>Links</h2>

<p>Compare.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CBPbG1a6EP8">ELP &ndash; Take a Pebble &ndash; 1971</a></p>

<p><a href="https://youtu.be/7RSRoM_fc9I">The Nice &ndash; Hang on to a Dream &ndash; 1969</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rachel Flowers plays Trilogy (and Tarkus)]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/02/06/rachel-flowers-plays-trilogy/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-06T11:51:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/02/06/rachel-flowers-plays-trilogy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you&rsquo;re a fan of Emerson, Lake and Palmer, checkout Rachel Flowers
playing &ldquo;Fugue&rdquo; and &ldquo;The Endless Enigma (Part 2)&rdquo; starting at the
3m29s mark at NAMM 2016.</p>

<p>She&rsquo;s also famous for her rendition of &ldquo;Tarkus,&rdquo; the entire piece.  Of
course she finally got Keith Emerson&rsquo;s attention and was able to play
it on his Hammond C3 and original Moog.</p>

<p><a href="https://youtu.be/-mzcED3vJ3g">NAMM 2016 Nord Piano 3 Performance with Rachel Flowers</a><br />
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HrXuvkj5Vi0">Rachel Flowers-Tarkus (complete)-solo piano</a><br />
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FLT3Cb96-Mk">Rachel Flowers &ndash; Tarkus with Emerson&rsquo;s Modular Moog</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meeblip Synthesizer]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/11/21/meeblip-synthesizer/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-21T14:42:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/11/21/meeblip-synthesizer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Meeblip is a nifty little synthesizer with MIDI input.  If memory
serves it seems to have a set of oscillators, filters and LFO that&rsquo;s
about the same as the original Mini Moog.</p>

<p><a href="http://meeblip.com/">meeblip.com</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
