<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: apple | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/apple/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2017-02-06T07:33:20-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Counterfeit Apple Cables from Amazon]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/23/counterfeit-apple-cables-from-amazon/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-23T07:11:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/23/counterfeit-apple-cables-from-amazon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is why I only buy Lightning cables, chargers and batteries for
Apple products from the Apple Store.  It&rsquo;s just too risky to buy them
anywhere else.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>It&rsquo;s been known for a long time that cheaply made Lithium Ion
batteries are very dangerous and will short, catch fire and burn.  Now
Samsung has made this abundantly clear.</p>

<p>Ben Lovejoy of <em>9to5 Mac</em> writes &ldquo;More than 90% of &lsquo;genuine&rsquo; Apple
chargers &amp; cables sold on Amazon are fake, says Apple.&rdquo;</p>

<blockquote><p>There’s no shortage of third-party chargers and cables sold for Apple
equipment, some of them claiming to be the genuine article, but Apple
has found that even Amazon has been selling counterfeit products
labelled as the real thing. The products concerned were sold by Amazon
directly, and not by a third-party Marketplace seller.</p>

<p>The items have now been removed from sale, and Apple is suing the
company that made them …</p></blockquote>

<p>Amazon responded.</p>

<blockquote><p>Amazon responded, stating that the company ‘has zero tolerance for the
sale of counterfeits on our site.  We work closely with manufacturers
and brands, and pursue wrongdoers aggressively.’</p>

<p>Given the number of fake Apple products available, we always urge
caution where the price is significantly lower than the official
price. This is especially true in the case of MagSafe power supplies,
where any price lower than available from authorized resellers is an
immediate warning flag.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="https://9to5mac.com/2016/10/19/amazon-fake-apple-chargers-cables/">Article at 9to5 Mac</a><br />
<a href="http://www.patentlyapple.com/patently-apple/2016/10/apple-sues-mobile-star-for-selling-counterfeit-power-adapters-and-charging-cables-through-amazon.html">Patently Apple</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[IOS 10 Upgrade]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/10/ios-10-upgrade/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-10T00:22:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/10/ios-10-upgrade</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s upgrade week for IOS.  I finally decided to take the plunge and
upgrade IOS 9 to IOS 10 on my iPhone 6S.  Usually I wait until about
the second minor update has come out and we&rsquo;re now at 10.0.2 as of
late last week, so Sunday night was the night.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>Even though the initial problems with over-the-air upgrades was
solved, I&rsquo;m still sticking with using iTunes on my desktop Mac Mini to
do the upgrade.  I grabbed my charging cable, plugged the phone into
the computer, started up iTunes because it&rsquo;s configured not to start
automatically, and first went to do a back up.</p>

<h2>Backup and Download</h2>

<p>Starting at about 22:35, I did an encrypted backup which said it was
taking about 10 minutes but that last 10 seconds seemed to take an
additional five minutes or so.  The encrypted back up will grab the
key chains and such.</p>

<p>From there I clicked the button to proceed with the 10.0.2 install and
it began the download to my computer.  This was the most uncomfortable
part because there&rsquo;s no progress bar or anything to really indicate
it&rsquo;s working.  I was monitoring the network traffic with Activity
Monitor and could see the actual packet rates as it downloaded, but I
would have preferred to have more feedback.</p>

<p>The downloading seemed to finally finish at about 23:40.  I just
happened to look up and notice the message in iTunes that said it was
downloading had changed to click Upgrade to begin the upgrade.</p>

<h2>Install</h2>

<p>The upgrade was much quicker and the progress bars appeared on the
phone as usual.  After only about 14 minutes at 23:54 the phone went
dark for quite a few seconds.  Again I wondered if all was well but
the white reboot screen with the black apple finally appeared.  There
was another progress bar and then I was logging in with my pass code
on the phone at 23:56.</p>

<p>iTunes then popped up a box saying there was an upgrade from the
carrier so I clicked that button and it quickly and silently installed
with no indication that anything happened from the phone itself.</p>

<p>By about midnight I was done.  I fooled around with the phone for
another 15 minutes or so, moved the newly appeared Home app into a
folder, and it was done.</p>

<h2>Post Install</h2>

<p>I just looked at things briefly. The lock screen, swipe-up screen and
the notifications screen are all different.  The new buttons in
Messages were there but it was too late to try any of that.  Also the
wake-up, unlock process is different.  So far it&rsquo;s a little confusing
in the sense that I&rsquo;m not sure what&rsquo;s different.  You push the home
button to unlock the screen which is what I thought I used to do.</p>

<p>If there&rsquo;s anything else interesting enough to follow up on I&rsquo;ll
report back later.</p>

<h2>References</h2>

<p>From iMore <a href="http://m.imore.com/ios-10">iOS 10 review: Cleaner, cleverer, and more convenient</a><br />
From Song-a-Day Jonathon Mann <a href="https://youtu.be/0heNVPPEy24">Video</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Latest iPhone Home Screen]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/25/latest-iphone-home-screen/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-25T16:46:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/09/25/latest-iphone-home-screen</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/20160926.0559.iPhone_Homescreen.png"></p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s the most recent image of my iPhone home screen as it continues
to evolve.  I think the most recent, previous image was this one.</p>

<p><a href="/blog/2014/11/09/ios-8-dot-1/">IOS 8.1</a></p>

<!-- More -->


<h2>Vs. the Old Screen</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/20141109_iPhone.jpg"></p>

<p>Instapaper is out.  I still use it on the desktop sometime but, since
I switched to Safari (yep), it has reading mode which is easy and
basically does the same thing.</p>

<p>I really like Read Quick and I&rsquo;m a fan of Clayton and Natalie Morris,
at least when they&rsquo;re on Twit.tv podcasts.  It&rsquo;s a neat idea and it
actually works, but I just wasn&rsquo;t using it.  When I&rsquo;m commuting
(driving) and at other times I&rsquo;m more often listening than reading.  I
just stopped using it very much.</p>

<p>The dreaded Facebook has arrived.  Yeah.  I finally decided to bite
the bullet and try using Facebook for news as well as family goings on
so I listened to Robert Scoble explain to Leo Laporte how to tune
Facebook&rsquo;s news feed, groups, etc.  I&rsquo;ve been using it since February.</p>

<p>I just removed Evernote and put Byword there a few minutes ago.  I&rsquo;m a
fan of Evernote but they seem to be struggling (as the press puts it)
and I decided it was a good time to move another one of my data sinks
to the text-Markdown world.  So now I write notes using Drafts, save
them to Dropbox (where they are titled and formatted) and access them
using various Markdown formatters.  The formatter that allows both
previewing the Markdown but also editing the notes within Dropbox is
Byword.  On the Mac desktop I use Marked for previewing and, of
course, just Emacs in a terminal window to edit.  This has been
working surprisingly well.  The only thing missing right now is that
Byword doesn&rsquo;t render included images.  There are some competing
standards between apps on how that&rsquo;s done, i.e., how images are
included.  There is Multi-markdown and I think it has a standard way,
but Byword doesn&rsquo;t seem to use it.  I&rsquo;m not sure I&rsquo;ve done all of the
required homework on that one, though.</p>

<p>I still have my Evernote account and it&rsquo;s still on my phone, but just
not on the home screen.  I also exported my notes and wrote an XML
parser (well, I used the Python pre-existing XML library) to un-XML
them.</p>

<p>Drafts is a wonderful app I&rsquo;ve been using for a while.  As everyone
that talks about it says, it&rsquo;s just for entering text.  It opens super
fast and it&rsquo;s ready for you just to type.  I have it set up to take
notes and save them to Dropbox with the formatting described above.
It&rsquo;s where my notes went, even when I was using Evernote.  From other
apps' Share sheets, I can send things to Drafts so it basically
connects all of my apps together.</p>

<p>Finally, Safari.  Chrome just keeps bloating in various ways and I
heard that Safari handled battery life on the iPhone in a much better
way.  That makes sense.  It seems secure enough (but note the most
recent &ldquo;pwn&rdquo; (however you spell it) conference where Chrome withstood
and Safari fell two or three times.  I tried switching to Safari quite
a few months ago, both on the phone and desktop, and I&rsquo;ve been using
it ever since.  There are some Google apps that Chrome handles better,
mainly their finance stock charts, but usually Safari is fine.  Chrome
is still on my phone and I still use it at work.  I wouldn&rsquo;t argue
that Safari is better (except for the memory footprint, maybe faster
and with better battery management where I <em>would</em> argue it&rsquo;s better),
but it&rsquo;s seemed good enough so far.</p>

<h2>References</h2>

<p><a href="/blog/2014/11/09/ios-8-dot-1/">IOS 8.1</a><br />
<a href="/blog/2016/02/06/tuning-facebook/">Tuning Facebook</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Upgrade to Mac OS X 10.11]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/11/17/upgrade-to-mac-os-x-10-dot-11/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-17T08:55:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/11/17/upgrade-to-mac-os-x-10-dot-11</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve finally upgraded to Mac OS X 10.11 at home.  There&rsquo;s really not
much to say so far.  The only new/changed feature I really see and use
is Mission Control.  Ohter than that it&rsquo;s pretty much business as
usual.</p>

<p>The process went quite smoothly.  I started the download and left it
unattended.  Then I returned later and started the install and left it
running unattended.  Note that I usually never leave an upgrade
running but they did take a few minutes and I had other things to do
including even being out of the house for a while.</p>

<p>When I came back and the new login screen was presented I logged in
with no trouble and only had to enter the Apple id for iCloud.</p>

<p>There may be features I&rsquo;m using that are new or changed and I haven&rsquo;t
used them enough in the past so I&rsquo;m unaware of the differences.</p>

<p>I hear that Notes has become quite good but I&rsquo;m sticking with Evernote
and Drafts on my phone.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Is OS X Yosemite 10.10 is Safe Without Anti Virus?]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/03/20/is-os-x-yosemite-10-dot-10-is-safe-without-anti-virus/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-20T05:11:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/03/20/is-os-x-yosemite-10-dot-10-is-safe-without-anti-virus</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the Apple Support Communities, Linc Davis gives an excellent
answer to this question with a summary of the built-in security
features of OS X 10.10 and the additional precautions you should take.</p>

<blockquote><p>All versions of OS X since 10.6.7 have been able to detect known
Mac malware in downloaded files, and to block insecure web
plugins. This feature is transparent to the user. Internally Apple
calls it &ldquo;XProtect.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>Starting with OS X 10.7.5, there has been a second layer of
built-in malware protection, designated &ldquo;Gatekeeper&rdquo; by Apple. By
default, applications and Installer packages downloaded from the
network will only run if they&rsquo;re digitally signed by a developer with
a certificate issued by Apple. Software certified in this way hasn&rsquo;t
necessarily been tested by Apple, but you can be reasonably sure that
it hasn&rsquo;t been modified by anyone other than the developer. His
identity is known to Apple, so he could be held legally responsible if
he distributed malware. That may not mean much if the developer lives
in a country with a weak legal system (see below.)</p></blockquote>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>Starting with OS X 10.8.3, a third layer of protection has been
added: a &ldquo;Malware Removal Tool&rdquo; (MRT). MRT runs automatically in the
background when you update the OS. It checks for, and removes, malware
that may have evaded the other protections via a Java exploit (see
below.) MRT also runs when you install or update the Apple-supplied
Java runtime (but not the Oracle runtime.) Like XProtect, MRT is
effective against known threats, but not against unknown ones. It
notifies you if it finds malware, but otherwise there&rsquo;s no user
interface to MRT.</p></blockquote>

<p>His answer is the third one down.</p>

<p><a href="https://discussions.apple.com/thread/6624843">Is OS X Yosemite 10.10 is safe without anti virus?</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
