<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: apple | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/apple/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2014-12-10T08:03:11-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Warning: Don't Lose Your Apple ID Recovery Key]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/12/10/apple-id-recovery-key/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-10T07:51:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/12/10/apple-id-recovery-key</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Setting up two-factor authentication is a good idea, but it&rsquo;s
important to carefully save your recovery key in a safe place where
you won&rsquo;t lose it.</p>

<p>This story by Owen Williams makes this point clear.</p>

<p><a href="http://thenextweb.com/apple/2014/12/08/lost-apple-id-learnt-hard-way-careful-two-factor-authentication/">From The Next Web, The dark side of Apple’s two-factor authentication</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[IOS Reliable Updates]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/10/ios-reliable-updates/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-10T06:42:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/10/ios-reliable-updates</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are two key reasons that I&rsquo;m overjoyed to have made the switch
from Android to IOS and the iPhone.</p>

<p>One is the reliability of OS updates.  There&rsquo;s no worrying about
pure-Google vs. vendor-imposed-UI and junk apps. There&rsquo;s no waiting
for a vendor to either roll out an update or, more likely, just force
you to buy a new phone or wait for your cycle to end to get a new
phone.</p>

<p>The IOS updates are (so far) annual, universal and hassle
free.  And by hassel free I&rsquo;m referring to the above issues.  It&rsquo;s
granted there have been hiccups and bugs, but usually they are
resolved in a reasonable time.  I try to be cautious and wait for a
minor update or to before diving in.  Thus, I skipped 8.0 and waited
for 8.1.</p>

<p>The other joy is from the pictures the iPhones make.  There are
Android phones with better camera specs on paper, and yet, the photos
are often just not up to par.  My Galaxy Nexus made images that ranged
from okay to terrible.  When I go back and look at them now, they look
even worse than I realized.  I know other people disagree but I&rsquo;m
firmly in the camp: There&rsquo;s no contest here.</p>

<p>So, that makes two items removed from the list of things to have to
deal with.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[IOS 8.1]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/09/ios-8-dot-1/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-09T21:53:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/09/ios-8-dot-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/20141109_iPhone.jpg"></p>

<p><a href="/blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 30</a></p>

<p>Today I upgraded to IOS 8.1 with no trouble and it&rsquo;s working well so
far.</p>

<p>I am one of those users who doesn&rsquo;t have the 5-GB or so of space on my
iPhone to do an over-the-air upgrade.  In spite of that, you can do an
upgrade without needing the space if you connect your iPhone to your
Mac (or Windows?) running iTunes and use iTunes to do the upgrade.  It
does the downloading and expansion of files on your desktop machine
then installs the upgrade over the USB cable.</p>

<p>The upgrade/install went without any trouble and it took almost
exactly 36 minutes it predicted.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve not used it too much.  So far, all the apps look and work the
same as in IOS 7.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Mac Mini, iPad, and More]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/17/new-mac-mini/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-17T07:50:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/17/new-mac-mini</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 7</a></p>

<p>From Jason Snell at his new site, Six Colors, &ldquo;<a href="http://sixcolors.com/post/2014/10/apples-ipadmac-event-first-thoughts/">Apple’s iPad/Mac event: First thoughts</a>.&rdquo;</p>

<p>From <a href="http://www.theverge.com/2014/10/16/6989443/apple-ipad-mac-event-8-most-important-things">The Verge, &ldquo;The 8 most important announcements from the Apple iPad and Mac event&rdquo;</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[iPhone After Eight Months]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/06/20/iphone-after-eight-months/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-20T06:17:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/06/20/iphone-after-eight-months</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/20140620_iphone.png"></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s now been eight months since I switched to the iPhone in October
2012.  The honeymoon is over and I&rsquo;ve been chewing on the green grass
for a while.  I can say I&rsquo;m just as happy and pleased with the the 5C
as I was when it was new, maybe even more.</p>

<p>It does everything I need or want it to do.  I have a nice set of apps
I use daily, a simulation and a game here or there, and generally I
can find just about anything I need in an app and it all works fine.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m still using the Gmail and the Google Maps apps for email, maps and
navigation.  Amazon cloud player was just updated and is still my
primary music player.  Netflix works fine but I typically use the
Youtube app for watching videos.</p>

<p>Apple&rsquo;s iMessage works great for texting with images and video with
the rest of the family and we all have iPhones at this point.</p>

<p>The camera continues to make great pictures, as expected.</p>

<p>Here are some of the most recent apps of significance I&rsquo;ve added.
Loom was bought by Dropbox who introduced an app called Carousel, so
I&rsquo;m not using it to automatically upload and archive photos.  Carousel
is nice as an app but there doesn&rsquo;t seem to be a correspondingly nice
web interface other then a plain Dropbox folder with a <em>lot</em> of image
files in it.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not a fan of Facebook.  In fact I don&rsquo;t like it much at all.
However, I have to say that Paper is nicely done, beautiful in some
ways, but a little quirky sometimes.  I like it many times better than
the regular Facebook interface because it&rsquo;s fun to use, but I ignore
the news feed and those other screens.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve become interested in trains lately and Trainz Driver is a fun
simulator.</p>

<p>If you compare the current image of my home screen here to the image I
<a href="http:/m149daily-blog/blog/2013/10/07/transition-to-the-iphone/">posted back in October 2012</a>, you can see that it hasn&rsquo;t changed much.
That&rsquo;s screen one and I only use three screens of apps that are about
&frac12; to 2/3 full.</p>

<p><em>Image: my current iPhone screen one.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
