<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: apple | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/apple/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2016-02-06T12:34:54-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Upgrade to Mac OS X 10.11]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/11/17/upgrade-to-mac-os-x-10-dot-11/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-17T08:55:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/11/17/upgrade-to-mac-os-x-10-dot-11</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve finally upgraded to Mac OS X 10.11 at home.  There&rsquo;s really not
much to say so far.  The only new/changed feature I really see and use
is Mission Control.  Ohter than that it&rsquo;s pretty much business as
usual.</p>

<p>The process went quite smoothly.  I started the download and left it
unattended.  Then I returned later and started the install and left it
running unattended.  Note that I usually never leave an upgrade
running but they did take a few minutes and I had other things to do
including even being out of the house for a while.</p>

<p>When I came back and the new login screen was presented I logged in
with no trouble and only had to enter the Apple id for iCloud.</p>

<p>There may be features I&rsquo;m using that are new or changed and I haven&rsquo;t
used them enough in the past so I&rsquo;m unaware of the differences.</p>

<p>I hear that Notes has become quite good but I&rsquo;m sticking with Evernote
and Drafts on my phone.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Is OS X Yosemite 10.10 is Safe Without Anti Virus?]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/03/20/is-os-x-yosemite-10-dot-10-is-safe-without-anti-virus/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-20T05:11:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/03/20/is-os-x-yosemite-10-dot-10-is-safe-without-anti-virus</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the Apple Support Communities, Linc Davis gives an excellent
answer to this question with a summary of the built-in security
features of OS X 10.10 and the additional precautions you should take.</p>

<blockquote><p>All versions of OS X since 10.6.7 have been able to detect known
Mac malware in downloaded files, and to block insecure web
plugins. This feature is transparent to the user. Internally Apple
calls it &ldquo;XProtect.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>Starting with OS X 10.7.5, there has been a second layer of
built-in malware protection, designated &ldquo;Gatekeeper&rdquo; by Apple. By
default, applications and Installer packages downloaded from the
network will only run if they&rsquo;re digitally signed by a developer with
a certificate issued by Apple. Software certified in this way hasn&rsquo;t
necessarily been tested by Apple, but you can be reasonably sure that
it hasn&rsquo;t been modified by anyone other than the developer. His
identity is known to Apple, so he could be held legally responsible if
he distributed malware. That may not mean much if the developer lives
in a country with a weak legal system (see below.)</p></blockquote>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>Starting with OS X 10.8.3, a third layer of protection has been
added: a &ldquo;Malware Removal Tool&rdquo; (MRT). MRT runs automatically in the
background when you update the OS. It checks for, and removes, malware
that may have evaded the other protections via a Java exploit (see
below.) MRT also runs when you install or update the Apple-supplied
Java runtime (but not the Oracle runtime.) Like XProtect, MRT is
effective against known threats, but not against unknown ones. It
notifies you if it finds malware, but otherwise there&rsquo;s no user
interface to MRT.</p></blockquote>

<p>His answer is the third one down.</p>

<p><a href="https://discussions.apple.com/thread/6624843">Is OS X Yosemite 10.10 is safe without anti virus?</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Siracusa on Swift]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/12/20/siracusa-on-swift/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-20T13:05:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/12/20/siracusa-on-swift</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>John Siracusa&rsquo;s review of each OS X version are legendary, but the
10.10 article has a nice dive down into some of the details of the new
Swift language and how it&rsquo;s compiled.  There are some impressive
features here.</p>

<p><a href="http://arstechnica.com/apple/2014/10/os-x-10-10/21/#swift">OS X 10.10 Yosemite: The Ars Technica Review, Swift</a><br />
<a href="https://developer.apple.com/swift/">Introducing Swift at Apple Developer</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Warning: Don't Lose Your Apple ID Recovery Key]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/12/10/apple-id-recovery-key/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-10T07:51:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/12/10/apple-id-recovery-key</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Setting up two-factor authentication is a good idea, but it&rsquo;s
important to carefully save your recovery key in a safe place where
you won&rsquo;t lose it.</p>

<p>This story by Owen Williams makes this point clear.</p>

<p><a href="http://thenextweb.com/apple/2014/12/08/lost-apple-id-learnt-hard-way-careful-two-factor-authentication/">From The Next Web, The dark side of Apple’s two-factor authentication</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[IOS Reliable Updates]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/10/ios-reliable-updates/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-10T06:42:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/10/ios-reliable-updates</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are two key reasons that I&rsquo;m overjoyed to have made the switch
from Android to IOS and the iPhone.</p>

<p>One is the reliability of OS updates.  There&rsquo;s no worrying about
pure-Google vs. vendor-imposed-UI and junk apps. There&rsquo;s no waiting
for a vendor to either roll out an update or, more likely, just force
you to buy a new phone or wait for your cycle to end to get a new
phone.</p>

<p>The IOS updates are (so far) annual, universal and hassle
free.  And by hassel free I&rsquo;m referring to the above issues.  It&rsquo;s
granted there have been hiccups and bugs, but usually they are
resolved in a reasonable time.  I try to be cautious and wait for a
minor update or to before diving in.  Thus, I skipped 8.0 and waited
for 8.1.</p>

<p>The other joy is from the pictures the iPhones make.  There are
Android phones with better camera specs on paper, and yet, the photos
are often just not up to par.  My Galaxy Nexus made images that ranged
from okay to terrible.  When I go back and look at them now, they look
even worse than I realized.  I know other people disagree but I&rsquo;m
firmly in the camp: There&rsquo;s no contest here.</p>

<p>So, that makes two items removed from the list of things to have to
deal with.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
