<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: computing | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/computing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2016-11-01T00:31:56-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rowhammer]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/01/rowhammer/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-01T00:18:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/01/rowhammer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Rowhammer is a sophisticated, clever and dangerous way to attack
computers and Android phones.  Dan Goodin reports in <em>Ars Technica.</em></p>

<!-- More -->


<blockquote><p>Researchers have devised an attack that gains unfettered &ldquo;root&rdquo; access
to a large number of Android phones, exploiting a relatively new type
of bug that allows adversaries to manipulate data stored in memory
chips.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://arstechnica.com/security/2016/10/using-rowhammer-bitflips-to-root-android-phones-is-now-a-thing/">Using Rowhammer bitflips to root Android phones is now a thing</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Email Phishing Attack]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/01/email-phishing-attack/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-01T00:10:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/01/email-phishing-attack</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well, in my earlier post on security tips I mentioned links in email.
According to an article in <em>Business Insider</em>, that&rsquo;s exactly how John
Podesta&rsquo;s account was compromised.</p>

<!-- More -->


<blockquote><p>Simply put: Rather than clicking a legitimate link from Google, he
apparently clicked through to a fake website run by hackers. When he
entered his account information, he handed over the keys to his
Gmail.</p></blockquote>

<p>This article by Ben Gilbert goes into some detail about how this was
done.  It was an easy effort by the attacker and could have been
avoided with a bit more care on the part of the user.  He even did the
right thing in reporting it to his IT support but still clicked the
dangerous link in the email.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/hillary-clinton-campaign-john-podesta-got-hacked-by-phishing-2016-10">Hillary Clinton&rsquo;s campaign got hacked by falling for the oldest trick
in the book</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What's going on inside Lithium Ion Batteries?]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/23/whats-going-on-inside-lithium-ion-batteries/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-23T07:32:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/23/whats-going-on-inside-lithium-ion-batteries</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Steve Gibson from Security Now provided two excellent sources this
week explaining what&rsquo;s happening when lithium ion batteries fail.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>From Paul O’Shea, Editor, <em>Power Electronics News</em> interviewing Nadim
Maluf, CEO of Qnovo, and Robert Nalesnik, VP of Marketing for Qnovo.</p>

<blockquote><p>Now, let’s examine one particular manufacturing defect in which a
slight misalignment between the anode and cathode occurs during the
assembly process. The same structure as above now has the anode layer
shifted slightly to the right. At the misaligned edge, the requisite
overlap of the anode relative to the cathode is now diminished or even
possibly eliminated. The anode/cathode ratio at this spot drops below
the requisite limit for ensuring safety. The result is the onset of
lithium metal at this edge. The lithium metal forms on the anode
edge. As the lithium metal grows in size and thickness, it ultimately
punctures the separator and causes an electrical short between the
anode and cathode. Boom! There is a catastrophic failure.</p>

<p>The tolerance requirements in the manufacturing of lithium-ion
batteries have risen sharply with increasing energy density. Short of
using new materials (which still do not exist in commercial
deployment), increasing the energy density means reducing all the
extra space inside the battery that is not made of anode and cathode
materials. These are the only two materials that store energy;
n> everything else is just overhead. They are still needed for other
functions and safety, but they do not contribute to storing electrical
charge. Therefore, battery designers keep reducing this overhead and,
in the process, make the manufacturing tolerances even tighter. That
is a recipe for many disasters to come unless we start adding a lot
more intelligence to the battery to avoid and mitigate these
undesired situations.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.powerelectronicsnews.com/technology/pushing-to-the-very-edge-of-safe-li-ion-charging">Pushing to the very edge of safe Li-ion charging</a><br /></p>

<p>From the Qnovo blog.</p>

<p><a href="http://qnovo.com/104-perils-4-4-volts/">104. The Perils of 4.4 Volts</a><br />
<a href="http://qnovo.com/103-real-science-behind-exploding-batteries/">103. The Real Science Behind Battery Safety</a><br />
<a href="http://qnovo.com/102-easy-not-right-pick-samsung/">102. It’s Easy, but Not Right, to Pick on Samsung</a><br />
<a href="http://qnovo.com/101-making-sense-100-kwh/">101. Making Sense of 100 kWh</a><br />
<a href="http://qnovo.com/100-state-lithium-ion-battery/">100. The State of the Lithium Ion Battery</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Counterfeit Apple Cables from Amazon]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/23/counterfeit-apple-cables-from-amazon/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-23T07:11:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/23/counterfeit-apple-cables-from-amazon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is why I only buy Lightning cables, chargers and batteries for
Apple products from the Apple Store.  It&rsquo;s just too risky to buy them
anywhere else.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>It&rsquo;s been known for a long time that cheaply made Lithium Ion
batteries are very dangerous and will short, catch fire and burn.  Now
Samsung has made this abundantly clear.</p>

<p>Ben Lovejoy of <em>9to5 Mac</em> writes &ldquo;More than 90% of &lsquo;genuine&rsquo; Apple
chargers &amp; cables sold on Amazon are fake, says Apple.&rdquo;</p>

<blockquote><p>There’s no shortage of third-party chargers and cables sold for Apple
equipment, some of them claiming to be the genuine article, but Apple
has found that even Amazon has been selling counterfeit products
labelled as the real thing. The products concerned were sold by Amazon
directly, and not by a third-party Marketplace seller.</p>

<p>The items have now been removed from sale, and Apple is suing the
company that made them …</p></blockquote>

<p>Amazon responded.</p>

<blockquote><p>Amazon responded, stating that the company ‘has zero tolerance for the
sale of counterfeits on our site.  We work closely with manufacturers
and brands, and pursue wrongdoers aggressively.’</p>

<p>Given the number of fake Apple products available, we always urge
caution where the price is significantly lower than the official
price. This is especially true in the case of MagSafe power supplies,
where any price lower than available from authorized resellers is an
immediate warning flag.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="https://9to5mac.com/2016/10/19/amazon-fake-apple-chargers-cables/">Article at 9to5 Mac</a><br />
<a href="http://www.patentlyapple.com/patently-apple/2016/10/apple-sues-mobile-star-for-selling-counterfeit-power-adapters-and-charging-cables-through-amazon.html">Patently Apple</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Security Basics]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/16/security-tips/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-16T15:40:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/16/security-tips</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The information world is a dangerous place these days.  You can lose
everything in an instant.  There&rsquo;s more at stake.  The biggest one is
probably your personal and family pictures.  The next is personal
financial and other important information, documents, etc.  I don&rsquo;t
know if it&rsquo;s any more dangerous but more of us have more important
information stored on our computers and other devices.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s my own list of the basics.  There&rsquo;s nothing original here.  You
should hear about the same thing from any security or IT professional.</p>

<!-- More -->


<h2>Summary</h2>

<ul>
<li>Don&rsquo;t open links and attachments in email, messages</li>
<li>Keep systems and apps, everything, updated</li>
<li>Keep Internet browsing on Main Street</li>
<li>Make backups, 3, 2, 1 (three copies, two media, one off site)</li>
<li>Use Google Chrome</li>
<li>Use Gmail</li>
<li>Use a password manager like LastPass or 1Password</li>
<li>Never install something you weren&rsquo;t looking for</li>
</ul>


<h2>The Basics</h2>

<h3>Don&rsquo;t open links and attachments in email, messages</h3>

<p>This is one of the biggest threats today.  You click a link and
download an attachment and you&rsquo;ve given malware, an attacking computer
program, access to <em>your</em> computer.  Fortunately most of our systems
today are secure enough that they can&rsquo;t be compromised unless you take
the action yourself so the game is to trick you into running the
evil code.  Sending you email that looks like a legitimate, important
message from your bank or the IRS, or maybe telling you you&rsquo;ve won
something or have an important message, maybe an unpaid bill.</p>

<p>If the message is from a bank or some institution or business, see if
you can get to the same information by going to their web site on your
own, not by clicking in the email, and finding what they&rsquo;re talking
about.  If nothing else, call them.</p>

<p>If it&rsquo;s from a family member, text them or call them and ask if they
sent it to you and if they&rsquo;re sure it&rsquo;s okay.</p>

<p>Many of the largest company security breaches in recent news have been
the result of finally tricking an employee to click on something in an
email message.</p>

<h3>Keep systems and apps, everything, updated</h3>

<p>All software and, in fact, most hardware, is updated regularly.  These
updates are important.  Many people are working hard to find and fix
bugs that could expose you to attack.   On Windows, Mac OS, and Linux,
you should turn on automatic updates so your system is updated on a
regular basis.</p>

<h3>Keep Internet browsing on Main Street</h3>

<p>This means stick to well known and reputable sites: people,
businesses, destinations.  Don&rsquo;t go down the side streets of the
Internet and definitely don&rsquo;t stray into any dark alleys.  As in real
life, it only leads to trouble.</p>

<h2>Make backups, 3, 2, 1</h2>

<p>That means three copies, two media, one off site.  This may be the
second most important thing you can do, maybe the first.  First, this
is just basic data stewardship.  It&rsquo;s gives you the best chance of not
losing it all.  However, with the recent, dramatic rise in ransom
ware, backups are even more important.  Ransom ware gets into your
computer (e.g., by getting you to click a link in email) and encrypts
all of your files.  Then you have to pay a web site anywhere from $100
to $1000 for a key to unlock your files.  There&rsquo;s no other way to get
them back.  However, if you have a recent enough backup then you can
ignore the ransom ware attackers, wipe your computer clean and
restore your files.</p>

<p>Here is the simplest way to do this.  Buy a second, external USB hard
drive which should cost from $60 to $90, attach it to your computer
and use a program that backs up your files to it nightly.  Then
subscribe to a service like Carbonite or Back Blaze. They both charge
about $5 per month.</p>

<h2>Use Google Chrome</h2>

<p>As Internet browsers go, Chrome is the most secure.  This is proven
often and Chrome was the clear winner at this year&rsquo;s annual &ldquo;Pwn to
own&rdquo;
security contest, as it usually is.  Chrome isn&rsquo;t perfect but it will
help keep you safe.</p>

<h2>Use Gmail</h2>

<p>Gmail is the best email period and it&rsquo;s also very safe and will work
hard to help keep you secure.  It&rsquo;s also not perfect, though, so you
still have to follow all of the other guidelines here.  I&rsquo;ve used
Gmail since it came out in 2004, that&rsquo;s 12 years, and it&rsquo;s sad when I
hear people talk about email problems and issues that I haven&rsquo;t even
thought about for those 12 years.</p>

<h2>Use a password manager</h2>

<p>Maybe the two biggest are LastPass and 1Password.  I personally prefer
LastPass but pretty much everything I say here about LastPass applies
to 1Password as well.  You put all of your passwords into LastPass for
everything you use.  If you install it into your browser, it will log
into sites for you automatically.  Make sure every site has a
<em>different</em> and <em>long</em> password, at least 25 characters, usually with
a mixture of upper case, lower case, numerals, and other special
characters.  Lastpass will make up new passwords for you.  Remember,
you won&rsquo;t be typing in these passwords.  Lastpass will do that for
you.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a good practice to use a different user name for each site and it
can also be a random jumble of letters.  Similarly, if you have to
answer security questions for the site, use a jumble of letters for
that.  In other words, don&rsquo;t put your mother&rsquo;s maiden name as &ldquo;Smith&rdquo;
but enter it as &ldquo;GAStiOnOgyRiVEnDETorpoyaL&rdquo;.  Use different answers
for every site.  Put them in the Notes section of that account on
LastPass.</p>

<p>There is one important thing:  Lastpass (and 1Password) uses a master
password to unlock access by you to the rest of your passwords.  You
should make the master password easy to remember and key in, but also
be absolutely sure to write it down and store it in a non-obvious,
very safe place.</p>

<h2>Never install something you weren&rsquo;t looking for</h2>

<p>This is a rule from Steve Gibson of GRC.com and Security Now.  If you
get a pop up message on your computer that says it&rsquo;s time to install
an update or something else, don&rsquo;t do it.  It could be fine, but don&rsquo;t
take the chance.  This is what we mean by &ldquo;something you weren&rsquo;t
looking for.&rdquo;   Instead of clicking on the popup, go to the actual
application or go to the web site and see if you can find whatever the
popup was talking about there.  Maybe go to your system&rsquo;s app store
and see if there are pending updates there.</p>

<h2>What about virus software?</h2>

<p>Did you notice I didn&rsquo;t mention virus software or anything to remove
adware or malware.  Those days are pretty much over.  The types of
attacks and the real problems usually aren&rsquo;t viruses any more.  If you
have Windows, turn on Microsoft&rsquo;s own, built in virus scanning.  It&rsquo;s
sufficient and free.  You definitely don&rsquo;t need anything scanning your
email or web connections, especially if you use Chrome and Gmail.</p>

<p>I do use ad blocking software, Ghostery on the desktop.  I&rsquo;m not
qualified to recommend which ad blocking software is best right now.
Anyway, ad blocking is more about avoiding browsing nuisances of ads
covering a web page you&rsquo;re trying to read and are not so much a
security matter.</p>

<h2>Next</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ll soon follow up with part 2, Bonus Tips.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
