<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: computing | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/computing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2016-12-20T15:19:32-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[USENIX Computing Systems]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/12/20/usenix-computing-systems/"/>
    <updated>2016-12-20T15:02:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/12/20/usenix-computing-systems</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For many years I received the USENIX &ldquo;Computing Systems&rdquo; journal and
recently, when doing I search, I discovered the entire archive is
on-line.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.usenix.org/publications/compsystems/computing-systems">Computing Systems</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Color Gamut]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/23/color-gamut/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-23T01:06:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/23/color-gamut</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The phrase &ldquo;color gamut&rdquo; has been thrown around a lot lately.  What is
it?  This blog post by Craig Hockenberry explains color gamut.</p>

<blockquote><p>From your point-of-view, the important thing about DCI-P3 is that it
can display a wider range of color. Apple’s promotional literature
states that the new iPad Pro has &ldquo;up to 25% greater color saturation
than previous models.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<!-- More -->


<p><a href="http://blog.iconfactory.com/2016/04/looking-at-the-future/">Looking at the Future</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rowhammer]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/01/rowhammer/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-01T00:18:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/01/rowhammer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Rowhammer is a sophisticated, clever and dangerous way to attack
computers and Android phones.  Dan Goodin reports in <em>Ars Technica.</em></p>

<!-- More -->


<blockquote><p>Researchers have devised an attack that gains unfettered &ldquo;root&rdquo; access
to a large number of Android phones, exploiting a relatively new type
of bug that allows adversaries to manipulate data stored in memory
chips.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://arstechnica.com/security/2016/10/using-rowhammer-bitflips-to-root-android-phones-is-now-a-thing/">Using Rowhammer bitflips to root Android phones is now a thing</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Email Phishing Attack]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/01/email-phishing-attack/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-01T00:10:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/01/email-phishing-attack</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well, in my earlier post on security tips I mentioned links in email.
According to an article in <em>Business Insider</em>, that&rsquo;s exactly how John
Podesta&rsquo;s account was compromised.</p>

<!-- More -->


<blockquote><p>Simply put: Rather than clicking a legitimate link from Google, he
apparently clicked through to a fake website run by hackers. When he
entered his account information, he handed over the keys to his
Gmail.</p></blockquote>

<p>This article by Ben Gilbert goes into some detail about how this was
done.  It was an easy effort by the attacker and could have been
avoided with a bit more care on the part of the user.  He even did the
right thing in reporting it to his IT support but still clicked the
dangerous link in the email.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/hillary-clinton-campaign-john-podesta-got-hacked-by-phishing-2016-10">Hillary Clinton&rsquo;s campaign got hacked by falling for the oldest trick
in the book</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What's going on inside Lithium Ion Batteries?]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/23/whats-going-on-inside-lithium-ion-batteries/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-23T07:32:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/23/whats-going-on-inside-lithium-ion-batteries</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Steve Gibson from Security Now provided two excellent sources this
week explaining what&rsquo;s happening when lithium ion batteries fail.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>From Paul O’Shea, Editor, <em>Power Electronics News</em> interviewing Nadim
Maluf, CEO of Qnovo, and Robert Nalesnik, VP of Marketing for Qnovo.</p>

<blockquote><p>Now, let’s examine one particular manufacturing defect in which a
slight misalignment between the anode and cathode occurs during the
assembly process. The same structure as above now has the anode layer
shifted slightly to the right. At the misaligned edge, the requisite
overlap of the anode relative to the cathode is now diminished or even
possibly eliminated. The anode/cathode ratio at this spot drops below
the requisite limit for ensuring safety. The result is the onset of
lithium metal at this edge. The lithium metal forms on the anode
edge. As the lithium metal grows in size and thickness, it ultimately
punctures the separator and causes an electrical short between the
anode and cathode. Boom! There is a catastrophic failure.</p>

<p>The tolerance requirements in the manufacturing of lithium-ion
batteries have risen sharply with increasing energy density. Short of
using new materials (which still do not exist in commercial
deployment), increasing the energy density means reducing all the
extra space inside the battery that is not made of anode and cathode
materials. These are the only two materials that store energy;
n> everything else is just overhead. They are still needed for other
functions and safety, but they do not contribute to storing electrical
charge. Therefore, battery designers keep reducing this overhead and,
in the process, make the manufacturing tolerances even tighter. That
is a recipe for many disasters to come unless we start adding a lot
more intelligence to the battery to avoid and mitigate these
undesired situations.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.powerelectronicsnews.com/technology/pushing-to-the-very-edge-of-safe-li-ion-charging">Pushing to the very edge of safe Li-ion charging</a><br /></p>

<p>From the Qnovo blog.</p>

<p><a href="http://qnovo.com/104-perils-4-4-volts/">104. The Perils of 4.4 Volts</a><br />
<a href="http://qnovo.com/103-real-science-behind-exploding-batteries/">103. The Real Science Behind Battery Safety</a><br />
<a href="http://qnovo.com/102-easy-not-right-pick-samsung/">102. It’s Easy, but Not Right, to Pick on Samsung</a><br />
<a href="http://qnovo.com/101-making-sense-100-kwh/">101. Making Sense of 100 kWh</a><br />
<a href="http://qnovo.com/100-state-lithium-ion-battery/">100. The State of the Lithium Ion Battery</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
