<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: internet | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/internet/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2017-04-01T06:07:54-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Unreadable Web]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/01/unreadable-web/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-01T00:27:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/01/unreadable-web</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Kevin Marks has written an excellent article on how web pages are
being made very hard to read because it&rsquo;s the in-style thing to do.</p>

<!-- More -->


<blockquote><p>There’s a widespread movement in design circles to reduce the contrast
between text and background, making type harder to read. Apple is
guilty. Google is, too. So is Twitter.</p>

<p>Typography may not seem like a crucial design element, but it is. One
of the reasons the web has become the default way that we access
information is that it makes that information broadly available to
everyone. “The power of the Web is in its universality,” wrote Tim
Berners-Lee, director of the World Wide Web consortium. “Access by
everyone regardless of disability is an essential aspect.”</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="https://backchannel.com/how-the-web-became-unreadable-a781ddc711b6#.70urt9e64">How the Web Became Unreadable</a><br/></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DOS IOT Botnet Attack]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/01/dos-iot-botnet-attack/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-01T00:22:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/01/dos-iot-botnet-attack</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There&rsquo;s been a lot of discussion about the insecurity of the internet
of things (IOT) devices such as security cameras, DVRs, thermostats
and more.  Frankly, many of these are Linux systems that are poorly
prepared from a security standpoint and sometimes blatantly exposed.
Such devices were used in the recent, massive attacks against the DNS
service.</p>

<!-- More -->


<blockquote><p>&ldquo;We&rsquo;re seeing attacks coming from a number of different locations,&rdquo;
Drew said. &ldquo;An Internet of Things botnet called Mirai that we
identified is also involved in the attack.&rdquo;</p>

<p>The botnet, made up of devices like home Wi-Fi routers and Internet
protocol video cameras, is sending massive numbers of requests to
Dyn&rsquo;s DNS service. Those requests look legitimate, so it&rsquo;s difficult
for Dyn&rsquo;s systems to screen them out from normal domain name lookup
requests.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://arstechnica.com/security/2016/10/double-dip-internet-of-things-botnet-attack-felt-across-the-internet/">Double-dip Internet-of-Things botnet attack felt across the Internet</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Email Phishing Attack]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/01/email-phishing-attack/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-01T00:10:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/11/01/email-phishing-attack</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well, in my earlier post on security tips I mentioned links in email.
According to an article in <em>Business Insider</em>, that&rsquo;s exactly how John
Podesta&rsquo;s account was compromised.</p>

<!-- More -->


<blockquote><p>Simply put: Rather than clicking a legitimate link from Google, he
apparently clicked through to a fake website run by hackers. When he
entered his account information, he handed over the keys to his
Gmail.</p></blockquote>

<p>This article by Ben Gilbert goes into some detail about how this was
done.  It was an easy effort by the attacker and could have been
avoided with a bit more care on the part of the user.  He even did the
right thing in reporting it to his IT support but still clicked the
dangerous link in the email.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/hillary-clinton-campaign-john-podesta-got-hacked-by-phishing-2016-10">Hillary Clinton&rsquo;s campaign got hacked by falling for the oldest trick
in the book</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[So Long Leo Beranek]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/23/so-long-leo-beranek/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-23T06:54:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/23/so-long-leo-beranek</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&ldquo;Leo Leroy Beranek (September 15, 1914 – October 10, 2016) was an
American acoustics expert, former MIT professor, and a founder and
former president of Bolt, Beranek and Newman (now BBN Technologies).&rdquo;
from Wikipedia.</p>

<!-- More -->


<blockquote><p>In 1969, the company he helped found, Bolt, Beranek &amp; Newman, won a
contract from the Defense Department’s Advanced Research Projects
Agency to build the first computer-based network, which came to be
called Arpanet.</p>

<p>By demonstrating the ability to share data and messages through vast
computer networks, Arpanet, a product of government-sponsored
research, paved the way for the creation of the internet. Among its
many breakthrough achievements, his company sent the first email
message that used the @ symbol, in 1972.</p></blockquote>

<p>from The New York Times article &ldquo;Leo Beranek, Acoustics Designer and
Internet Pioneer, Dies at 102&rdquo; by Glenn Rifkin, The New York Times, 2016-10-17.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2016/10/18/business/leo-beranek-dead.html">Leo Beranek, Acoustics Designer and Internet Pioneer, Dies at 102</a><br />
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BBN_Technologies">BBN Technologies</a><br />
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ARPANET">ARPANET</a><br />
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_the_Internet">History of the Internet</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Security Basics]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/16/security-tips/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-16T15:40:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/16/security-tips</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The information world is a dangerous place these days.  You can lose
everything in an instant.  There&rsquo;s more at stake.  The biggest one is
probably your personal and family pictures.  The next is personal
financial and other important information, documents, etc.  I don&rsquo;t
know if it&rsquo;s any more dangerous but more of us have more important
information stored on our computers and other devices.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s my own list of the basics.  There&rsquo;s nothing original here.  You
should hear about the same thing from any security or IT professional.</p>

<!-- More -->


<h2>Summary</h2>

<ul>
<li>Don&rsquo;t open links and attachments in email, messages</li>
<li>Keep systems and apps, everything, updated</li>
<li>Keep Internet browsing on Main Street</li>
<li>Make backups, 3, 2, 1 (three copies, two media, one off site)</li>
<li>Use Google Chrome</li>
<li>Use Gmail</li>
<li>Use a password manager like LastPass or 1Password</li>
<li>Never install something you weren&rsquo;t looking for</li>
</ul>


<h2>The Basics</h2>

<h3>Don&rsquo;t open links and attachments in email, messages</h3>

<p>This is one of the biggest threats today.  You click a link and
download an attachment and you&rsquo;ve given malware, an attacking computer
program, access to <em>your</em> computer.  Fortunately most of our systems
today are secure enough that they can&rsquo;t be compromised unless you take
the action yourself so the game is to trick you into running the
evil code.  Sending you email that looks like a legitimate, important
message from your bank or the IRS, or maybe telling you you&rsquo;ve won
something or have an important message, maybe an unpaid bill.</p>

<p>If the message is from a bank or some institution or business, see if
you can get to the same information by going to their web site on your
own, not by clicking in the email, and finding what they&rsquo;re talking
about.  If nothing else, call them.</p>

<p>If it&rsquo;s from a family member, text them or call them and ask if they
sent it to you and if they&rsquo;re sure it&rsquo;s okay.</p>

<p>Many of the largest company security breaches in recent news have been
the result of finally tricking an employee to click on something in an
email message.</p>

<h3>Keep systems and apps, everything, updated</h3>

<p>All software and, in fact, most hardware, is updated regularly.  These
updates are important.  Many people are working hard to find and fix
bugs that could expose you to attack.   On Windows, Mac OS, and Linux,
you should turn on automatic updates so your system is updated on a
regular basis.</p>

<h3>Keep Internet browsing on Main Street</h3>

<p>This means stick to well known and reputable sites: people,
businesses, destinations.  Don&rsquo;t go down the side streets of the
Internet and definitely don&rsquo;t stray into any dark alleys.  As in real
life, it only leads to trouble.</p>

<h2>Make backups, 3, 2, 1</h2>

<p>That means three copies, two media, one off site.  This may be the
second most important thing you can do, maybe the first.  First, this
is just basic data stewardship.  It&rsquo;s gives you the best chance of not
losing it all.  However, with the recent, dramatic rise in ransom
ware, backups are even more important.  Ransom ware gets into your
computer (e.g., by getting you to click a link in email) and encrypts
all of your files.  Then you have to pay a web site anywhere from $100
to $1000 for a key to unlock your files.  There&rsquo;s no other way to get
them back.  However, if you have a recent enough backup then you can
ignore the ransom ware attackers, wipe your computer clean and
restore your files.</p>

<p>Here is the simplest way to do this.  Buy a second, external USB hard
drive which should cost from $60 to $90, attach it to your computer
and use a program that backs up your files to it nightly.  Then
subscribe to a service like Carbonite or Back Blaze. They both charge
about $5 per month.</p>

<h2>Use Google Chrome</h2>

<p>As Internet browsers go, Chrome is the most secure.  This is proven
often and Chrome was the clear winner at this year&rsquo;s annual &ldquo;Pwn to
own&rdquo;
security contest, as it usually is.  Chrome isn&rsquo;t perfect but it will
help keep you safe.</p>

<h2>Use Gmail</h2>

<p>Gmail is the best email period and it&rsquo;s also very safe and will work
hard to help keep you secure.  It&rsquo;s also not perfect, though, so you
still have to follow all of the other guidelines here.  I&rsquo;ve used
Gmail since it came out in 2004, that&rsquo;s 12 years, and it&rsquo;s sad when I
hear people talk about email problems and issues that I haven&rsquo;t even
thought about for those 12 years.</p>

<h2>Use a password manager</h2>

<p>Maybe the two biggest are LastPass and 1Password.  I personally prefer
LastPass but pretty much everything I say here about LastPass applies
to 1Password as well.  You put all of your passwords into LastPass for
everything you use.  If you install it into your browser, it will log
into sites for you automatically.  Make sure every site has a
<em>different</em> and <em>long</em> password, at least 25 characters, usually with
a mixture of upper case, lower case, numerals, and other special
characters.  Lastpass will make up new passwords for you.  Remember,
you won&rsquo;t be typing in these passwords.  Lastpass will do that for
you.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a good practice to use a different user name for each site and it
can also be a random jumble of letters.  Similarly, if you have to
answer security questions for the site, use a jumble of letters for
that.  In other words, don&rsquo;t put your mother&rsquo;s maiden name as &ldquo;Smith&rdquo;
but enter it as &ldquo;GAStiOnOgyRiVEnDETorpoyaL&rdquo;.  Use different answers
for every site.  Put them in the Notes section of that account on
LastPass.</p>

<p>There is one important thing:  Lastpass (and 1Password) uses a master
password to unlock access by you to the rest of your passwords.  You
should make the master password easy to remember and key in, but also
be absolutely sure to write it down and store it in a non-obvious,
very safe place.</p>

<h2>Never install something you weren&rsquo;t looking for</h2>

<p>This is a rule from Steve Gibson of GRC.com and Security Now.  If you
get a pop up message on your computer that says it&rsquo;s time to install
an update or something else, don&rsquo;t do it.  It could be fine, but don&rsquo;t
take the chance.  This is what we mean by &ldquo;something you weren&rsquo;t
looking for.&rdquo;   Instead of clicking on the popup, go to the actual
application or go to the web site and see if you can find whatever the
popup was talking about there.  Maybe go to your system&rsquo;s app store
and see if there are pending updates there.</p>

<h2>What about virus software?</h2>

<p>Did you notice I didn&rsquo;t mention virus software or anything to remove
adware or malware.  Those days are pretty much over.  The types of
attacks and the real problems usually aren&rsquo;t viruses any more.  If you
have Windows, turn on Microsoft&rsquo;s own, built in virus scanning.  It&rsquo;s
sufficient and free.  You definitely don&rsquo;t need anything scanning your
email or web connections, especially if you use Chrome and Gmail.</p>

<p>I do use ad blocking software, Ghostery on the desktop.  I&rsquo;m not
qualified to recommend which ad blocking software is best right now.
Anyway, ad blocking is more about avoiding browsing nuisances of ads
covering a web page you&rsquo;re trying to read and are not so much a
security matter.</p>

<h2>Next</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ll soon follow up with part 2, Bonus Tips.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
