<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: internet | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/internet/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2016-02-21T08:22:51-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tuning Facebook]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/02/06/tuning-facebook/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-06T12:29:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/02/06/tuning-facebook</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Okay, I&rsquo;ve decided to try using the dreaded Facebook a little more,
particularly after hearing all of the talk about instant articles in
news and more people using Messenger. I knew about this podcast of
Robert Scoble (who&rsquo;s all in on Facebook) trying to teach Leo Laporte
how to use it back in August but had never gotten around to checking
it out.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>If you want to learn how to &ldquo;really use&rdquo; Facebook in it&rsquo;s current
form, I recommend watching it and even working through this stuff.</p>

<p>So, starting around about 2016-01-30, I&rsquo;ve been trying most of what
they discuss there over the past few days and I am seeing my FB
experience much improved. There&rsquo;s a lot you can do to fine tune and
control things. I&rsquo;ll see how the news feeds compare to my Twitter
feed, etc.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=U53iO3b1K-c">Triangulation 169: Robert Scoble&rsquo;s Facebook Lesson</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Indie Web]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/17/indie-web/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-17T08:22:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/17/indie-web</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since I first began the 30-day blogging challenge the indie web
movement was on my list of topics to discus.  My thinking on
it, and related topics, is still unsettled.  I&rsquo;ve read some and, well,
read some more.  Kevin Marks frequently appears on the Twit network
and particularly on <em>This Week in Google</em>, and has talked about the
indie web on many occasions.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a brief and early poll on where I am so far.  I like the basic
principle of owning all of your content.  That&rsquo;s the foundation of
this very site, this blog.  I don&rsquo;t like strongly coupling my various
identities across sites, not that strongly.  I prefer that they be
weakly coupled, if at all.  I&rsquo;m not that interested in discussions,
engagement and feedback.  At least not in the usual way they occur on
the web.</p>

<p>Microformats comprise a clever and intriguing idea.  I think there&rsquo;s value
in this evolved approach to (this part of) the so-called semantic
web.</p>

<p>The microformats movement has eschewed email and gone to using IRC
(Internet Relay Chat) and a wiki for their communication.  This hits
at the communication problems that I spend a lot of my
internet-thinking time on.  Email seems terribly inadequate in many
ways and yet insists being the best fit for many needs, particularly
when Gmail is used.  I agree with not using email for long messages or
long documents&mdash;I&rsquo;ve adopted a similar approach to communication.
(For long documents and messages I email a Google document instead of
a long email message).</p>

<p>I loathe using IRC.  That in itself is worth at least one long blog
post.  We use it at work since I&rsquo;ve been unable to stave off the push
by the millennials (plus or minus) there to use IRC.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s a very nice &ldquo;indie web in a box,&rdquo; With Known, which you can
even get a hosted account with.  At first, that seems anti-indie-web,
but it&rsquo;s all very well done.  The source is open and you can start on
their servers then move onto your own when you wish, similar to using
Wordpress.</p>

<p>So that&rsquo;s a quick update.  There should be more to come.</p>

<p><a href="http://indiewebcamp.com/">Indie Web Camp</a><br />
<a href="http://microformats.org/">Microformats</a><br />
<a href="http://www.kevinmarks.com/">Kevin Marks</a><br />
<a href="http://twit.tv/">Twit.tv</a><br />
<a href="https://withknown.com/">Known</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A History of the Internet]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/01/a-history-of-the-internet/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-01T08:19:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/01/a-history-of-the-internet</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/NSFNET-backbone-T3.png"></p>

<p><a href="http://www.inetdaemon.com/tutorials/internet/history.shtml">History of the Internet</a> at InetDaemon.com is a brief and nice account of how the Internet
began.</p>

<p><em>Image credit: CC BY-SA 3.0 Merit Network, Inc.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
