<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: octopress | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/octopress/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2014-10-24T09:09:12-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Octopress After 512 Days]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/12/octopress-after-512-days/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-12T23:10:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/10/12/octopress-after-512-days</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Day 2</p>

<p>Well, I was supposed to report back in on how it&rsquo;s been going with
Octopress after using it a while.  It&rsquo;s now been 512 days, or one year
and 147 days, or about 17 months which is about one year and five
months.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s basically been going okay.  The process isn&rsquo;t bad.  I put up
posts now and then with varying frequency.  Some are &ldquo;full&rdquo; posts with
picture and permission, some are occasionally long, and some are
short, ~tweet-length updates.</p>

<p>I like Octopress a lot.  The best part is writing in Markdown which
means my source files are all plain text and I have a copy of all of
them, so the blog is already in my possession and easily read without
any software or publishing.</p>

<p>The Octopress scripts are easy to use.  Right now I run a new_post
command to create a file, edit the file with Emacs, then re-generate
the blog and finally push the changes up to Github which is where I
publish it.</p>

<p>Adding an image is hardly more difficult than it was with Blogger.  I
have to download the image and get it into the machine I&rsquo;m writing
on.  Then it&rsquo;s just copying the image to a source directory in the
blog tree and adding one line to the Markdown file.</p>

<p>Yesterday, on Saturday I wrote the beginning of a Python script to
automate running those commands.  So far it handles it all up to
running Emacs on the created file.  Next will come updating the git
repo locally then pushing up the changes.</p>

<p>The biggest down side at the moment is that the archives are organized
in the single page view by date and year, but they aren&rsquo;t physically
organized in the real file tree.  Also there&rsquo;s no way to segment the
blog into archive pieces.  Generate, I think, rebuilds the whole site
basically and, as the site grows, it&rsquo;s taking a while to do a generate
now.  Okay, it takes 25 seconds but it seems like a long while.</p>

<p>As the archive grows to be years long, I believe it will become a big
unweildy.  It would be better if there was a way to segment off pieces
of the archive, e.g., each year, so you don&rsquo;t end up regenerating it
all every time.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m actually pretty sure there is a way to do this, I&rsquo;ll just have to
dig it up when there&rsquo;s time.</p>

<p>See <a href="/blog/2013/06/08/leaping-to-a-new-blogging-platform/">Leaping to a New Blogging Platform</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
