<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: tv | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/tv/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2015-03-23T08:58:19-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thirty Years Since We Watched Voyager on TV]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/09/14/thirty-years-since-voyager/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-14T08:42:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/09/14/thirty-years-since-voyager</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/20130914_saturn.jpg"></p>

<p><em>[This is a re-post of a blog post I first wrote and posted in
 2010-11-12 in <a href="http://monolith149daily.blogspot.com/2010/11/thirty-years-since-we-watched-voyager.html">Monolith149 Daily</a>.
 I&rsquo;ve made some slight edits to the text.]</em></p>

<p>I was the director of the planetarium at the time and had received a
letter from NASA that they were broadcasting live coverage of the
Voyager 1 encounter via satellite.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>When I was a kid, reading library books about the solar system, there
would often be a chapter at the end of the book on the Grand Tour of
the Planets.  A favorable alignment of the four gas giants, Jupiter,
Saturn, Uranus and Neptune, would allow a single spacecraft to visit
each of them using gravitational assist, in the distant future of the
1980s.</p>

<p>Fast-forward to 1977, either 5 Sep 1977 (Voyager 2) or 20 Aug 1977
(Voyager 1), I forget which.* It&rsquo;s morning and I&rsquo;m lying on the sofa
after being at the museum&rsquo;s observatory all night.  I&rsquo;m watching the
Voyager spacecraft launch on TV.  With those launches, the Grand Tour
became a reality and Voyager 2 visited all four planets.</p>

<p>However, it was Voyager 1 that visited Jupiter and Saturn first.  The
spacecraft stole some of Jupiter&rsquo;s orbital momentum, causing Jupiter
to fall just a little bit toward the sun, as it accelerated on to
Saturn</p>

<p>The event was going to happen on 12 Nov 1980.  There was no NASA
channel at the time so I had to call the local cable operator (Cox)
and ask them to tune into the particular satellite and transponder
that NASA had arranged and to feed the coverage out over a spare
channel on their cable plant.  It took some convincing since they were
reluctant to actually commit a channel, even for a one-time event.  In
the end, I think I ended up talking to a guy in a control shack,
probably running their dish farm, who impressed me as not wanting to
be bothered with events from other planets.  My memory is that I never
got an absolute firm commitment but something more like a shaky okay
which was more than a little worrisome.</p>

<p>Next, it was necessary to find a video tape recorder and it turned out
there was one I could borrow from the board of education.  I drove
down to their dusty equipment warehouse to pick it up.  Or maybe it
was just the road by the warehouse that was dusty.  It was an old
&frac34;-inch U-Matic machine, a video cassette size frequently used
by TV stations in those days.  The &frac12;-in cassettes were just starting
to become popular as the VHS vs. Betamax battle was raging.</p>

<p>We hauled the recorder over to the house of one of our staff members'
parents to record the coverage since they had cable.  The encounter
was in the middle of the day and several of the planetarium staff were
crowded into their den, watching the show.</p>

<p>It was a heady time indeed as we watched those black and white
pictures scroll slowly in because the data download rates from the
space probe were slower than the modems of the time.  Of course they
were not digitally post-processed yet&mdash;they were pretty raw
images&mdash;so there were just the beginning hints of some of the amazing
sites to come.  The coverage cameras showed ecstatic scientists
watching the same images appear on their control room monitors and
there were several interviews with Ed Stone, Carl Sagan and others who
were seeing their own life-long fantasies come true.</p>

<p>Sometimes you suddenly arrive at those moments when you get goosebumps
and a lump in your throat, when you know you&rsquo;re experiencing pinnacle
achievements in human history.  This was one of them.</p>

<p>As the pictures crawled in, I believe it was possible, even in those
first images, to see the spokes in the rings, the braided F-ring, and
some of the other jaw-dropping, never-imagined features of Saturn
up-close.</p>

<p>After recording the fly-by, we borrowed a TV from one of the local TV
shops.  It was just a standard 19-in, or slightly larger, CRT.  We set
it up in the planetarium and opened to the public for a replay of the
&ldquo;live&rdquo; Voyager-Saturn encounter.  I remember we had a bit of
difficulty because the video tape recorder had a separate RF
modulator, the size of a small, chunky game cartridge, that had to be
physically plugged into the back of the machine before we could get a
signal to the TV.</p>

<p>I guess we had enough lead time to advertise the event using the usual
TV and newspaper avenues because there was a pretty good turnout.
There were college professors, amateur astronomers and many other
enthusiastic folks from the community who were just as thrilled
as the crew at JPL to see these first images coming back from the
ringed planet, even though our replay was delayed by hours.</p>

<p>As I recall there were encounter events over two or three days as
Voyager flew by some of Saturn&rsquo;s moons and made its way across
Saturn&rsquo;s &ldquo;miniature solar system,&rdquo; so we had probably two and possibly
three nights of replay.</p>

<p>Today Voyager 1 is over 115 AU (astronomical units) from the Sun.  By
definition, the Earth is 1 AU from the Sun.  Pluto is, on average, about 40
AU distant.  Voyager 1 is the most distant, active spacecraft in the solar
system and it&rsquo;s still collecting and transmitting data.</p>

<p>&ldquo;In four to six years, Voyager 1 is expected to cross beyond the
heliosheath, the outer layer of the bubble around our solar system
that is composed of ionized atoms streaming outward from our sun,&rdquo;
reports a news release from NASA this past October [2010].</p>

<p>We&rsquo;ve come a long way from those solar system books from the library,
written in days when artists never even thought to include clouds when
illustrating the Earth as seen from space.  I&rsquo;ve been amazed to see so
many of those funny but always awe-inspiring artist&rsquo;s conceptions come
to reality.  It will be fascinating to see which ones come next.</p>

<p align="center">
*&nbsp;*&nbsp;*
</p>


<p>It was just past the turn of the century and I&rsquo;d never thought about
it before even after a couple of years or so.  It was a friend who
pointed out to me that the two vehicles sitting in our driveway were a
Voyager and a Saturn.</p>

<p>__________<br>
* No that&rsquo;s not a typo.  Due to the solar system and mission mechanics
involved, Voyager 2 was actually launched before Voyager 1.</p>

<p><em>Image Credit</em></p>

<p><em>Ghostly Spokes in the Rings</em></p>

<p><em>Scientists first saw these somewhat wedge-shaped, transient clouds of tiny particles known as “spokes” in images from NASA&rsquo;s Voyager spacecraft. They dubbed these features in Saturn&rsquo;s B ring “spokes” because they looked like bicycle spokes. An electrostatic charge, the way static electricity on Earth can raise the hair on your arms, appears to be levitating tiny ring particles above the ring plane, but scientists are still figuring out how the particles get that charge as they analyze images from NASA&rsquo;s Cassini spacecraft.</em></p>

<p><em>The image on the left was obtained by Voyager 2 on Aug. 22, 1981. The
image on the right was obtained by Cassini on Nov. 2, 2008.</em></p>

<p><em>Image credit: NASA/JPL and NASA/JPL/SSI</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[3D TV]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/06/18/3d-tv/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-18T05:15:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/06/18/3d-tv</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/20130618_3dtv.jpg" title="" ></p>

<p>Since it actually became a reality of sorts, I&rsquo;ve neither been
fanatical about nor enthusiastic for 3D TV.  I&rsquo;m not sure why.  After
all, it&rsquo;s been a wonderful orb set to rise on the future horizon for a
long time.  Now it&rsquo;s just one more thing that sits somewhere between
yawn-inducing boredom and outright annoyance.</p>

<p>The annoying part is demonstrated by 3D movies.<!-- more -->  I&rsquo;ve discovered in
more than one case that 3D can actually ruin a cinema outing.  Now I
avoid 3D movies.  In fact, I&rsquo;ve announced that I won&rsquo;t go to them any
more.</p>

<p><em>Avatar</em> was a beautiful movie.  I saw it in 3D IMAX and enjoyed every
bit of it.  But <em>TRON:Legacy</em> was a disaster in my 3D IMAX experience.
I liked the movie well enough, but there were weird reflections in the
3D glasses from the white light on black uniforms.  And sometimes I
couldn&rsquo;t tell which parts of the movie were the intentional 2D scenes
vs. the 3D scenes.  I&rsquo;d already given up on 3D movies once before but
I gave this one a shot based on a recommendation.  I don&rsquo;t intend to
make that mistake again soon.</p>

<p>What I do enjoy at the theatre is higher resolution. Those new digital
projection systems are wonderful!</p>

<p>I also like watching movies on HDTV and I expect that 4K TV will be
wondefully compelling.</p>

<p>It reminds me of an article I read some years ago about computer
screen resolution.  The technology was headed toward higher and higher
resolution displays but the author pointed out that color resolution,
lots more colors, was much more important to our eyes than spatial
resolution.  It&rsquo;s true. If you put a high-resolution screen beside a
lower-resolution but more-colors screen, you&rsquo;ll prefer the more
subtle, richer colors over the higher res.</p>

<p>Just like there&rsquo;s a place for written text, and there&rsquo;s certainly a
place for 2D images <em>that aren&rsquo;t moving</em>, there will always be a place
for 2D movies.</p>

<p>Yet, some day some inventor will get it just right and create a 3D
experience you have to go out and buy.  For now, I wonder if we&rsquo;ll
advance effect of immersion too far.  I don&rsquo;t want to walk in a room
at my house and have to grab a light sabre to fight for my life!
Sometimes I just want to sit down and watch TV.</p>

<h2>See also</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/06/17/business/media/future-of-3-d-tv-murky-as-espn-ends-channel.html">Future of 3-D TV Murky as ESPN Ends Channel</a>
by Brian Stelter at the New York Times.</p>

<p>Via
<a href="https://twitter.com/mediagazer/status/346901541212520449">@mediagazer</a></p>

<p><em>Image credit: <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/davidberkowitz/4260784467/">David Berkowitz on Flickr</a>.  CC by 2.0.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A long time ago on Sesame Street]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/06/08/sesame-street-original-cast/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-08T11:29:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2013/06/08/sesame-street-original-cast</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Retweet from <a href="https://twitter.com/GuyKawasaki/status/343388340759977984">@GuyKawasaki</a></p>

<p><a href="http://holykaw.alltop.com/a-long-time-ago-on-sesame-street-photo-of-the-original-cast-video?tu3=1">Photo of the original cast</a> [video]</p>

<p>I was sort of past &ldquo;kid&rdquo; when Sesame Street began, but some folks may
enjoy this nostalgia.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
