<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: telescope | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/telescope/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2016-09-30T18:15:26-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Buying a Telescope - Part 2b]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/03/buying-a-telescope-part-2b/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-03T06:27:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/03/buying-a-telescope-part-2b</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/blog/2014/10/11/blogging-for-30-days/">Day 24</a></p>

<p>Recommendations continued.</p>

<h2>Binoculars</h2>

<p>The first recommendation is always binoculars.   They are two
telescopes instead of one.  They are the most portable telescopes you
can get and you get two, one for each eye.</p>

<p>The investment is around $100.  It&rsquo;s a good investment because,
regardless of how serious you become as an astronomer, you always have
a need for binoculars.  There are some objects that don&rsquo;t look as good
in a telescope.  A total lunar eclipse is an example.  When I was a
serious deep sky observer, I often found objects or at least the stars
surrounding their location using binoculars.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>Finally, if you decide you don&rsquo;t enjoy astronomy that much, instead of
binoculars getting forgotten in a closet, they are always useful for
things like concerts, sporting events, and nature viewing.</p>

<p>The ideal binocular size for astronomy is 7x50 or 10x50.  That means
the magnification is 7x or 10x and the aperture is 50-mm.  The
aperture divided by the magnification is the diameter of the exit
pupil and having an exit pupil near the size of the dilated pupils of
your dark-adapted eyes is the goal.  The 7mm to 5mm exit pupil sizes
fit the dilated pupil size of young and middle-aged adults fairly
well. Our eyes dilate less as we age.</p>

<p>The binocular should also have a tripod mounting point, usually a hole
in the middle tapped for a &frac14;-20 screw.  You can then buy a binocular
tripod adapter to attach them to a camera tripod.  You can make an
adapter for the cost of a few cents at a hardware store with a &frac14;-20
bolt and nut or two, and a small angle bracket.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve had a pair of Orion Scenix 7x50 binoculars for quite a few years
and I&rsquo;ve been quite happy with them.  They aren&rsquo;t the highest
precision or quality binoculars but they are well-made and do the job
pretty well for my own observing.</p>

<p><a href="http://telescope.com/">Orion telescope.com</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
