<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: solarsystem | Monolith149 Daily]]></title>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/categories/solarsystem/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//"/>
  <updated>2017-02-06T07:33:20-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Guyton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[CisLunar 1000]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/17/cislunar-1000/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-17T04:35:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/17/cislunar-1000</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There&rsquo;s been a lot of talk about space exploration and development.
Here&rsquo;s a slightly more practical sounding vision from the United
Launch Alliance (ULA).</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>If you&rsquo;re not familiar with ULA, it&rsquo;s &ldquo;a
joint venture of Lockheed Martin Space Systems and Boeing Defense,
Space &amp; Security. ULA was formed in December 2006 by combining the
teams at these companies which provide spacecraft launch services to
the government of the United States. U.S. government launch customers
include both the Department of Defense and NASA, as well as other
organizations. With ULA, Lockheed and Boeing held a monopoly on
military launches for more than a decade, until the US Air Force
awarded a GPS satellite contract to SpaceX in 2016.&rdquo;  That&rsquo;s a quote
from Wikipedia.</p>

<p>With all of the talk lately about going to Mars, particularly after
Elon Musk&rsquo;s recent presentation of his Life to Mars vision, I&rsquo;ve been
giving some thought to what I really think about space travel in the
near future.  I&rsquo;ll write that up soon.  In the mean time, this
video seems to ring a bit more in tune with my off the cuff, poorly
informed, guesses.</p>

<p><a href="https://youtu.be/uxftPmpt7aA">ULA Innovation: CisLunar-1000</a></p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_Launch_Alliance">United Launch Alliance</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Japanese Pictures from the Moon]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/13/japanese-pictures-from-the-moon/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-13T07:28:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/13/japanese-pictures-from-the-moon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&ldquo;Japan just released high-resolution pictures from its Kaguya orbiter,
including some that have never been seen before by the public.&rdquo;</p>

<p>From Victoria Jaggard, National Georgraphic.</p>

<!-- More -->


<blockquote><p>The Kaguya (Selene) lunar orbiter, a Japanese spacecraft nicknamed
after a legendary moon princess, launched in 2007 carrying two
high-definition TV cameras, which it used to capture stunning video
and pictures of the lunar surface.</p>

<p>Although the mission ended in 2009, this week the Japanese space
agency released the entire haul of digital images captured by Kaguya
during its lifetime. Some of the images have never been seen before by
the public.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://news.nationalgeographic.com/2016/10/moon-earth-pictures-japan-kaguya-hdtv-space-science/">Haunting Pictures Show Earth Rising Over the Moon</a><br />
<a href="http://www.darts.isas.jaxa.jp/planet/project/selene/hdtv/index.html.en">Kaguya HDTV Data Publication System</a><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Dwarf Planet 2014 UZ224]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/13/new-dwarf-planet-2014-uz224/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-13T05:54:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2016/10/13/new-dwarf-planet-2014-uz224</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A new trans-Neptunian object 2014 UZ224 has been annouced by the
discoverers.  It&rsquo;s orbit has a semi-major axis of 109 AU with a
current distance of 93 AU in the scattered disc.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>Calla Cofield reports in Space.com,</p>

<blockquote><p>The dwarf planet, called 2014 UZ224, measures about 330 miles (530
kilometers) across and is located about 8.5 billion miles (13.7
billion km) from the sun, NPR reported today (Oct. 11). For
comparison, Pluto&rsquo;s largest moon, Charon, is about 750 miles (1,200
km) in diameter, and reaches a maximum distance of about 4.5 billion
miles (7.3 billion km) from the sun.</p>

<p>A year on 2014 UZ224 (the time it takes the dwarf planet to orbit the
sun) is about 1,100 Earth years. One Pluto year &hellip; is about 248
Earth years.</p></blockquote>

<p>The object was discovered using the Dark Energy Camera.</p>

<blockquote><p>A project called the Dark Energy Survey is using observations from the
DECam to create a map of the universe that provides information
relevant to the study of dark energy. The DES maps have already been
used to study dark matter (which makes up about eighty percent of all
the mass in the universe but whose exact nature is still a mystery)
and to find previously unidentified objects.</p>

<p>Part of the DES includes taking images of a few small patches of the
sky &ldquo;roughly&rdquo; once per week, according to the mission website, and
that&rsquo;s what made this new discovery possible.</p></blockquote>

<p>The interesting part of this article tells how undergraduate students
made the discovery by analyzing data with software they wrote.</p>

<p>Once again there&rsquo;s a minor crisis in naming.</p>

<blockquote><p>The smallest object in the solar system that has earned the title of
&ldquo;dwarf planet&rdquo; (prior to this new discovery) is Ceres, which lies in
the asteroid belt between Jupiter and Mars. Ceres is 590 miles (950
km) across. The object 2014 UZ224 might be too small to be considered
a dwarf planet, Gerdes told NPR, but that will have to be decided by
the International Astronomical Union (which made the controversial
decision to demote Pluto to a dwarf planet). There are four other
recognized dwarf planets in the solar system, but scientists think
there could be dozens — or even more than 100 — objects that size that
have yet to be discovered, according to NASA.</p></blockquote>

<h2>Distances</h2>

<p>I like it&rsquo;s easiest to think of solar system distances in terms of
light travel time from the sun.  It takes sunlight about eight minutes
to reach the Earth from the Sun.  It&rsquo;s 43 minutes to Jupiter, over
five hours to Pluto on average, and 15 hours to UZ224.</p>

<p>The chart below is based on the semi-major axis of each orbit which
you can think of as the average of the maximum and minimum distances
from the Sun.</p>

<pre><code>Earth     1.0 AU =      8.3 min
Jupiter   5.2 AU =     43   min
Neptune  30   AU =   4h10m
Pluto    39   AU =   5h25m
UZ224   109   AU =  15h08m
</code></pre>

<h2>References</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.space.com/34358-new-dwarf-planet-found-2014-uz224.html">New Dwarf Planet Found in Our Solar System &ndash; Space.com</a><br />
<a href="http://www.minorplanetcenter.net/mpec/K16/K16TA4.html">Minor Planet Electronic Circular 2016-T104</a><br />
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scattered_disc">Scattered disc</a><br />
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trans-Neptunian_object">Trans-Neptunian object</a><br />
<a href="http://www.ctio.noao.edu/noao/node/1033">Dark Energy Camera</a><br />
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2014_UZ224">2014 UZ224 on Wikipedia</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[So Long Walter H. Haas]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/04/18/so-long-walter-h-haas/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-18T15:11:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2015/04/18/so-long-walter-h-haas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>Haas devoted his entire life to the study of the Moon and planets.</p></blockquote>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>At a time when professional astronomers held little regard for amateur
observers beyond their meteor and variable-star reports, Haas changed
the paradigm. First, he published (in 1938, at age 21) his in-depth
observations of brightness changes around major lunar craters. Then,
four years later, he followed with a four-part, 76-page opus titled
&ldquo;Does Anything Ever Happen on the Moon?&rdquo; that appeared in the Journal
of the Royal Astronomical Society of Canada. These became the opening
salvo in a lifelong quest &ldquo;to arouse interest in a neglected branch of
astronomy.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>On March 1, 1947, while still at UNM, he dispatched a self-produced
6-page newsletter titled The Strolling Astronomer. Haas already
envisioned this simple missive becoming something bigger: it was
subtitled &ldquo;Association of Lunar and Planetary Observers&rdquo; and branded
with &ldquo;Volume 1, Number 1.&rdquo; By the second issue, a month later, the
budding ALPO had grown to 41 members. Within six years, the
association boasted 350 members from all around the world.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.skyandtelescope.com/astronomy-news/walter-haas-1917-2015-04072015/">Walter H. Haas (1917–2015) by Kelly Beatty</a><br /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.alpo-astronomy.org/">ALPO</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ray Bradbury - If Only We Had Taller Been]]></title>
    <link href="http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/12/ray-bradbury/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-12T23:31:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kmggh.github.io/m149daily-blog//blog/2014/11/12/ray-bradbury</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/postimages/ray_bradbury.png" title="" ></p>

<p>On 12 November 1971, exactly 43 years ago, Ray Bradbury spoke to an
audience at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory on the eve of Mariner 9
arriving at Mars.  On stage with him were Arthur C. Clarke, Carl
Sagan, Bruce Murray, and Walter Sullivan.  Bradbury read his poem, &ldquo;If
Only We Had Taller Been.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Today, on 12 November 2014, the Philae spacecraft &ldquo;docked&rdquo; with the
comet 67P/Churyumov-Gerasimenko.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EBtZjbTDTDk">Youtube Video &ndash; Ray Bradbury &ndash; If Only We Had Taller Been</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
